[MUSIC]
Welcome to this lecture of the course on
Process Mining Data Science in Action.
In this fourth lecture,
on conformance checking we continue to
focus on token-based replay,
as a means to diagnose and
quantify discrepancies,
between modeled and observed behavior.
In the last lecture,
we introduced a notion of
token-based replay as a means
to do conformance checking.
In this lecture we will
focus on several examples,
showing this conformance
checking technique in action.
This was one of the examples
that we saw before,
given this one log containing
almost 1,400 cases.
We checked the conformance with
respect to four different models.
The first model and
the last model had a perfect fitness.
The two other models showed that therer were
differences between the log and the model.
So, how does it work if
we quantify fitness,
in terms of a number between zero and one?
We need to count the number of missing
tokens, consumed tokens, remaining tokens,
and produced tokens, while replaying
the event log on top of the model.
Okay, let's take a look at some questions.
Some of these may take some
time to actually compute.
What is shown here is an event
log containing 35 cases,
as is indicated in the table.
We have this very simple process
model that we have seen before,
the question is to compute fitness, using
the formula shown on the previous slide.
To answer this question,
we first look at the trace acd,
which happened once in this event log.
As always, we start with the production
action on the source place,
then we can execute a.
We consume one token and
produce two tokens.
Then we need to do c,
c is also possible, so we do
a consumption and a production action.
Now we need to execute d,
but d is not enabled because there
is no token on place p3.
So, we see that there is a problem,
we need to add a missing token and
only then we can execute d.
It leads to the consumption of the two
tokens, and the production of one token.
Finally, we need to consume
the token from the final place, and
when we have done that, we see that
one token is remaining in place p1.
So if we now add up these numbers
we can see that in this example,
there are five produced tokens,
five consumed tokens,
there is one missing token, and
there is one remaining token.
And we can use this to quantify
the fitness of this single trace.
But we need to do that for the whole log.
We do that using a spreadsheet,
and the row highlighted now
shows the trace that we just looked at,
with one missing token and
one remaining token, five produced
tokens and five consumed tokens.
This trace happened only once,
so if we multiply this by one,
then we get these numbers of consumed,
produced, missing and remaining tokens.
We can also take a look at another trace,
for
example, the first one,
which is perfectly fitting.
If we replay it, we don't encounter
any missing or remaining tokens.
This trace is happening ten times, so
we need to multiply the numbers for
this trace by ten.
If we do this for all the traces,
then we can add up the number of produced,
remaining, consumed, and
missing tokens, as is highlighted here.
And then we can simply apply the formula,
and get, the fitness of 0.96.
So this is the way that we
can compute a fitness for
a log consisting of multiple traces.
Here we can see the output of ProM,
so ProM
provides exactly the types of diagnostics
that we obtained during replay.
So here you can see the missing or
remaining tokens,
one can see the overall fitness.
But one can also select the cases
that are fitting and not fitting.
Note that this is not
output taken from ProM 6,
it's taken from an earlier version,
ProM 5.2.
Because ProM 6 provides more
advanced conformance checking techniques,
that we will discuss in the next lecture.
Let us take a look at another example.
So the question to you is, now we look at
an event log that contains only one case.
And this one case contains only one event,
namely e, please compute the fitness
using the formulas that we have seen before.
To answer this question,
we need to replay this trace.
We start with the production
action on the source place, and
then we need to execute e.
But as it is clearly visible, e is not
enabled because p1 and p2 are empty,
they have no tokens.
So, we record the fact that we have two
missing tokens, one for p1, one for p2.
Then we can execute e, we consume
two tokens, we produce two tokens.
And then the trace has ended.
But the environment still needs to
consume a token from place end, but
place end contains no token.
So, we record the fact that
there is a missing token there,
we consume that token.
And then if we look at the final state,
we can see that there are still tokens
remaining, namely in the source place and
places p3 and p4.
So if we look at these numbers, we can
see that we have three produced tokens,
three consumed tokens, three missing
tokens and three remaining tokens.
So what is now the fitness
of this particular trace?
It is equal to 0, because we do 3 divided
by 3, and then we take 1 minus that number.
And that holds both for production and
consumption, so the fitness is equal to 0.
In other words, none of the,
produced tokens was actually used.
And none of the consumed
tokens,was actually present,
showing that this is clearly the worst
fitness that one can imagine.
Let us take a look at another example,
this is a log that consists of 33 cases.
For example,
trace acd happens 10 times, trace d,
that you can see at the bottom,
happened only once.
Again, we would like to
compute the fitness.
Again we create the spreadsheet
to evaluate the fitness of
this particular example.
And just as an illustration
let us focus on the trace ace.
This trace has happened five times.
And let us replay it using
the technique that we have seen before.
If we do this,
then we have these numbers of consumed,
produced, missing, and remaining token.
There is one token remaining,
and there is one token missing.
So that leads to five traces,
each having the remaining token and
a missing token so in total there are five
remaining tokens and five missing tokens.
Next to the five times five produced
tokens and consumed tokens.
Well, this was an example for this row,
we can do that for all the rows and then
we get these total numbers of produced,
remaining, consumed and missing tokens.
And this leads to a fitness
of just below 0.9.
And again we obtain this by applying
the formula that we have seen before.
Here again we can see some diagnostics
in ProM, so ProM is showing the fitness,
exactly the same fitness as
what we have computed by hand.
And again we can see where
are the tokens remaining and
where are the tokens missing.
Numbers that have a minus sign in front of
them, they correspond to missing tokens.
Positive numbers correspond to
kind of like tokens that are not
consumed while replaying the trace.
As a last example take a look at
this event log containing 20 cases.
The first trace is a b e f c d,
and I hope that you can see that
there are some problems here.
So again the question is how
to quantify the fitness and
we can do it in exactly the same
way as we have seen before.
In this case we get in total 200
produced tokens, 200 consumed tokens, 40
remaining tokens and 40 missing tokens,
and this leads to a fitness of 0.8.
Also again a screen shot of ProM,
showing exactly this same type of
diagnostics, that we have seen before.
Okay, so this is the replay approach, and
you can see that it works really
nice on the simple examples, but
we are making some simplifying
assumptions while doing this.
First of all, in all the examples,
all the transitions that we looked at,
have a unique and visible label.
If we want to apply this technique to
models that may have multiple transitions
with the same label, or transitions that
do not have a label that are invisible.
We need to apply heuristics and so, there
may be situations in which the diagnostics
may be misleading because, while
replaying in a way, we need to guess, for
example, which of the two transitions
having the same label should be executed.
The conformance values may also
be sometimes too optimistic.
If there are many problems,
then what you will see is that the net
gets flooded by tokens, because each time
a token is missing, it is simply added.
So, in the end, there may be too many
tokens and you can execute everything.
And last but not least,
this simple approach makes local decisions
that may lead to misleading diagnostics.
Let us take a look at this example
showing that local decision
making is not good enough.
So if you look at this trace, we want
to execute a, c1, c2, e1, e2 and e3.
And these numbers have been
chosen in an arbitrary manner so
we can have many more c activities.
We could have also a much
longer chain of e activities.
The problem is that the execution of a,
at the beginning,
can not be matched with
the execution of e1, e2, and e3.
But if we do the replay what
you will see is that it
naively starts replaying
from the beginning.
So, we start with the produced token
on the source place, then we execute a,
we consume one token, produce two tokens.
Then we can do c1 and c2,
not encountering any types of problems.
But then when executing e1,
we see that there is a problem,
because one of the input places
of e1 doesn't contain a token.
So we need to record the fact that
there is a missing token here, and
then we can continue towards the end,
adding the produced and consumed tokens.
At the end we consume
a token from the sink place.
And we acknowledge that there is
a remaining token left behind.
So, these diagnostics
are a bit misleading, because,
in the beginning we chose the path
through a, whereas, if you look
at it more closely, it would probably have
been better to take the path involving b.
The fitness is computed in this case, and
it gives a particular number, but
the diagnostics are a bit problematic.
It does not provide a corresponding
path through the model,
because the path that is now being
replayed, if we look at the p and
c tokens, is a path that is not possible.
What we would really like to see is that
we would like to see the path which is
closest to the trace that we
have observed in reality.
And in this case, this would have been
the sequence b, c1, c2, e1, e2, e3.
In the next lecture, we will look at
the notion of alignments, and
the diagnostics provided by
alignments are much better.
So here you can see
an example of an alignment,
the top row of such an alignment
corresponds to a trace in the event log.
The bottom row corresponds
to a real path in the model.
And we would like to relate these two.
We also have this symbol which
indicates a so called no move.
It is modeling the fact,
that reality could not mimic the model or
the model could not mimic reality.
So, we have move in log only,
something happened in reality which
could not be mimicked by the model.
We have a move in model only,
something is needed according to
the model, but did not happen in reality.
And we have so called synchronize moves,
or moves in both.
Indicating that a model and
log agree on what should happen.
So, if you look at alignments we get
a much better diagnostics than through
simple token replay, because you can
clearly see from the alignment that there
was a problem related to a and
b at the beginning.
In the next lecture we will talk more
about alignments, if you would like to
read more on conformance checking
please take a look at chapter seven.
Thank you for watching this lecture,
see you next time.
[MUSIC]