[MUSIC]
Glad to see you again.
In the previous lecture, we introduced
the topic of conformance checking.
There are many situations where we
would like to compare modeled and
observed behavior.
Today we will discuss a particular
technique to check conformance.
This technique is called causal
footprints, and the idea is based on one
of the ingredients of the alpha algorithm
that we saw in an earlier lecture.
When we introduce the alpha algorithm,
we used matrices like this.
This is called the footprint
of a particular log.
We are using notions such as causality,
parallel, and choice.
And they are based on the direct
succession relationship.
For example, if you take a look at
this particular causal footprint,
you will see that this arrow is
indicating that a is followed by b,
at least once in the log, but it is
never the case that b is followed by a.
This parallel symbol is indicating
that b is sometimes followed by c,
and c is sometimes followed by b.
So they happen in both directions.
Then there is this symbol, which is the
choice symbol, which is indicating that b
is never followed by e and
e is never followed by b.
So these are the ingredients
of creating a footprint and
it is very important to realize that we
can create a footprint-based on a log.
But that we can also create
a footprint placed on a model,
because a model can generate traces.
And also by statical analysis
of these types of models,
we can already derive this
matrix with all the causalities.
In this case, there's a process model
discovered by the alpha algorithm.
Both have the same causal footprint,
and so there are no differences.
What we are going to do
next is we are going to look at
the more complicated log, and we are going
to consider four different process models.
Some match well with original log.
Others do not.
And we will use the footprints
to analyze these differences.
Let's take a look at the full log and
the causal footprint related to it.
It's shown here.
If we apply the alpha algorithm we get
the model that is shown here on the right.
And in this model when we analyze it, the set of
traces we find exactly the same footprint.
So the footprint of log and
model coincide.
In this case we say that the
footprint-based conformance equals to 1.
This means that there is a perfect match.
If the footprint-based conformance
metric has a very low value,
it means that there is not a good
match between log and model.
This is computed as the fraction of cells
in the footprint matrix where log and
model agree upon.
So let's now take a look
at the second model,
which is not a perfect match
with the original event log.
For example if you look
here at the cell of a and
d, you can see that a is
never followed by d.
This followed by b and
c, but never followed by d,
which was the case in the original log.
So, we can create such a causal
footprint based on this model.
And then we can compare the footprint of
model two with the original event log.
And we can put these two matrices on top
of each other and look at the differences.
For example, we see that indeed in the log
a is sometimes followed by d,
but never the other way around.
And in the model, model N2, a and
d never follow one another.
So we see a difference there.
We can also take a look at b and
d and we see that, in the event log,
they are considered to be concurrent
because they happen in any order.
But if we look at the model N2,
we see that b is followed by d,
but d is never followed by b.
And in such a way we can analyze
all the differences between
the original log and model N2.
Here the differences are highlighted.
And we can count them and
we can diagnose them.
So here in the matrix we
just see the differences.
So for example we can see
that if we look at b and
d, in the log it was parallel,
in the model it was sequential.
And we can count these differences.
So there are 64 cells.
And in 12 of these cells,
there is disagreement.
So it's 1 minus 12 divided by 64 is
a footprint-based conformance of 0.8125.
So, this way we can quantify
differences between log and model.
We can also provide
diagnostics as is shown here.
The elements of the footprint matrix,
where model and
log disagree,
you can visualize them in the model.
For example,
the visualization here is showing that in
the original log a could be followed by d,
but this is no longer possible.
So, we can diagnose differences,
we can also quantify them.
Let's now take a look at a question.
So, now we are taking another model and
the two models that we
have considered before.
And I would like to ask you to estimate
the footprint-based conformance
based on the original event log and
the model that is shown here.
So how can we compute this?
We take the original footprint
matrix of the event log.
We take the model, and
then we see where the footprint matrix of
the model disagrees with
the footprint of the original log.
And these are highlighted here.
So what we can see is that in
the model many activities are missing.
These missing activities in the model
will never follow one another or
any of the other activities.
Whereas in the original
event log they did.
Again we can count the differences.
In this case there are 16 cells where
there is disagreement between log and
model.
And that leads to a footprint-based
conformance of 0.75.
Let's take a look at another model.
This is the flower model,
which allows for lots of behavior.
And again, try to estimate what you think
is the footprint-based conformance between
the original log and this flower model.
To answer this question,
we do the same as what we did before.
We take the original footprint and
compare it with the footprint
of the process model.
This process model allows for
much more behavior than what
we have seen in the log.
So if we visualize the differences, you
can see that in total there are 45 cells
different, and that leads to
a very low conformance of 0.29.
And so this has a worse conformance than
the three models that we have seen before.
Because of the massive amount of
additional behavior allowed by
this flower model.
Causal footprints
are incredibly flexible.
In the sense that you can compare logs to
logs, you can compare models to models,
and you can compare models to event logs.
And so
we can make many different comparisons.
It also implicitly captures fitness,
precision, and
generalization, but
in a rather indirect way.
The approach also has many limitations.
So, for example, we do not look at
the frequencies of traces in the log.
Behavior is only considered indirectly.
We only consider directly
follows relations when
building the footprint metrics.
So, you can have two different processes
that have exactly the same footprint,
although their behavior are different,
as long as they have the same
directly follows relationship.
In one go, we address issues like fitness,
precision, and generalization.
But often you want to
have separate metrics for
these different conformance dimensions.
This is why,
in the next two lectures we will look
at additional conformance
checking techniques.
In the next lecture we will look
at so-called token-based replay.
If you would like to read
more on conformance checking,
you can take a look at Chapter 7.
Thank you for watching this lecture.
See you next time.
[MUSIC]