[MUSIC]
Welcome to this lecture.
This is the fifth and
last lecture on conformance checking.
Today we present the most
advanced approach,
relating event logs to process models.
Here you see again an overview,
of the three conformance checking
approaches used in this course.
We started from footprints
where we basically only
compared the syntactical structure,
using the directly follows relation.
Then we looked at a more advanced
approach, using token-based replay.
Today we will look at alignment-based
conformance checking.
So what are the requirements for
conformance checking,
overcoming the limitations of
the approaches that we have seen before?
First of all, conformance checking
should not impose any restrictions on
the process model notation.
For example, we should not be
restricted to work-flow nets.
We should not be restricted to models,
where there cannot be two
transitions having the same label.
Or where there are silent steps, for
example to model an OR
split or an OR join.
Moreover, we really would like to
see the closest matching path,
through the process model.
So if we see something in reality,
we want to relate it to a valid
path through the process model.
Why is this necessary?
It is necessary for performance analysis,
where we replay reality on top of the
model to see where the bottlenecks are but
also if we look at more
sophisticated notions of conformance
involving precision, generalization or
more advanced forms of diagnostics.
We first need to relate reality
to a path through the model.
So it's a kind of enabler for
all kinds of other types of analysis.
What is the notion of an alignment?
Here we can see a trace taken from
the bigger log that we have used before.
We compare it to the model and
in this case, there is a path through
the model that exactly matches,
the trace that we have seen in the log.
So the top row is a trace through the log.
The bottom row is the trace
through the process model, and
in this case they perfectly agree.
Here you see an example of another trace,
that doesn't fit into the model.
If we look at the trace a, d, e,
g, h, we can see two problems.
First of all, a b or c is missing, which
should be executed concurrently to d.
Moreover, at the end it cannot be that
both decisions are taken at the same time.
So we should have g or h, but not both.
The alignment is clearly
illustrating these problems, so
in the alignment we can see that
the model had to take a b move which was
not mimicked by reality, and
at the end there was a g and an h.
And in the model one of
these two had to be ignored.
So, what are the terms that we are using,
when we are talking about alignments?
So, an alignment is a row consisting
of two lines, where the top line
refers to the log, the bottom line
refers to the path through the model.
We can have a move in log only,
then we only see
the label of an activity in the top row,
but not in the bottom row.
A move in model only is the reverse.
The model had to make a move which
could not be mimicked by reality.
If we look at a move in both,
also called a synchronous move,
then both make a move at the same time.
Note that all of these terms and
these concepts and also
the corresponding analysis techniques, are
independent of the process model notation.
So we can do this for Petri nets, for
BPMN models, for transition systems,
it doesn't really matter.
Let us take a look at some examples.
So, the first notion that we
would like to introduce is
the notion of an optimal alignment.
There are multiple ways of relating
a reality, to a path through the model,
and in principal, there may be many
paths possible through the model.
So which path are we going to choose?
We choose the path that is closest
to what we have seen in reality.
So here,
it is very obvious that the top alignment,
is the alignment that is optimal.
Because there's a perfect agreement,
between model and log.
Here, we see a more tricky example, so,
we look at a trace that doesn't fit,
it's an example that we have used before.
And now there are multiple
explanations that can be used.
so, which one is the best explanation for
what we have seen?
In the first alignment that you see here,
it basically says that a and
b have been swapped.
The second alignment,
takes us explanation that the e1, e2,
e3 that we saw reality, in the model
correspond to d1, d2, and d3.
So which is the best alignment?
It is difficult to say,
it depends on the cost function.
Are the deviations related to e1,
e2 and e3.
More or less of here, than the deviation
that we saw with respect to a and b.
To quantify this and
to make an objective decision we
introduced the notion of a cost function.
So we associate costs to moves.
If we have a synchronous move,
where log and
mobile agree on the action to be taken,
we have cost 0.
For all the other situations,
we need to introduce positive costs.
What we typically do is that,
if two activities disagree,
that we say the costs are infinite,
in other ways we give it such high cost
that we will never take such a solution.
And if we use a standard cost function
we assign to a move on model and
a move on log the same cost, namely one.
So, in the remainder in all of
the examples we will use this standard
cost function.
So if we apply it to the examples
that we have seen before, then we
can look at the three alignments and we
can see that the top alignment has cost 0,
the second alignment has cost 2, because
we have a move a log and a move in model.
The bottom one has cost 10,
because there are 10 no move symbols.
So the top one is optimal, because there
is no other alignment that has lower cost.
We can take a look at this example,
here we see the two alignments
that we have seen before.
Now, using the standard cost function,
we can make a decision, and we can decide
that, the first one is
an alignment that is optimal,
because we can not find other
alignments that have lower costs.
And so all alignments have cost two or
higher.
Let's take a look at this example, so, and
it is intended to show that there
may be many different optimal alignments,
given a trace in the log, and a model.
So the cost of this alignment is two.
The explanation that this alignment
provides, is that the reality e and
f happened, but we should ignore them.
In other ways, we don't go through the
loop, we only go through the process once,
and we ignore e and f, cost 2.
Another explanation also having cost 2,
is the explanation that we have to go
through the iteration once, and, so, now,
we accept the fact that we
need to execute f but, for
that we need to add two events that
did not happen in reality to explain.
The scenario in terms of a path in
the model from beginning to end.
And so d and
b are missing in the event log, but
in this explanation they are added.
So there can be multiple alignments,
corresponding to the same trace and
the same model.
Let's see whether you
understood these concepts.
So, take a look at this trace.
The one that we have seen before,
and the model.
How many optimal alignments are there?
The answer is nine.
There are nine optimal alignments, and
let's try to understand what
these nine alignments are.
Here we see the two that
we have shown before, and
the b move in model only
is highlighted in red here,
because this b could be replaced by a c,
and so we have these possible variants.
Now when we say that okay, there are three
possible optimal alignments, but
there are more,
because d is concurrent with b and c.
So, we can reorder these
different variants.
So we can swap the move related to d
with the move related to b, or to c.
So, if we look at the situation we can
see that there are actually nine moves in
total, because we can look
at all the combinations of
all the different variants.
So far we have considered only
the standard cost function,
which assigns cost one to a move
in log and a move in model, but
one can think of any cost structure also
take into account other attributes and
other properties of events.
So, for example, if we would need
to align these two, actions, so
one event in the log, and one execution
of a transition in the model,
then we could take into account
how similar thesee activities are,
if they are very similar,
then we can have a lower cost.
We can also assign penalties
to activities that
are being executed by the wrong person.
So, suppose that John is not
authorized to execute this activity,
then we can associate a penalty to it.
In most process models, you also often
have deadlines, things should happen, for
example within a period of three weeks.
If then in reality it takes four weeks,
you can assign a penalty to the fact
that things are being too late.
One can also take into account data,
so certain paths through the
process model are only allowed for
particular types of customers or
particular types of orders.
For example larger orders or smaller
orders should take different paths.
This also can be taken into account,
when creating a cost function and
a corresponding alignment.
One can take a look at the risks, one
can take a look at context information.
So anything can be added
to this cost function, and
still we can provide
an optimal alignment and
diagnose the differences taking into
account these other perspectives.
So far we only provided diagnostics,
move in model only, move in log only.
As indications of that reality and
the model disagree.
But if we want to quantify fitness,
using a number between zero and
one, we need to think of
a worst case scenario.
What kind of costs does
the worst case scenario have?
Well if you think about it, the worst
case scenario is a scenario where we
just have move in models,
and move in logs.
So what does it mean?
Take a look at this example again,
and let us
compute fitness using
the worst case scenario.
In this case, the worst case scenario is
that for all the events in the trace,
we just do a move in log only.
Next, we take the shortest
path through the model, and
do just move in model only actions.
And if we do that,
then we get this number.
So, the optimal alignment had a cost
of two, we have seen that before.
The trace has length seven,
the shortest path has length five.
So if we fill out the formula,
we will see that the fitness of
this particular trace is 0.83.
So this is the way that
we can compute fitness.
Now try to compute
fitness using this trace.
And again we should think about a worst
case scenario to be able to compute this.
The answer is as follows.
So, we need to align the trace
that we have seen with the model.
Look at the optimal alignment,
and the worst case alignment.
The optimal alignment,
we have seen that before, has a cost of 2.
If we look at the worst case alignment,
what does it look like?
Well, this is an example
of a worst case alignment.
So, and it consists of two parts,
if we look at the first part
we see that everything that was in the
log, corresponds to a move in log only.
And then we take the shortest
path through the model, and
we just do move on model there.
And if we do that, we can see that
the optimal alignment has a cost of two.
And the worst case scenario,
has cost six plus six.
And now we can use these numbers
to fill out in the formula, and
we find the fitness of 0.833.
Just by accident, it is the same
value as what we have seen before.
So what are the advantages
of aligning log and model.
We can directly relate observed behavior,
to the model itself,
which is very important.
It is very flexible, I showed to you
that one can use any cost function,
assigning penalties to
not making deadlines,
events being executed by the wrong person,
etcetera.
We get very detailed diagnostics.
We can compare events at
a very refined level.
And after aligning the log and the model,
we get a path through the model,
and we can do all kinds of
other types of analysis.
And so that
makes alignments extremely important.
To illustrate this,
let us take a look at this diagram.
So this is a path through the model,
and so this is the modeled behavior.
If then in reality we see a deviating
trace, we can use alignment
to diagnose where these deviations are,
and why they happened.
But this is not the only thing,
why alignments are important.
We can also use alignments to
squeeze behavior that we see in
reality into the model,
even if it does not fit perfectly.
This is crucial for performance analysis,
and all kinds of other types of
analysis that require us to use the model
and the event data at the same time.
One element of conformance checking
that we did not discuss so far,
is the ability to drill down.
So we can always separate
traces into fitting traces and
non-fitting traces, and
then we can analyze them separately.
So we can do this to try to understand,
what the differences are,
between the deviating cases and
the non-deviating cases.
Note that if we separate
a log like this in two parts,
we can analyze the two parts as
if they are a new event log.
So we can apply all of the techniques
that we have seen before.
We can also move beyond fitness and
control flow.
So, our lion's share of attention that
we have given so far, was focused on
fitness but also precision, generalization
and simplicity are important.
And there are precise
definitions possible also for
these dimensions but
they are outside the scope of this course.
Also, if we look at
things like alignments,
we have mostly focus on control flow.
But we can also take into
account the other perspectives,
as has been illustrated before.
A nice example of are the so
called data-aware alignments,
that take into account control flow and
data at the same time.
To read more on conformance checking
you can look in chapter seven.
Also see the article highlighted here,
that this providing much more information
related to the notion of alignments.
Thank you for watching,
and hope to see you soon.
[MUSIC]