[MUSIC]
Glad to see you again.
In the last two lectures, we discussed
a two-phase process discovery approach,
based on state-based regions.
Today, we will discuss
the limitations of this approach, but
also point out possible extensions.
So here, again, you see an overview
of the two-phase approach.
In the first phase, we construct a
transition system based on the event log,
and we can play with different
abstractions to make a more general or
more specific model.
Once we have the transition system, we try
to discover concurrency using the notion
of regions, and
get the corresponding Petri net.
In the last lecture,
we explained this algorithm to
convert a transition
system into a Petri net
by discovering concurrency,
using the notion of state-based regions.
So let us take a look at an example.
So suppose that we have an event log, and
that this is a transition system,
that we have learned from it.
Once we have such a transition system
we would like to discover which things
happen in parallel?
Which things happen in sequence?
What choices are there?
And if we do this we start by looking at
what are the so-called
minimal non-trivial regions.
Here every color corresponds to
a minimal non-trivial region.
Once we have these regions we can easily
construct the corresponding Petri net
capturing the behaviour that
is in the transition system.
So in this example the transition
system and the Petri net are bisimilar.
So what does this mean?
It means that they are equivalent
from a behavioral point of view.
More precise any move of the transition
system can be mimicked by the Petri net,
and any move of the Petri net can be
mimicked by the transition system.
So that's the approach.
So what are possible problems
related to the state-based regions.
First of all, as you will see in a minute,
there are certain process constructs
which can not be discovered.
But as we will show
later, there are many extensions
possible to resolve these problems.
A more foundational problem
is that regions have
difficulties balancing the four forces,
fitness, precision,
generalization, and
simplicity, in a right manner.
But we will see more about
this later in this lecture.
So let us start by
looking at some examples.
So we have a log and in the log
there are always two occurrences of a.
So what is the corresponding
transition system?
It is a transition
system that we see here.
What is the Petri net constructed
from this transition system,
if we use the basic algorithm
that we have described before?
If we try to construct
the corresponding Petri net,
we first need to decide what are
the regions.
But in this case, only the empty region
and the set of all states form a region.
So there are no nontrivial
regions in this example.
So if we construct a corresponding
Petri net using the algorithm,
the Petri net consists of just one
transition, and this Petri net allows for
two a's, but also for
one a, three a's, 15 as.
So it's not the behavior
that we started with.
It allows for more.
Let us take a look at another example.
Here you see an event log where
all traces start with an a,
all traces end with a c and
in between there can be any number of b's.
If we construct a corresponding
transition system it looks like this.
If we again try to apply the basic
state-based region algorithm,
what is the Petri net
that will result from it?
If we construct a Petri net
based on this transition system,
we first need to,
compute the minimal nontrivial regions.
And in this case, there are three of them.
The region just consisting of
state s1 indicated in red here,
the region consisting just of state 2,
the region consisting just of state 3.
So these are three regions, and
if you observe them closely you
will see that b is never crossing.
Right?
So, it's always non-crossing so
it's never entering and never exiting.
So if we compute the corresponding Petri
Net based on this minimal non-trivial
regions, then we get the Petri net where
b is unconnected to any of the places.
Because it is always
Petrinon-crossing.
This allows for
more behavior than the behavior that
we could see in the transition system.
So, for example, this Petri net
allows b to be executed before a or
after c which was not the case in the
original behavior that we started with.
Let's take a look at the third example.
Again, we take a log.
From it we construct a transition system.
It looks like this.
So we see a followed by b.
Or we just see b.
Again there is the question,
what is the Petri net.
That we get if we apply
state-based regions.
To answer this question,
we again first compute the regions
which are indicated here.
In total,
there are four different regions, and
if we convert these
regions into a Petri net.
We find the Petri net with two transitions
that can be executed concurrently.
So the original behavior
is possible in this model.
But the model also allows for
behavior that we did not see before.
In particular,
we can see that the sequence,
b followed by a, is possible in the Petri
net, although we never observed it,
in the original log, and it's not a trace
of the corresponding transition system.
So, the three examples
that I just showed to you,
they all produce a Petri
net that allows for
the behavior that we have seen, but
it also allows for more behavior.
So, in other words, the Petri net
can simulate the behavior that we
started with, but it also allows for more.
And so the transition system cannot always
mimic the behavior of the Petri net.
So one can look at various refinements.
And one of the refinements
is based on label splitting.
So how does it work?
We first compute the corresponding
transition system,
using some notion of abstraction.
Once we have the transition system
we check certain properties.
In this case the forward closure property.
If this property does not hold we
know that we need to split labels.
Concretely, we need to
rename a into a1 and a2.
Once we do that,
we can apply again our technique, and
construct a corresponding Petri net where
you have two transitions labeled a.
Exactly capturing the behavior
that we would like to see.
Let's take a look at the example where
we had the trace a comma b and
the trace just consisting of b.
Again, we apply the approach that we
had before, and now again we apply
label splitting, because we see that the
forward closure property does not hold,
it's not important that you exactly
understand what it means, but
we can detect based on the properties of
the region, whether it is okay or not.
If it's not okay,
we need to apply label splitting.
In this case,
we rename the b's into a b1 and a b2.
We apply standard region theory and
then we end up with this process model,
where we have two b transitions capturing
the behavior that we would like to see.
The ProM plug-ins, based on state-based
regions, they ensure bisimulation.
So if we feed it with the examples
that we just showed it is able to
create a correct Petri net,
in this case by spitting the two a's.
It is also able to handle these loops
that were disconnected before so
note now that b is connected
to the place in the middle.
If we apply it to this example
that we have seen before
it correctly splits the b's.
And so the ProM plug-in again uses these
extensions to guarantee the proper result.
Besides label splitting
there are many extensions and
refinements of this basic region approach.
So we can impose
any constraint on places.
So for example we could say we only
want to have places that have,
at most, two inputs, and
at most, two outputs.
Or we only want to have places where it
is a clear split or a join, but not both.
And many of these extensions are possible.
So, we have now covered the first weakness
of the state-based region approach.
Now we focus on the second problem,
how to balance the four forces.
And we understand that regions
have problems with this.
This is a picture that
we have seen before.
It illustrates that if we
are discovering a Petri net
we need to balance different forces.
There's a struggle between fitness and
simplicity between generalization and
precision.
So, if we now look at
the two phase approach,
what are the properties of this
approach in terms of these four forces?
Let's first start by looking at
building the transition system.
When we build a transition system,
we have many parameters that we can use.
So, for example,
if we take the prefix automaton, so
we consider the entire past of a trace of
the prefix, and we apply no abstraction.
So the ordering is preserved.
Then based on the particular log,
this is the transition system that you
can see in the background that we get.
So this transition system is
good in terms of fitness.
It is good in terms of precision.
But it is not simple and
it is not generalizing.
We could have chosen a different,
abstraction.
For example the abstraction where
we only look at a last event.
If we do that and
we apply it to the same log we get
a much simpler transition system.
The problem with this transition
system is that it has a good fitness,
it is generalizing, it is simple but at
that the same time it is not very precise.
That allows for all kinds of
behaviors that we did not see before.
So when building the transition system,
we can look at the various trade offs
between fitness, simplicity,
precision and generalization.
If we look at the second step there we
would like to discover
concurrency by using regions.
Here if we use the classical approaches,
behavioral equivalence is preserved.
Earlier, I explained you
the notion of bisimulation.
So, any move of the transition
system can be mimicked by
a move of the corresponding Petri net,
and vice versa.
So there is no generalization, and
there is no special consideration for
notions like simplicity.
And so if we would like to address these
things we need to do it in the first step.
So let's give a summary of the two
phase approach based on regions.
It can be used specifically
through the extensions to
capture very complicated process patterns.
Patterns that existing algorithms like the
alpha algorithm cannot really discover well.
It also provides
insight into the essence of
process discovery and concurrency.
As drawbacks, there is the problem
that if we look at the second phase,
when we are discovering concurrency.
We ensure that the result is
bisimilar to the transition system.
So that may lead to overfitting.
We are not generalizing in this phase.
Also, in the second step we can not,
filter out infrequent behavior.
If we would like to do so, we need to do
so while building the transition system.
So noise and incompleteness
cannot be handled very well.
But it's still a very
important approach because it
shows what the essence of
process discovery is all about.
This was the last discovery technique
that we are going to discuss in detail.
You can read chapter six and
read more about this.
In the next lecture we will
specifically look at other
approaches that we will not
cover in any form of detail.
Thank you for watching this lecture.
See you next time.
[MUSIC]