[MUSIC]
Welcome to this lecture.
Today we discuss another
approach to check conformance.
It is based on replaying the event log to
diagnose differences, between modeled and
observed behavior.
This figures show a desire line, this
desire line is clearly indicating that
the behavior of people, is very different
from the expected or modeled behavior.
One can think of the gate in
this diagram as the model,
one can think of the desire
line as the event log, and
what is shown is that there is
clearly deviating behavior.
Through conformance checking we would
like to diagnose such differences, and
we would also like to
associate a number to it.
How good is the conformance?
In the last lecture,
we looked at conformance
checking using causal footprints.
And this approach has
all kinds of problems.
For example, it does not take
into account the frequency of traces and
it does not actually look at the behavior.
Today, we will look at a much more refined
method based on token-based replay.
So let's take a look at an example,
we see a trace a b e g,
and this trace does not
fit into this model.
If we would just consider fitness
at the level of complete traces,
one would say, this trace has a fitness
of zero, because it doesn't fit.
Such answers are not
very useful because we
would like to look at fitness and
conformance at the level of events.
Because if would have long traces,
then we may have logs,
where none of the traces is actually fitting.
We would get the conformance of 0, but
this would be a very misleading number.
So, we need to look at somehow
the fraction of events that
is fitting and the fraction of
events that is not fitting.
This is done through counting so
called missing and remaining tokens, and
to illustrate this let's replay
this trace on this model.
So we first execute a,
after executing a we execute b,
we still do not see any problem.
But while doing this we are producing and
consuming tokens.
Then, the event log says that we need
to execute e, but, e is not enabled.
So we count a missing token, you see that
there is a problem, we record it, and
we continue.
Then we execute e, after executing e,
we need to execute g,
and we don't encounter any
additional problems, except for
the fact that when we reach the end of the
trace, there is still a token left behind.
So this example, we have one remaining
token and one missing token.
The total of a six produced tokens,
there are six consumed tokens,
there is one missing token and
one remaining token.
So, we can put these into
a formula that looks like this,
that computes fitness as
a number between zero and one.
The 0 means, the fitness is as bad as
is possible, a fitness of 1 means perfect
fitness, the trace could be replayed
without encountering any problems.
So in this case p and c are equal to 6,
m and r are equal to 1.
So if we fill that in in this formula,
we get a conformance of
0.83 for this particular trace.
So what is this approach based on?
It is based on simply counting the number
of produced, consumed, missing and
remaining tokens.
Missing tokens are tokens that
are consumed while they are not there.
So we need to add a token, the counter
r refers to the tokens that
are left behind at the end.
That were not consumed.
So, while replaying a trace.
At any point in time,
the place contains
p plus m minus c tokens and
this number should be positive,
because there cannot be a negative
number of tokens in a place.
And at the end,
we would like this place to be empty.
So this leads to a couple of
invariants that are shown here.
If you do the replay,
p plus m will always be bigger or
equal to c, because we cannot have
a negative number of tokens in a place.
C will also be at least m because we
are never going to add missing tokens
if they are not needed for consumption.
And at the end, r is the number
of tokens remaining on the place,
so r is equal to p plus m minus c.
All these numbers, they hold at
the level of an individual place.
But they also hold at the level
of all places in the process model.
There is a special step needed at
the beginning and at the end, so
in the beginning the environment needs to
produce a token, for the source place.
And at the end, that the environment needs
to consume a token from the sink place.
Note, that in the latter case if there is
no token remaining on the final place,
at the end of the trace,
you still need to consume it.
So this will add an extra
missing token, if it is not there.
This way we really check
whether the trace,
has terminated in the desired final state.
Let us take a look at some examples, so
here you see a trace that
is perfectly fitting.
So if we replay it, we expect that
the counters m and r, will remain 0.
But still,
we need to understand the principle so,
to start easy we look at
something that fits perfectly.
Initially, the environment puts
a token into this source place.
That means that we need to increment the p
counter by 1, as has happened here.
Now, the event log says that a is
the first activity to be executed.
So in the Petri net,
we are forced to fire a,
if we execute a we are consuming one
token, and we are producing two tokens.
So we update the corresponding counters,
now we have three produced
tokens in total.
In the next step we need to execute c and
again we consume and
produce a token, and update a counter,
we need to execute d.
Again, we add a consumed and
a produced token.
Then the event log says we need to
execute an e, this is indeed possible.
And now we are consuming two tokens,
and producing one token.
So now the c counter, has been set to 5.
Then we do activity h, and reach
the state with the token on place ends.
Now the environment,
takes this token and consumes it.
So we update the c counter,
so what we see at the end is
that p equals 7, c equals 7,
m and r equals 0.
So, if we fill that out in the formula
that we've seen before, b is 7,
c is 7, m is 0, r is 0,
then we get this result which equals 1.
So, this is perfect
fitness as we expected.
Let's now take a look at
a more interesting trace,
namely a trace that doesn't fit.
And you can easily see that it doesn't
fit, because the trace says that
after a we should execute d, which based
on the model is clearly not possible.
Let's again compute fitness using
the formula that we just have seen.
It again starts by the fact
that environment puts
a token on the source place,
so p is equal to 1.
Then, in the event log we see that
we need to do an a, we execute it,
we consume and produce a token,
getting these counters.
Now the event log says
that we need to do d,
and what you can clearly see is that d
is not possible according to the model,
because before, b or
c should have happened.
So, now we record the fact that there is
a missing token, and so we add a token,
but we increment the m counter by one,
yielding this state,
so m is now equal to 1,
p is equal to 3, c is equal to 2.
Now we execute c, we consume and
produce one token, update the counters,
we need to execute e.
Consume 1, produce 1,
finally, we need to do h.
We, again, consume and produce 1 token.
As before, at the end of the trace
the environment needs to consume a token,
whether it's there or not.
In this case the token is there,
so there's no problem.
So it is being consumed,
and now we see that p and
c have the same value, namely equal to 6.
What we now see is that at the end
there is still a token remaining in p2.
So, we update the r counter, and these
are the final values that we get.
As we see, values for p and
c and m and r, are both equal to 1.
And we can also overlay the model with
diagnostic information showing where
the problems are.
We can put these numbers into the formula
that we have seen before, and
if we do that, we get this result.
And so the fitness is 0.83.
This is fitness at the level
of an individual trace.
We can lift this notion,
to an entire event log.
And this is the formula that,
that describes that, it looks very
impressive but actually it's quite simple.
We are just summing up all the missing and
consumed and the remaining and produced
tokens over all the individual traces.
The same trace can appear multiple times,
we have a multi set,
therefore we take the sum over this multiset
and multiply it by the number of missing,
consumed, remaining and produced tokens.
So, here you see the individual
ingredients, and actually it is just
exactly the same as we have seen before,
but lifted to the level of an entire log.
So let's take a look at this example.
So we see again the event log
that we also used before.
We see four models, and
we can again compute replay fitness,
using the approach that I just described.
If you do so,
then these are the values that you get.
So, the first model that was
discovered using the alpha algorithm of
has a fitness of one,
that is what we expected.
But also note that the last model, the so
called flower model, has a fitness of one.
It is too general, but
from a fitness point of view it is okay,
because it allows for
all the behavior that has been seen.
To capture the fact that this model is
not a good representation of the log,
one needs to look at the notion
of precision to capture this.
By doing this replay we can also
provide very sophisticated and
detailed diagnostics, so if you look at
the diagnostics that I've shown here,
by comparing the log
with the second model.
We see that we have a fitness of 0.95,
but we can also see in terms of
the diagnostics how many times
an activity or a transition in Petri net
terms was being executed, how many times
a token was flowing over a particular arc.
The diagnostics clearly show,
that there is a problem with respect
to the ordering of b and c and b.
And so, c and b should be concurrent to d,
but now they are in sequence.
So all the traces,
where d happens before b or
c, they don't fit well into this model,
as is shown by the diagnostics.
If we take a look at this model, and
again compare it with the original log,
we can see even more problems.
And again,
by looking at a number of missing and
remaining tokens
in each of the places,
we can get a good understanding
of where the differences are.
So, through replay,
we can capture diagnostic information,
where are the differences,
and how severe are they, and we can
also compute a global fitness metric.
If you would like to read more
about token-based replay for
conformance checking,
please read more in chapter seven.
In the next lecture,
we will consider a more sophisticated
technique, based on alignments.
Thank you for watching,
and hope to see you soon.
[MUSIC]