[MUSIC]
Welcome to this lecture.
Thus far,
our main focus was on process discovery.
In this lecture today, we will introduce
another very important process mining
task, namely conformance checking.
This is a diagram that we have
seen several times before, and
it is now highlighting where
conformance checking fits in.
So we no longer want to discover
a process model, but we would like
to compare a process
model with the corresponding event log.
When doing conformance checking,
we need to take into consideration
the four dimensions that
we've also discussed when we were
looking at process discovery techniques.
However in many of the conformance
checking techniques, replay fitness,
the ability to replay the event log
on the model is the thing
which is most important.
And also, many of the techniques that we
will discuss in this lecture
will focus on that dimension.
But it doesn't mean that the other
dimensions are not important.
When we look at replay fitness,
we have already seen the principle before.
So the basic idea is that we would
like to replay traces that we
have seen in the log on top of a model.
So we have executed a and c and now
the event log says that we should do e.
But if you look at the model and
you look at the state that we are in,
e is not yet enabled.
So we need to force the process forward,
although we see that something
does not fit completely.
And we go towards the end.
But while doing that, we are counting
how many problems we see, and
we are also recording the types
of problems that we have seen.
So this is what we are trying to
do if we are checking for fitness.
If we do this we are comparing observed
behavior with modeled behavior.
So, the kind of diagnostics that
we can show are diagnostics at
the level of an event log.
For example, these are the traces
that do not fit well into the model.
We can also provide
diagnostics at the model level,
showing the parts of the model
where reality often deviates.
Or we can look at global metrics.
For example,
we will often look at a fitness metric,
having a value between zero and one,
where zero means that fitness is very
poor and a fitness of one means that
everything that was seen in the log was
indeed possible according to the model.
So what are use cases for
conformance checking?
The first use case is related
to auditing and compliance.
Things at the level of business processes.
We would like to understand,
do people deviate?
Why do they deviate?
Are the things that are reported,
reported correctly?
Another use case is that we want
to use conformance checking to
evaluate the quality of process
discovery algorithms and their results.
Last but not least, often we also want to
check conformance to some specification
based on the actual behavior.
For example, if we have a piece
of software and that software has
a specification describing how it should
work, we can compare it with a real
event log and see where the software
is deviating from the specification.
Also if we provide services,
we can also check
whether the description of the service
is consistent with the actual behavior.
So there are many different use cases.
For all of these cases we
need to have a model that we
are checking the event logs to.
And these models, in our case it will
typically be a Petri net.
But it can also be any set of rule or
any set of model that captures
some kind of behavior.
If we look at auditing,
the basic idea is to
check whether what was reported
was reported correctly.
And this is done to check whether
business processes are executed within
the boundaries set by managers,
governments, and other stakeholders.
And these boundaries are expressed
in terms of a process model or
a set of rules.
And one can think of rules
as small process models.
In the last couple of years there has
been lots of emphasis on compliance and
auditing related issues.
Many of you know the term Sarbanes-Oxley.
And that is referring legislation
that has been created
to ensure that organizations are doing
what they say they are doing.
A completely different use
case is the evaluation of
process discovery algorithms.
Suppose that I have four algorithms.
I use these algorithms.
I get four process models.
And then I would like to know which is
the best process discovery technique.
And we can compare them using conformance
checking, typically looking at the four
dimensions fitness, simplicity,
generalization and precision.
This is not an easy task.
If we try to compare the results of
different process discovery algorithms.
Or when a process discovery
algorithm has a lot of parameters.
We can also create many discovered models.
What are the best models
that we can look at?
In this diagram every red dot corresponds
to a discovered process model.
And the two dimensions indicate how
well the fitness of that model is and
how well the precision of that model is.
Then the question is,
what are good models to consider?
That is not the single best model,
because what you can clearly see in
this diagram is that there is apparently
a tradeoff between precision and fitness.
So if we pick a model on
the so-called Pareto front,
then we are looking at a model for
which there are no other models
that are better in all dimensions.
So, the model highlighted
here is Pareto optimal.
And, because this model exists,
the models indicated in grey
cannot be Pareto optimal if we
just look at these two dimensions.
We can take a look at another
model on the Pareto front and
again you can see that a couple
of models are discarded.
Because they are dominated by the models,
the models on the Pareto front.
You can do that for all the models on the
Pareto front and then we get red dots.
And if we are just interested
in these two dimensions,
these are all the models that we should
inspect because they are interesting.
The other models are not
interesting because there is
always a model that is better, or
at least as good in all the dimensions.
So far, we considered two dimensions,
fitness and precision, and
in this diagram you can see that model 5
is being dominated by model two because
model 2 is better in terms of fitness and
is better in terms of precision.
However, if we include a third dimension,
it may be that model 5
is on the Pareto front.
So if we, for example, plots fitness
against simplicity, one can see that
if you look at model 5 it is no
longer dominated by model 2 or
any of the other models.
So there is no model that at the same
time has a better fitness, precision and
simplicity, than model 5.
So it's not dominated.
So it is on the Pareto front.
And so we are interested in the models
that are on the Pareto front.
And compare and discover models is not
very easy, because one model can be better
in terms of fitness but worse in terms
of simplicity or the other way around.
So there is no such
thing as the best model.
And that is very
important to understand when you're
looking at process discovery.
Let's get back to
compliance-related questions.
So, we are comparing an event
log with the process model.
If there are deviations,
an obvious question to ask is,
is the model wrong or is the log wrong?
And both can be the case.
So deviations may be
considered to be good or bad.
In this context,
we often talk about breaking the glass.
In many processes, people deliberately
deviate from the process and
in that way do something good.
Ans so for example,
in hospitals doctors will deviate and
by these deviations they are
saving the lives of patients.
We can also look for positive deviants.
Things that deviate but
in a positive manner.
And so deviations are not always negative.
And it is not always the case that
the process model is right and
the event log is wrong.
So far we have been discussing
conformance checking mostly offline.
But, of course,
you can also that at the runtime.
Online conformance checking means that
the moment that the deviation occurs,
you immediately generate an alert.
In the next couple of lectures we
will focus on conformance checking
techniques and thereby we often
focus just on control flow.
We also typically do not look
at the simplicity of the model.
We can of course do conformance
checking for models with data or time.
For example, the model specifies that
a case should be handled within 30 days.
But the first type of techniques
that we will look at do not do that.
In the next lectures we will look at three
types of approaches, causal footprints,
token-based replay and
alignment-based conformance checking.
And in the next lecture,
we will start with causal footprints.
If you would like to read more
about conformance checking,
Chapter 7 is devoted to it.
Thank you for watching,
and hope to see you soon.
[MUSIC]