[MUSIC]
Glad to see you again.
Process models are very important for
understanding and improving processes.
However sometimes it is
better to first explore the event data.
Today we will show that dotted charts can
provide valuable insights in the early
stages of a process mining project.
Lion's share of attention so far has gone
to the output side, creating models.
Today we will look at the input side.
We will look at event logs, and
we will see that there are different
ways of exploring them.
And in particular, we will look at the
dotted chart to create a helicopter view
of the event data that we
are trying to analyze.
This is the simplistic view of event
data that we have used so far.
So one can think of it as a table where
every row corresponds to an event.
Each event should have a case ID,
an activity name and a time stamp.
And sometimes we have resource
information for other data.
However the real picture
is a bit more involved.
To illustrate this we are using this so
called object model
which is relating process models to
event data and is showing the structure
of events and their relations
to activities and processes.
So let's first take a look at
the part that we know very well.
So if we look at an event, an event
always belongs to a case, precisely one.
A case can be composed of more events,
and a case belongs to a process.
And a process may of course
have multiple cases.
If we look at an event,
events have attributes.
They refer to an activity, but we also
have other attributes like timestamps,
resources, costs,
transactional information, etcetera.
So timestamps are very important for
the ordering of events, and for
doing performance analysis.
Resources refer to people, organizations,
machines, that are needed to
execute a particular activity.
They are also very important for
analysis so
you should try to exploit this
in whatever way possible.
So far we didn't give a lot of attention
to transactional information but
many event logs contain
information referring to
the start time of an activity,
the end time of an activity.
Whether it was suspended,
resumed, etcetera.
So, let us focus on this
transactional information.
We assume that there is a particular
transactional model that
activities follow.
And here you see the most detailed
transactional model that is being
considered in the context
of process mining.
So we see many different activities
relating to when things have started,
when things have completed, whether things
have been aborted, etcetera, etcetera.
So the simplest scenario is where we
just have one event per activity,
this is so called completion event.
And, if we, we look at many logs,
they don't really have
this transactional information and we
interpret it as being a complete action.
There are also cases when we have
a start event and a complete event.
This is very important if we would like
to measure the duration of an activity.
So one activity has two events,
a start event and a complete event.
But much more involved
scenarios are possible, and
here you can see some examples.
So it may be that an activity was started,
but
then was suspended for some time,
then resumed, possibly also aborted.
So, what we see here
are so-called activity instances.
And we can think of them as paths
through the life cycle model that is
shown at the bottom of this slide.
There can be multiple instances of
the same activity within the same case.
For example, if we would have a loop,
then this would be a typical
pattern that we could see.
We see for activity a, a start and
a complete, then another start and
a complete, etcetera.
But there may also be situations
where it is less clear.
So here we see, an activity,
a, that has two instances because we see
two starts and we see two completes.
But we can assume that this
is what has happened or
we can assume that this
is what has happened.
So it's unclear which start
corresponds to which complete.
So we have these two possibilities.
So how to resolve this possible confusion?
Well one way is that events,
when they are being recorded,
they already have explicit references
to so called activity instances.
So that we know which start,
corresponds to which complete.
It's also possible that we
don't have this information.
And then, when we are replaying the log,
we can simply create it or compute it.
Note that this is just one of several
possible confusions that may arise.
For example,
it may also be that we have two starts and
just one complete, and so
one complete is missing.
How do we create these activity instances?
One can use all kinds of heuristics
to resolve these types of issues.
So let's assume that we have
these activity instances.
If we have these activity instances, there
is a clear relationship between an event
and an activity instance, and activity
instance corresponds to an activity.
So events are related to
activities in this way.
So this is often the key part
of control flow discovery,
that we can relate events to
activities in a process model.
So far we looked at attributes
at the event level.
But as shown on this slide it may also
be the case that the case as a whole,
has attributes.
For example, the type of a customer,
the birth date of a patient,
the flow time of a case.
These are not properties
of an individual event but
of the case as a whole, and
we can exploit them using process mining.
Note that sometimes we will need to
compute these attributes of cases or
events.
So for example, the flow time of
a case can be computed based on
the first event of a case and
the last event of a case.
In general, there may be many attributes
that we would like to compute.
These are called derived attributes,
and they may use information not only
of the given case that we are analyzing,
but of the whole context of that case.
So for example, when an event was being
executed, how busy was it in the process?
How many resources were available?
How many cases were pending?
We can look at the workload
of individual resources and
add that as an attribute of the event so
that we can use this at a later stage.
So it's very important to relate
context information to events and
cases if you would like to do
a more refined type of analysis.
This picture illustrates
why this is crucial.
For example, if we are interested in
understanding why there are delays in
a process and we would look at one case,
for example one customer in isolation,
we would not be able to see and
understand the whole picture.
So we need to related individual events
and cases to the overall context.
Okay, let us now take
a look at a dotted chart.
This is a technique to explore event
data before we start building model.
And it often reveals very intriguing and
interesting information.
So what is the basic
idea of a dotted chart?
We already briefly have seen examples
before, so it is an helicopter view,
showing all the events.
Every dot corresponds to an event and
we have two axes.
On the x-axis we plot time, on the
y-axis we can plot properties of events.
For example, the case they belong to,
the resource that was executing the event,
or the task that was being executed.
We can also color these dots.
It can, for example, be based on the the
person that was executing that event.
It's best to show this using examples,
and in ProM,
there are two plugins
that create dotted chart.
It's a dotted chart plugin,
and it's a so-called viewer.
It's the XDotted chart.
But the concepts that they
use are very similar.
However, sometimes you need to
use one rather than the other.
For example, if you're running
into performance problems.
In the remainder of this lecture
I will focus on the dotted chart.
But in the XDotted chart you will
see very similar functionality.
To illustrate a dotted chart,
let us take a look at an event log.
What it represents is not that important,
but
we have 500 cases and
more than 7500 events.
How can we explore them
using the dotted chart?
Well, to get an understanding
of the process behind,
the dotted charts that we will
see in the remainder, here you
see a process model that was automatically
discovered using the inductive miner.
So if the process starts
with one activity,
then there are three activities
that are concurrent.
But they are all optional.
They can all be bypassed.
Then there is a sequence of activities and
there is a loop.
Sometimes things need to be repeated.
And at the end there is a decision,
accept or reject.
This is a model created
by the inductive miner.
It's a process tree.
We can also visualize it as a BPMN model.
Or we can visualize it as a Petri net.
But the goal of this lecture is
not to look at the process models.
I only show you these models so
that you have an understanding of
the data that we are trying to explore.
Typically you do it in
the other way around.
So here is a dotted chart of
the data set that I just described.
So what we are plotting here,
on the one axis we have the time,
in this case the actual time.
On the other axis, on the y-axis,
every line corresponds to a case.
And the color of the dot is
the activity that is being executed.
So if we now zoom in into one line
we are looking at one case, and
for this one case we can see
a sequence of event that have happened.
And the color is indicating which event it
was, which activity it was that occurred.
We can also take another view.
Now, we again use absolute time
of the x-axis, but on the y-axis,
we are plotting the activities that we
could earlier see in the process model.
So, we can see at what points in time
particular activities were being executed.
And you can see that there
are certain patterns emerging here.
So, we have activities versus actual time,
the color of the dot is the activity.
This is exactly the same diagram but
it is illustrating that we can
change the coloring of the dot.
Now the coloring of the dot refers to the
resource that is executing a particular
activity and you can see a clear
correlation between certain colors and
certain rows,
indicating that particular types of
resources execute particular
sets of activities.
This is the same plot but
now on the y-axis we plot the resources.
The color of the dot is the activity.
So this picture can be seen as
orthogonal to the previous one.
And now we can see at what points in
time our particular resource is busy.
We can change the color of the dots.
So what you see here is that we started
with the coloring based on activities and
now the coloring is based on the resources
executing all the different events.
So far we looked at absolute time.
Here you see a picture where we
are using relative time on the x-axis.
So all the cases start at time 0.
And they all start with the same activity,
as is clearly visible
here by the red line.
But you can also see that certain
cases take a very short time.
The one at the top, versus other
cases take a much longer time.
These are the ones that you
can find at the bottom.
So this gives often an insight
in the duration of the cases.
We can also plot this in a different way.
For example, looking at the activities
that are being executed.
So again, it's the same idea.
But now, rather than cases on
the y-axis, we plot activities.
Again, time is relative,
everything starts at time zero.
This is logical time, so now we do not
care about the actual time differences,
but we look at what is the first event
in a case, what is the second event in
the case, what is the third event in
the case, and plot them in this way.
So, again,
on the y-axis we have cases, but
on the x-axis we have the logical time.
And again,
we can choose the coloring of the dot.
I've showed you
now many dotted charts, so what can we
actually see if we look at this data set?
If you, look at
what you can observe,
is that it is not a straight line.
It's not a straight diagonal line.
So the speed at which cases
is arriving is varying,
as is clearly indicated
here by the yellow line.
We also see these strange gaps.
The first one may not be that clear but
the second and third gap are very obvious.
So let's try to analyze
these in a bit more detail.
So if you look at the first gap and
we zoom in, which you can do with a dotted
chart then what we see is that
there is a period where various
activities are still being executed,
but no decisions are being made.
There's a two month period
without any decisions.
This is creating that cases
take longer as you can see in
the previous slide.
We can zoom into this problem in more
detail by looking at the resources.
And what this diagram shows
is that the resource taking
the decisions was inactive for
this period of two months.
Let us now take a look at the second gap.
Is it the same or
does it have a different reason?
If we take a look at the second gap
then we see that there is a period,
six weeks,
where there is no activity at all.
And at the end of the period we
suddenly see a burst of red dots and
these correspond to the first
activity executed in this process.
So apparently nothing could happen for
awhile.
No new cases were accepted.
And then suddenly many
new cases were created.
So let's try to understand it.
What we see here is that
the first resource and
the fifth resource are the only resources,
executed this initial activity.
And they were absent for a particular
period thereby also causing that
other people in the process could also not
work because no new cases were accepted.
If we look at the third gap,
we can see very similar problems
compared to the first one.
So, still, new cases are arriving but
no decisions are made for
an extended, period.
Let us take a look at another event
log taken from a Dutch housing agency.
So we use the following
settings to plot the chart.
So again we have actual time and
we are looking at every
row corresponds to a case.
And the color of the dot is based
on the activity that is being executed.
So, take a look at this dotted
chart of a real housing agency
and try to see what kind of
strange patterns you see.
Well the first thing that you can note
is that the arrival rate is increasing.
Because the line is curved
it means that more and
more cases at a higher speed
are arriving into this process.
Second you can see that there
are these vertical lines.
If you look carefully you can see
that things are being batched.
So for many cases the same activity is
happening within a very
small period of time.
We can zoom into the latter issue.
So you can
clearly see these patterns.
So, for example,
if we take a look at the top pattern,
then there was this short period of just
a few days where these activities
were being executed for these cases.
And in many of these cases
had been waiting for
a long time for
these activities to happen.
So, these activities correspond
to billing and archiving.
So, apparently here, a resource was not
available for a longer period of time.
And then in a very short period of time,
did all the work that had
been accumulating over weeks.
So in this lecture, we focused on
the input side of process mining.
We've seen that a dotted chart can
provide many interesting insights
that we need to look at before
we start creating models.
What we could also see is
that in event data there is
much more information than just
information about activities.
We have timing information.
We have information about resources,
and we should try to explore these.
So this is what will happen in
the next couple of lectures.
You can take a look at these two chapters
to read more about dotted charts and
analysis of processes using these
other perspectives like resources,
time and data.
Thank you for watching this lecture.
See you next time.
[MUSIC]