[MUSIC]
Welcome to this lecture of the course on
Process Mining, Data Science in Action.
Today, we will dive into
the world of process modeling and
start by introducing
a foundational process notation.
Namely, Petri nets.
On this slide,
you can see an illustration of
a traffic light as a very simple
process consisting of three states.
If we try to represent this in
terms of a Petri net process model,
we get a process model
that looks like this.
So we have the stage red,
green and orange.
We have transitions to switch from
one state to the other state.
So a Petri net is
a network that is static.
It does not change itself.
But in the Petri net we have so
called tokens.
Can be more of them.
In this case there's only one.
And the tokens can move from
one place to another place.
So the circles are places,
the squares are transitions.
And for example,
in this case transition rg can fire,
moving the token from
state red to state green.
The token in place green.
Can again be consumed by transition go,
and
the resulting state is the state orange,
with the token in place orange.
Finally, transition or can fire, resulting
in a state with the token in red.
So the network is static but
tokens can move over the network.
The state in a petri net
is called the marking.
So the initial marking is
the initial state of the process.
So the traffic light, if the initial
state is red we put a token in place red.
This is an example of a reachable marking.
When I was playing the token game,
you could see that we
visited the stage orange.
So, it's a state that is reachable.
This s an example of a state, a marking,
that is not reachable
from the initial state.
Let's take a look at another example.
Now initially there are two
tokens in place red.
So a possible reachable marking is
the marking with the token in green,
and a token in orange.
This is the marking that we
reach if we fire rg twice.
And go once.
So this is a reachable marking.
This is a marking that is not reachable,
that if we start with two tokens in this
particular example, we will always have
two tokens, so we can never end up
with this state having three tokens.
I already mentioned the terms,
enabling and firing.
So a transition is enabled if each of
the input places contains a token.
For example, if p1 contains a token and
p2 is empty, t1 is not enabled,
but if we add a token to p2,
then suddenly t1 is enabled.
And transitions that are enabled can fire.
So what does firing mean?
One can think of firing as
the occurrence of a transition,
the execution of a transition.
And in a petri net, a transition that
fires will consume one token from
each of the input places, and will produce
one token for each of the output places.
And so you have consumption and
production.
So this particular example.
If t1 fires, it will consume
the token from p1 and p2, and
produce tokens on the three output places.
So this example is already illustrating
that the number of tokens may change.
This case, from two to three.
Let's lake, look at several examples
to get a more intuitive feeling of
what these Petri Nets can do.
So in this case,
there are two tokens in p1 and
there are also already tokens
on the output place, p3.
Still t1 can fire.
It consumes a token from each of
the input places and produces a token for
each of the output places.
Note that there were two tokens in p1 and
in this state,
one of these two tokens has been consumed.
We can also have situations where
a place is both input place and
output place of a transition,
p3 is such a place.
Now if in this initial marking
that is shown here, we execute t1.
We will remove a token from p1 and
p2 as before.
But there also has to be a token in p3.
We take a token and
then return it when we execute it.
So the state after
firing t1 is this state.
So although the number of tokens
in p3 didn't change the token was
necessary for t1 to occur.
Let's take a look at some
more complicated situations.
Here you see p1 and p2 having
several tokens, p3 having one token.
So how many times can t1 fire?
In this particular initial marking.
If you look carefully you can see
that p2 is the limiting factor.
There are three tokens there,
so t1 can fire three times and
this results in this marking.
Note that t1 fired three times, and
each of these firings was atomic, so
consumption and
production happened at the same time.
What if there are multiple transitions?
So here we have t1 and t2.
T2 is enabled, but
t1 is not enabled because p1 is empty.
So the only thing that can
happen is that t2 will fire,
moving a token from p2 to p5.
Now we look at the situation where
we have three transitions which can
occur concurrently.
That is a so called,
parallel construction.
So, t1 and t2 and t3 can fire
without influencing each other.
So that means that they can fire in any
order, or perhaps even at the same time.
So look,
let's take a look at a possible scenario.
T2 can fire, then t3 can fire, then t1
can fire, resulting in this final state.
In this particular initial marking.
There are eight reachable states.
Because t1, t2, and
t3 can fire in any order.
In this course, we will typically
assume an interleaving semantics.
That, although things are concurrent, and
in principle can happen at
the same point in time.
We will always assume that they
happen in a particular order.
This is no limitation whatsoever
because all the states that you
can reach when you fire
things concurrently,
you can also reach by firing
transitions in a particular order.
So there is really no difference
from a practical point of view.
Here you can see an example of
the state explosion problem.
So we have now six transitions and each
of the input places contain six tokens.
So think about how many
states can be reached.
What is the number of reachable
markings of this petri net.
Well, more than 100,000
states are reachable.
Because they can fire in any order and
if we
look at every transition,
there are seven possible states
because any of the tokens can be before
the transition or after the transition.
So let's again take a look at
another example, showing let's say,
concurrency and, conflict.
So here we see a situation where t1 and
t2 are both enabled, but
only one of them can occur because they
are fighting for the same token in p2.
So for example if t1 occurs, this is
the state that we will end up with.
But t2 can no longer happen.
So t1 disabled t2.
Let's take a look at this example.
So in this example,
we see that there are three tokens in p1,
and they can be consumed by t1 and t2.
So the question is how many
final markings there are.
Think about this and
what you will see is that each of
the tokens can be consumed by
any of the two transitions.
So this yields, in total,
four different states.
One state, where t1 has happened three
times, and t2 has happened zero times.
One state, where t1 happened twice,
and t2 happened once, etcetera.
This is another example.
Again, think about what is the number
of possible final markings.
And if you look carefully you will
see that p1 is a limiting place for
t1, and p3 is a limiting place for t2.
So in this case,
there is only one possible final marking,
because there are sufficient tokens in p2.
In fact one token remains there.
If we look at the situation where
there are more tokens in p1 and p3,
than there are in p2,
then p2 becomes a limiting factor.
And if we look at the number
of possible final markings,
we will find that there are two
possible final markings.
This is one of them.
In this case, t1 fired twice,
t2 fired only once, or
you can have this state, where t2
fired twice, and t1 fired only once.
And these are both final markings but
nothing can happen anymore.
Let's now revisit our
traffic light example.
We are now interested in the question
of modeling two traffic lights.
How do we model two traffic lights?
Well there are two viewpoints.
One viewpoint is that we simply
take a copy, so we take
two copies of the traffic light example
and put them next to each other.
Another way that we can model two traffic
lights is by simply putting two tokens in
place red.
Each representing a traffic light.
These are two possible ways
of modeling a traffic light.
But in the first traffic light the
different traffic lights are identifiable.
We can talk about one is red and
the other is green.
In the second one that is not possible.
So if we look at a number of reachable
markings, there is a difference.
In the first model there
are nine reachable markings.
In the second model, there are
fewer reachable markings because we
cannot distinguish, for example,
between one traffic light being green and
the other being orange, and reversed.
So that's why we have less
reachable markings.
If we take a look at the example,
by just simply copying the two
traffic lights next to each other,
one can see a problem.
Both can switch to green at the same time,
yielding to all kinds of problems.
So we would like to avoid the situation
where both traffic lights switch to green.
In fact we want to ensure that
at any point in time one of
the two traffic lights is red.
So how to do that?
How to make them safe?
So we have two concurrent processes and
we want to synchronize them in some way.
That they exhibit a safe behavior.
In other words,
we want to limit the set of reachable
markings to the markings that are safe.
Well, the way to do that.
If we, don't want to,
enforce a certain order on the way that
they switch to green, is this solution.
So carefully look at
place x in this example.
This place is ensuring that only
one of the two traffic lights can
switch to green.
If the traffic light switches to green.
The token from x will be removed.
There by disabling the other traffic
lights to also switch to green.
And then, the token is only returned
to x once the traffic light,
that was first green, then orange,
switches back to red.
Only if it's red again,
there is a token in x and
the whole process starts again
from that initial marking.
So this is a safe way of
modeling traffic lights, but
it yields the situation that
it is nondeterministic.
It is unclear which of the two traffic
lights will switch to green first.
It is even possible that always the same
traffic light will switch to green.
And that the second traffic light
will never switch to green.
That is allowed by this model.
So a question that you could ask
yourself, if you take a look at
this model, how to make a traffic light
where things all are alternating?
So first,
the first traffic light switches to green.
Then the second, then again the first,
then the second, etcetera.
Well this can be modeled by splitting
this place x, in two places.
And these places,
exhibit the following behavior,
they trigger the other traffic
light to switch to green.
For example the token in x that
you can see in the current state,
it is triggering the second
traffic light to switch to green.
And when the second traffic light
has gone through the cycle it will
put a token in y, thereby
triggering the first traffic light.
And this way they will alternate.
So we no longer have
a non-deterministic system.
We now have a process where the next
state is always fixed and clear.
So this gave you some more
insight into process modeling and
particular petri nets.
In the next lecture, we will tell more
about this very foundational notation
that is very important to understand,
before we look at process discovery and
other process finding techniques.
Thank you for watching,
and hope to see you soon.
[MUSIC]