[MUSIC]
Welcome to this lecture of the course of
process mining data science in action.
Today we will focus on the class
of process models having a clear
start and end.
Traces in an event log correspond to
process instances of such models.
On this slide,
you see an example of a Workflow Net.
This is a Petri net that has
a well-defined start place and
a well-defined end place.
Moreover, it should be free of obvious
problems like livelocks and deadlocks.
And later we will introduce
the notion of soundness.
Traces in a log need to go from
the initial state to the final state.
So, this is a class of models
that is not only used for
process mining, but is also widely used
in the area of workflow management and
business process management.
So let's take a step back.
Business process management, BPM.
What is this?
This is the linking pin between IT and
management science.
And it has a long tradition.
The main goal is to ensure efficiency.
Already in the 18th century, Adam Smith
showed that by the division of labor,
you could make processes
more efficient and cheaper.
Taylor introduced
scientific management.
Henry Ford, we all know introduced
the notion of mass production,
when he made the T-Ford.
But the greatest breakthrough that we find
if we look at business process management,
how to make things more efficient,
started in the 1950s when information
systems and computers became omnipresent.
Currently, we can see a new wave.
Tremendous amounts of data are available.
So we can take BPM to the next
level where data is the new oil.
This is a variant of
the well-known BPM lifecycle.
If you look at the small
circle in the middle,
you can see that a BPM project,
if you want to make processes better,
more efficient, starts with a design or
redesign phase.
Then you implement or
configure an information system based
on the processes you have designed.
And then you run these processes, and
maybe you need to adjust them on the fly.
If you look at this well-known BPM
lifecycle from an analysis perspective,
you can look at model-based analysis,
which you use mostly in the design or
re-design phase.
And you can look at data-based analysis.
And process mining is typically focusing
on the red part in this diagram.
Learning from processes
while they are running.
So, what is the role of processes in BPM,
or work flow management.
First of all, process models
are used to reason about processes.
Where are the bottle necks?
How can we make things cheaper?
But models are also used inside processes.
For example, to support decisions.
Like will I accept this claim or not?
Here you see a list of typical ways
that process models may be used.
To discuss responsibilities and
bottlenecks.
To analyze compliance.
To predict possible problems in
the future using simulation.
And last but not least,
to configure information systems.
For example using workflow or
BPM technology.
Unfortunately, many models
are being used in practice.
Here you see a picture of the Tower of
Babel, indicating that there are so
many languages and
that sometimes it is a bit confusing.
In this course we will see several
different process modeling languages but I
would like to stress that the differences
between these languages are minimal.
They're all based on the same concept.
Here you see three types of process
models that one frequently sees.
The top shows the so called BPMN model.
The Business Process Model and
Notation that expresses
behavior of cases starting in initial
state, leading to some final state.
Below that you see a so-called
Event-Driven Process Chain, and
this is the notation typically used
in the context of systems like SAP.
At the bottom you see Petri nets,
and today we will focus on
a particular variant of Petri nets,
namely workflow nets.
The representations look different,
but they all try to express the same
phenomena, and in the end they
all generate traces of events.
We can all record event logs for these
types of processes if they are executed.
We've already seen a lot of Petri nets.
We know that they
are composed of places and
transitions and arcs and
tokens are flowing through them.
We've seen that before.
So here you see an example run,
just to refresh our mind a bit.
So, from the initial state with the token
on the start place, we can execute
different activities through firing
transitions until we reach the end.
So, this is one of many
possible firing sequences.
Before, we also saw the notion of a
reachability graph and a transition system.
So the Petri net shown here
generates this transition system,
which captures all the behavior.
And the trace that I just showed you, is
one path through this transition system.
So let's now focus on the question,
if we have a workflow net,
so a model with a start place and
an end place, is it a good model?
So here you see an example,
and please think about this.
Is this a good process model?
If you look carefully,
you will see that that is not the case,
because there is a possible deadlock.
If we take the loop back, we may end up
in the situation with just a token at c3
which corresponds to a deadlock.
Let's take a look at
another process model.
Again, take a minute to
look at this model, and
try to tell whether this
model is a good model or not.
If you look closely, you will see that in
the beginning there is an AND-split, but
it doesn't really
correspond to an AND-join.
So, again, we see that there is a problem.
And if you draw the reachability
graph of this model,
you will see that this doesn't have
the behavior that you expect it to have.
Let's take a look at another
variant of the same process.
Is this a good model?
It doesn't have the problems
that we have seen before, but
there is another problem in this model,
that the task pay compensation,
which is modeled by the transition
at the end, can never be fired.
It's dead.
You can never reach the state where
both of the input places are marked.
Let's take a look at another model.
So, carefully look at this model.
Is this a correct process model?
In terms that it doesn't have any of
the anomalies that we discussed before.
Yes, it has all the desired properties.
But one may ask yourself,
why is this a good model?
What is the criterion that we are using?
Well the criterion that we
are using is soundness, and
it is defined on top of WorkFlow
nets that we already introduced.
So a WorkFlow net has one start place,
one end place,
and all the transitions and all the places
are on a path from start to end.
Based on this,
we can define the notion of soundness.
A WorkFlow net is sound if and only if
the following four properties hold.
The first property expresses
that places should be safe.
At most, one token should be at
a place at any point in time.
There should be proper completion,
meaning that the moment we
put a token on the end place,
all other places should be empty.
We should have the option to complete.
No matter what we do, we should
always be able to reach the state,
the marking,
with just a token on the final place.
And last but not least,
there should not be any dead parts.
So all the parts of the process model
should potentially be activated.
So there should be scenarios
where they play a role.
So these are the four minimal
requirements that any WorkFlow net should
satisfy in order to be sound.
So let's take again a look
at several examples, and
try to see whether these models
satisfy these four properties.
So here we see again,
a process model, does it satisfy these
four properties, making it sound?
The answer is no.
The rows highlighted here in green,
correspond to properties that hold for
this particular model.
But we also see two properties,
proper completion and
option to complete, that do not hold.
And we can see that, because the state
that is now indicated by the red tokens,
is a reachable state, and from this state,
we can no longer go to the situation
where there's just a token on p6.
Let's take a look at another example.
Is this model sound?
Again we can look at
its reachability graph,
look at the traces that it generates.
And if we do that,
we see that only the last property,
absence of deadlock parts, holds.
All the other properties
are not satisfied.
Well, it's easy to see,
because once you put the token in p3,
transition t3 can fire any number of
times, and there is no way that you
can remove these tokens and
go back to the final state.
Yeah,
so it's clear that these
properties are violated.
If we take a look at this model.
Again, think about it.
Is this model sound or not?
Then you see that the top three properties
hold, but transition t3 is dead.
It cannot be executed.
So it's not a sound model.
Now we can take a look
at this model again.
Again, we can check whether it's sound,
and in this case,
we can see that all the four properties
are satisfied, making the model sound.
So on these toy examples it is very
easy to see whether things are sound or
not, but
in general it's much more difficult.
But there are good analysis techniques
to check soundness of such models.
Let's take a look at some more examples.
So, this shows a WorkFlow
net that is not safe.
So it's not sound because one of the four
properties is being violated, and
you can see the markings
here that can be reached.
So it's not sound.
This is another more tricky example
where there is no option to complete
because we can reach the
the state with just a token in place c3.
So then decision is not enabled, and
we get stuck somewhere in
the middle of the process.
So again it is not sound.
So, if we look at these properties,
you may have noticed that the option
to complete implies proper completion.
So in other words, if proper
completion does not hold, so there
is a token on the final place, but still
something is remaining in the process.
If it does not hold, then also
the option to complete does not hold.
And it's easy to see, because the only
way that a token in the middle of
this cloud can disappear is
to go to the final place, but
then there would be two
tokens in this final place.
So, if we have the option to complete,
we automatically have proper completion.
So when checking the model,
we don't need to look at proper completion
because it holds automatically.
There is a logical connection between the
Petri net properties that we have seen in
earlier lectures, and
the property of soundness that we
are looking at in this lecture.
So this is a Petri net, a WorkFlow net.
We can short-circuit it by adding
a transition from the final
part of the process to
the initial part of the process.
So in other words, when we reach the end,
we go back to the beginning.
This is the so-called
short-circuited WorkFlow net.
And we have the very nice property net
that a WorkFlow net is sound, if and
only if the corresponding short-circuited
Petri net is live and bounded.
If we also want to have safety, the first
property, it should also be safe.
But boundedness is sufficient
for the next three activities.
So what are the main types
of model-based analysis?
At a higher level we can
distinguish two types of analysis.
verification, like the soundness
checks we just discussed.
Performance analysis,
often using techniques like simulation or
Markov analysis.
These are the typical types
of analysis that people do
when they talk about
business process management.
However, just looking at
the models is not sufficient.
All these analysis techniques,
they rely on the quality of the model.
The model has to represent reality
properly, otherwise any
analysis result doesn't have any value.
Whereas if we look in practice,
often the model that people make by hand,
have a poor alignment with reality,
making the conclusions very unreliable.
So process mining aims to address
this problem by establishing a very
tight connection between models and
the actual event data.
In the next lecture,
we will really start talking about
concrete process mining algorithms.
In this case a discovery technique.
We will talk in the next lecture
about the Alpha Algorithm.
The goal of the Alpha Algorithm
is to discover WorkFlow nets.
So the types of process models
that we have discussed in this
lecture from event logs.
So we start from an event log,
as a multiset of traces, and
from this multiset of traces, we try to
automatically learn a process model
expressed in terms of a WorkFlow net.
And you can see an example here.
In the last couple of lectures we have
been talking about many things related to
process models.
So chapter two is the central chapter
where all of these things will
be discussed.
Thank you for watching this lecture and
hope to see you in the next lecture.
[MUSIC]