[MUSIC]
Welcome to this lecture.
Today we will learn the Alpha algorithm.
This is the first concrete discovery
technique presented in this
course on process mining.
Here you see a picture that we
have shown several times before.
It is showing play-in,
play-out, and replay.
So process discovery
corresponds to play-in.
If you take a look at this picture
that by now should look very familiar.
We are now focusing on the green
arrow indicated discovery.
So from an event log, we will
automatically learn a process model.
In our case, for
the Alpha algorithm, a Petri net.
So the Alpha algorithm was the first or
one of the first algorithms being
able to discover concurrency.
And so from event logs we want to learn
models that can have loops, that
can have parallel parts, that can have
choices, and the Alpha algorithm was
the first algorithm being able to do that
while guaranteeing certain properties.
So what kind of input does
the Alpha algorithm use?
We have seen event logs like this, and
when we apply the Alpha algorithm and
we just focus on control flow.
So we ignore the resources and
other data elements.
We ignore the actual timestamps
at which the events take place.
We only care about their ordering.
Also, we don't use the case ID or
properties of the case.
We only look at the order of
activities within a particular case.
So we can convert such an event
log to a multiset of traces.
And each trace is a sequence of
activity names, as you can see here.
So this is kind of based
on a real life log.
We can also take a look at
a more abstract example.
Here we see a log L1 which
contains six traces.
You can think of them as six different cases.
And they are modeled as
a sequence of activity names.
So, the sequence a, b, c,
d was executed three times.
There are three traces of that type.
So an event log is a multiset of traces,
because the same trace can appear multiple
times, and a trace is a sequence of
activity names where we abstract
from all the other attributes.
We will use these other
attributes in later lectures.
So what is the goal of
the Alpha algorithm?
If we feed it a log like L1 we want to
automatically learn a process model
as is shown here that allows for
the behavior that we have seen in the log.
So that's like a minimal
desire that we have.
Here you see another example
an event log which is a bit bigger.
If we feed this event log
to the Alpha algorithm,
it will automatically learn this process
model, which indeed captures all
the behaviors that we have seen,
but also more behaviors.
because there is a loop, so
in principle this model allows for
infinitely many traces, but it is
based on a finite number of examples.
In this course we will not
care too much about notations,
we have been talking about
notations in earlier lectures.
You can represent
a behavior as a Petri net.
You can represent it as a BPMN model.
You can represent it as an EPC,
as a UML activity diagram.
We do not care.
We just want to capture the behavior.
So here you see two process models
that express exactly the same in
two different languages.
Here you see another
pair of process models.
One in terms of Petri nets, the other
in terms of BPMN, that express exactly
the same behavior and can replay
the behavior that we have seen in log L2.
Process discovery is
incredibly challenging.
One has many competing requirements, and
the four main quality criteria for a
discovered model are shown in this slide.
Just like you need several
forces to keep a plane into the air.
We need to work with several forces
when we discover a process model.
In this lecture,
we will mostly focus on fitness, the
ability to replay the observed behavior.
But you'll learn in later lectures,
we will see that it is not that simple.
Okay, let's start.
Let's take a look at the Alpha algorithm.
The starting point for the Alpha
algorithm are ordering relations.
So, we do not care about frequencies.
We do not care about other attributes.
In this case, we are only interested in
seeing that in the log, we could see that,
that there was a sequence a, b,
c, d and that we could see
that a was followed by b.
And b was followed by c and
c was followed d.
This relationship is
called direct succession.
There was at least one case where
x was directly followed by y.
So if we look at this event log
we can find these relations.
So, for example,
if we take a look at the top one
it says that there was at least one
case where a was directly followed by b.
That's highlighted in the diagram.
Then there is a second relation.
It's called causality and
it is depicted by an arrow.
This means that x is followed by y,
but y is never followed by x.
So we can again take a look at our very
simple event log, and we will see that
a is sometimes directly followed by b,
but b is never followed by a.
So we derive this a arrow b property,
causality.
If the direct succession
relation holds in both directions,
we say that things are in parallel.
So we say x parallel y if x is
sometimes followed by y and
y is sometimes followed by x.
So again if we look at the model we
can see that, that holds for b and c.
So b is sometimes followed by c and
c is sometimes followed by b.
The last relationship holds if x is
never directly followed by y and
y is never directly followed by x, we then
say that there is a choice relationship.
So for example,
if we take a look at the log, and
we derive the relationships we will
see that b is never followed by e.
And e is never followed by b, so we say
that they are in a choice relationship.
These relations are used to
learn patterns in the process.
So if we see a is sometimes followed by b,
but
b is never followed by a, this is the
Petri net pattern that we expect to see.
A sequence.
If we see that a is sometimes followed
by b, but never the other way around,
a is sometimes followed by c, but
c is never followed by a, and b and
c never follow one another,
we learn this XOR-split pattern.
So apparently after doing a,
there is a choice between b or c.
Note that if we replay
this Petri net we will
get exactly these types of relationships.
The corresponding part to the XOR-split
is the XOR-join that you can see here.
And if you look at the ordering relations
I think it's fairly obvious.
So, b has a causal relationship with d,
c has a causal relationship with d,
but b and c never follow one another.
If we look at concurrency we
see the following behavior.
If we would look at an AND-split where
a is followed by both b and c but
they can be done in any order.
Perhaps at the same time.
Then we will find that a is
sometimes followed by b.
But never the other way around.
A is sometimes followed by c,
but c is never followed by a.
And b is sometimes followed by c.
And c is sometimes followed by b.
So if you would replay the token
game on top of this fragment,
you would indeed see that
these relationships hold.
So this is an indication that
a process has such a pattern.
Again, we can look at
the corresponding join pattern.
So what we now see is that again, b and
c can follow one another in any order,
and we have observed at least
once that b was followed by c.
And at least once that
c was followed by b.
Typically in different traces.
And we sometimes see that b is followed
by d but not the other way around, and
sometimes c is followed by d,
not the other way around.
So based on these patterns we can
automatically construct a Petri net.
And so here, we revisit the example and
you can see that these
patterns are there but actually in this
example, it's already a bit more involved.
And the Alpha algorithm can also
handle many more situations.
So let's take a look at these ordering
relations in a bit more detail.
When we take an event log we can
talk about so-called footprints and
that's the matrix that
you see on this slide.
Every cell in this matrix has
one of these four relationships.
So we either have a causality
in one direction,
a causality in the other direction, the
two activities never follow one another,
or they sometimes follow each
other in one direction and
other times in another direction.
These are the only four
possibilities that we have.
So in this example,
a is sometimes followed by c, but
c is never followed by a.
So if we take a look at the event log and
the corresponding process model,
we will see that both actually
have exactly the same footprint.
So if we would analyze the process
model and look at all the traces and
create this footprint based
on all the possible traces,
this would be the matrix that we see.
So model and event log agree on
the footprint, indicating that
they have from a behavioral point of view,
things in common.
We can take a look at another log.
A more involved example.
And again, we see the same phenomena.
The event log and the process model
have exactly the same footprint.
Suggesting that this model is indeed
the model of the behavior that we have seen.
So, to summarize this part,
when we talk about footprints,
we see certain patterns that
are reflected both in the log and
in the model, and these are the starting
point for the Alpha algorithm.
The Alpha algorithm is
a very basic algorithm.
It contains only eight lines but
they look scary at first sight.
So I will walk through these
eight lines step by step.
And it's surprising that with
such a simple algorithm,
you can actually discover such
a wide range of different processes.
Processes having concurrency, processes
having loops, processes having choices.
All of these things can be discovered
by this very basic algorithm.
But it looks very scary, I have to admit,
so let's walk through it step by step.
So we start with an event log,
which is a multi-set of traces.
And if we construct
a Petri net using the Alpha algorithm,
the first step that we take
is that we scan the event log
to see what are the activities or what
are the transitions that are appearing.
So we just look at the symbols
that occur in the event log.
So these will be the activities
in the process model,
each corresponding to a transition.
That's why we use the symbol T here.
Then we have the initial transitions, TI.
These are the transitions that
are the first in a trace.
So we can look at all the traces and
look at
what are the different activities that
happen in the first position of the trace.
Similarly we can look at TO,
the set of final activities.
End activities that happen
at the end of a trace.
So we have all activities.
Activities that happen at the beginning,
and
activities that happen at the very end.
After we have done this,
we have the key step to discover places.
If you think about process
discovery in terms of
Petri nets it's all about
discovering places.
And we will discover places by
identifying sets of transitions, A and
B, where A are the input transitions for
the place and B are the output
transitions for the place.
And we do that in a number of steps.
So this is the fourth line of
the description of the Alpha algorithm.
As I said, it,
it looks perhaps a bit scary.
But if you look at the intuitive idea
behind it, it's really simple.
So we are trying to find two
sets of activities, A and B.
And these activities should
have the following property.
If I take two activities in the set A,
they should never follow one another.
If I take two activities in the set B,
they should also never follow one another.
Even if we take the same activity,
it should never follow itself.
And so that's one requirement.
The second requirement.
If we take any activity in the set A and
we take any activity in the set B,
there should always be a direct
succession between these two activities.
So there should be at least one position
in the log where the element of
A is followed by the element of B and
that should hold for all combinations.
So that's what it says
in this fourth line.
So if we take a look at the footprint
matrix we can recognize this structure
because we are looking for a set a and
b where things never follow one another.
And we are looking for these other
connections where any element of a is
directly followed by any element of b,
but never the other way around.
That is what is indicated
here in the matrix.
So that is what we are looking for
but that is not sufficient.
Line five of the algorithm says that
we should only look at the sets A and
B that are maximal.
And it's very easy to see
why that is the case.
Suppose that we have this pair of
set of activities A and set of activities
B, having all these requirements.
Then if we remove a node in A or B.
Or we remove
the corresponding arcs.
What we see then is that
still the properties hold.
So any, in a way any subset
of this AB relationship
automatically also has the properties
that we listed before.
So here you can see two examples of A and
B sets which are smaller and
automatically satisfy all the requirements
as long as A and B are not empty.
So that means that we
would potentially get many,
many places and we don't want that.
So we only retain the maximal
elements of this set X.
And that is what we do in step five,
yielding a set Y, which will
correspond to the internal places.
And so, we delete all the elements
from X that are not maximumal.
In the sense what I've just discussed.
Now the remainder of the algorithm
is fairly simple.
So PL is the set of places.
So all the maximal pairs that we have just
discovered in step five are places and
we add an initial place I and
a final place O.
It's very easy to understand, yeah?
So it's important to see that the really
interesting part happens when we
look at these sets A and B, and thereby
derive the places that we want to see.
Then we take a look at the arcs.
And we already have the transitions,
we already have the places.
Here you see the arcs.
So here, you can see all
connections from the initial place,
I, to all the initial transitions in TI.
From all the transitions in the set TO.
So the transitions corresponding to
the activities that happen at the end.
And all internal places, and internal
places are represented by sets A and
B and the connections
are made accordingly.
So this is making the connections, but
the real logic was already
in steps four and five.
Where we identify the sets A and B.
Finally, we return the Petri net with
places P, transitions D, and arcs F.
And we get the result that we're after.
So let's replay these eight lines.
For example that we have seen before.
So this is the log.
This is the footprint matrix.
So we can see all the relationships.
Then we execute the different steps
of the algorithm where the key
steps are steps four and steps five.
So here you seek the relationship X.
They contain elements
which are not maximal,
some of these elements
are contained in other elements.
So we remove them as is indicated here.
Then we get a set Y, and
these correspond to the internal places.
So, for example, we can see that
there will be a place having as
input a and as output b and e.
And that is what you can see in the,
in the corresponding diagram.
So if we feed an event log to
a process mining tool like ProM,
which is supporting the Alpha algorithm,
we can load the log.
The log that I just used.
And indeed ProM returns
the model that we just saw.
So here you can see the Alpha algorithm
in action on a very tiny log.
Let's take a look at some other examples.
So, let's take a look at log
L3 that is shown here, and
the first question would be.
To apply the Alpha algorithm, what is
the footprint matrix of this event log?
Try to draw it.
If you do so, you will see this.
This is the footprint matrix
that is resulting from it.
So.
For example if you look at the row a and
column a we can see that a is
never followed by itself.
Which is a clear thing that
one can see in the log.
If you would look at row a and column b
we see that a is sometimes followed
by b but never the other way around.
Look at the log and
you can see that is indeed the case.
And we can look at all the roles for
example if we look at c and
d we will see that c is
sometimes followed by d and
sometimes d is followed by c,
suggesting the concurrency relationship.
So first we built a footprint matrix and
then we apply the alpha
algorithm that we have seen before.
So, given this footprint matrix,
we can execute the eight steps.
So, please try to do this yourself.
What is the model that
is resulting from this?
If you apply all the different
steps then this is
the process model that you discover.
And so you need to check it yourself
that this is indeed the result that will
be returned.
So if we feed this log again to ProM,
again we see exactly the model that
was predicted by the Alpha algorithm.
Because ProM implements exactly the eight
line algorithm that we have seen before.
Let's take a look at another event log.
So now we see four different traces
happening at different frequencies.
So if we take this event log
we will discover this process
model using the Alpha algorithm.
And take a look at the places and
the names that they have and
identify these sets a and
b and you can see that this is
actually the model that can
be derived based on this log.
And also if you look at this
model we can reproduce all
the traces that we see in the log and
nothing more.
And ProM indeed returns the same model.
Here we see another example.
I'm trying to show you as
many examples as possible that you
get a feeling for when this algorithm
indeed produces the right result.
So if we take this event log you
can see the footprint matrix.
We can apply the algorithm.
So here you see all of
the eight steps listed.
Where the steps to distinguish the X and
Y are the most crucial steps.
Then we will get this Petri net.
And again, we can see that this
is indeed a petri net that is
able to reproduce the observed behavior.
But also a bit more because the,
the patterns in the log
suggest that there is a loop.
So in summary, the Alpha algorithm
provides a basic discovery approach.
It has many limitations.
I didn't talk about these yet, I will
talk about them in the next lecture.
But still the algorithm is very
useful because it illustrates the key
ingredients of process discovery.
Discovering loops, discovering
concurrency, discovering choices.
It's all in there.
So for understanding process discovery
it's very important that you
practice with different examples,
apply the Alpha algorithm and
you will gain a better understanding
of the difficulties that one
encounters if one would like to discover
a process model just based on examples.
So we now move to chapter five.
And chapter five describes in
lots of detail with lots of
examples what the Alpha
algorithm is actually doing.
Thank you for watching and
I hope to see you in the next lecture.
[MUSIC]