[MUSIC]
Welcome to this lecture of the course on
process mining, data science in action.
Now that you are able to read and
create petri nets,
we start looking at properties like
deadlocks, liveness and boundedness.
What you see on this slide
is the reachability graph,
of the Petri net that we
have been showing before.
One can think of a reachability graph as
a transition system of a particular type,
having one specific initial state,
being the initial marking.
So this is a finite reachability graph,
but a Petri net
may also have a corresponding reachability
graph that is infinitely large.
So here the number of tokens in Petri,
is unbounded.
It can grow to any number by
just executing the cycle t1, t2.
So the reachability graph is infinite.
Having reachability graphs
that are infinitely large,
triggers the interesting
question of boundedness.
So a place is called k-bounded,
if there is no
reachable marking where there are more
than k tokens in this particular place.
If all the places of a Petri net are
k-bounded, then we say that the Petri net,
as a whole, is k-bounded.
We also say that the Petri net is
bounded if there exists such a k.
So if you take a look at this example,
one can see that p1 is two bounded,
p2 is also two bounded,
but p3 is unbounded.
So let's take a look at this
model in a bit more detail.
So p1 is 2-bounded.
Why is it 2-bounded?
Because the total number
of tokens in p1 and
p2 together can never
grow into more than two.
Only a token can disappear from
these two places by executing t3.
So two is an upper bound.
The same holds for p2.
p3, on the other hand, is unbounded,
because if we execute t1,
t2, t1, t2,
we can get any number of tokens in p3.
So the whole petri net is
unbounded because p3 is unbounded.
Safeness, is a particular
type of boundedness it is
boundedeness where k is equal to one.
If all the places never have a two or
more tokens, we call it a safe Petri net.
So if we take a look at
this example that we
have seen before then this Petri
net having this initial marking
is a safe Petri net because none of the
places can ever have two or more tokens.
If we take a look at this initial marking,
on the other hand,
we will see that the Petri net is
still bounded having this initial
marking, but it is not safe anymore.
It is now too bounded, and
if you carefully take a look at
the Petri net, you will see that it
is possible to put two tokens in x.
So x is two bounded but is not safe.
So that was the property of boundedness.
Now let's take a look at
the property of deadlock.
So, we say that a marking is dead
if no transition is enabled in it.
We say that the Petri net
has a potential deadlock,
if there is a reachable marking that
is dead where nothing can happen.
So a deadlock-free Petri net, for
any reachable state,
it enables at least one transition.
So let's now take a look at the example.
Example that I showed before.
This example has many deadlocks.
And here you see
a visualisation of one of them.
We can go through the loop t1,
t2 as many times as we want, but
the moment that we execute t3,
we end up in a deadlock.
So there are many
possible dead locks here.
So let's take a look at some example petri
nets and try to look at whether they
are dead lock free or not and
whether they are unbounded or not.
So, this petri net,
what kind of properties does it have.
Think a bit about it.
Okay.
So if we look at this Petri net and
we think of possible initial markings,
then this is a possible initial marking,
such that the Petri net is unbounded and
not deadlock-free.
So what we see is that we can go through
the loop as many times as we want,
put any number of tokens in p3.
So it is unbounded, but
it has a deadlock because the moment
we execute t3, we get stuck.
Another initial marking is the initial
marking that you see here.
Now there is only a token in p3.
So that means that none of
the transitions is enabled.
So the initial marking is already
a deadlock, but the model is now bounded.
Now one can start looking for
models, that don't have a deadlock.
That was part of the question.
Such models do not exist, because in this
Petri net, any initial marking that you
choose will have a deadlock.
Because by executing t3,
you can remove all
the tokens from the loop involving p1 and
p2, ending up in a deadlock.
Let's take a look at
the traffic light example, but
now without an initial marking.
Please, try to provide an initial marking
such that we see all combinations of being
bounded or not, bounded, deadlock-free or
not being deadlock-free.
Do all of these Petri nets exist?
Well, let's take a look at some examples.
So this is an initial marking
where the resulting Petri net
is bounded and deadlock-free.
This, in fact, is the state that
we have seen many times before.
This is another initial marking
that is immediately a deadlock so
the initial marking no transition
is enabled, so it is bounded, but
it is definitely not deadlock-free.
Because the initial marking
is already a deadlock.
Now we can start looking for
initial markings where
the resulting model is unbounded.
But in this case,
such a marking does not exist.
Because the total number of
tokens will always be limited,
no matter what initial marking we choose.
So after explaining what
a deadlock is,
we look at a more difficult property.
And that's the property of liveness.
So liveness can be defined as follows.
A transition is live if
from any reachable marking
it is possible to reach a marking
that enables this transition.
So, no matter what you do you can
fire any sequence of transitions
it is always possible to go back to
some marking where t is enabled.
So then we call a transition live.
A Petri net as a whole is live
if all transitions are live.
What is a logical consequence
of liveness is that if
a Petri net is live by definition,
it will al so be deadlock-free.
However, the reverse does not hold.
A petri net that is deadlock-free
does not have to be live.
And you can see an example
already on this slide.
If we look at this initial marking,
than in this initial marking,
the transitions corresponding to
traffic light one are all live.
And the transitions corresponding
to the second traffic light,
they are all not live.
They can never be executed.
So this is an example of a Petri net
that is deadlock free, but that is not live.
Showing that a live Petri net
is always deadlock free but
the reverse does not have to hold.
Liveness is a difficult property.
So, to illustrate this a bit further,
one can look at this diagram.
The blue dot indicates initial marking.
From the initial marking,
we can follow any sequence of activities.
Then we end up in the red marking.
What liveness now says is that no matter
what state we have reached, so no matter
what red marking we look at, it's
always possible from such a red marking
to go back to the space of markings
that are indicated by the green oval.
Where transition t is enabled.
In other words,
no matter what you do, it is always
possible to enable this transition.
If that property holds for
all transitions,
we say that the petri net is live.
So, now we get into more complicated and
also a bit artificial
petri nets but they let you think
about what is property x lead means.
So if we take a look at this
petri net is it bounded,
is it safe, is it deadlock free,
is it live.
Try to answer these questions for
this particular petri net.
Here is the answer.
The Petri net is not bounded,
because if we go through the cycle t1,
t2, t3, t1, t2, t3 we can repeat that as
many times as we want and in every round,
we put an additional token in p4.
So, p4 is unbounded, so by definition,
the Petri net cannot be safe.
Then the question is, is the,
Petri net deadlock free?
Well if you look carefully you can see
that the initial marking that is shown
here you can execute t1 and
then immediately execute transition t4.
Then you get stuck in the state
with just the token and t2.
So this is a deadlock.
So because there is a deadlock,
definitely the Petri net is not live.
Let's take a look at another example.
Again we have the same questions.
Is this Petri net in this particular
initial marking, is it bounded,
safe, deadlock free, and or live?
Again.
Think about what the answer
to this question is.
The answer is that the Petri
net is bounded but not safe.
And you can easily see that.
In the initial marking,
you can already execute t1, putting
a second token in p4, so
p4 is not safe, but it is two bounded
because there is no way of ever putting
more than two tokens in p4,
because in every round we add
the token and we again remove it.
The second question was, is the Petri
net deadlock-free, and, or, live.
Well, the Petri net is deadlock-free,
but it is not live.
You can see that if t5 occurs, then you
remove a token from this outer circle,
thereby not allowing the system to
go again through the cycle, t1,
t2, t3, et cetera.
So, t5 will disable behavior, but
there will always be a token in p4,
so t4 will always be enabled.
So this is another example of a situation
where the model is deadlock-free,
but not live.
If this is not clear to you, please try
to draw the reachability graph, and
you will see that these
properties are actually the case.
So, the reachability graph is
a special kind of transition system.
Firing sequences of
the petri net correspond to
path in the transition system.
The transition system is composed
of states and transitions.
So the states correspond to markings,
the transitions corresponds to
the transitions in the petri net but
in a reachability graph,
many transitions can refer to
the same transition in the Petri net.
Whereas in the Petri net, we only have
one transition with the same label.
In a transition system there may be one or
more initial states, and
zero or more final states.
This is more general than a Petri net
where we always have one initial marking,
and we really do not
talk about final states.
But these final states are important
if we talk about process mining.
In this particular example you see
a model that has one initial state and
has two final states, as indicated.
So, if we understand what a transition
system is that may have multiple initial
states and multiple final states we can
define the notion of complete traces.
So complete traces go from
the initial state to the final state.
So we only consider cases that go from
the initial state to the final state,
to one of the final states.
So this is an example of a complete trace.
So we execute a.
Then we do g once for a second time.
Then we do c, and then we do e.
So this goes from the initial state
to one of the final states.
This is another complete trace.
This is an example.
a and then four g's,
is an incomplete trace because we
are in state s2 and did not yet
reach one of the final states.
So it's an incomplete trace.
bf is another example
of an incomplete trace.
So a transition system,
may have infinitely many states, but
even if we look at the finer
transition system,
there may be infinitely many complete or
incomplete traces.
In this case, the transition system is
finite, but because of the loop involving
g, we can have infinitely many traces,
being complete or not.
So, let's take a look at the question.
How many complete traces are there
in this small transition system?
Please think about this.
There are five, complete traces.
And, it's easy to see.
Just replay on the transition system and
you will see that indeed, these are the
five complete traces that are there.
That go from one of the initial
states to one of the final states.
So far we have been talking
about transition systems,
let's now go back to Petri nets and
if we look at Petri nets and
we define Petri nets with a set
of final markings, then we
can convert that into a transition system
that may have multiple final markings.
And here you can see an example
where that is the case.
So let's take a look at this Petri net and
look at this behavior.
So given such a Petri net
with multiple final states,
we can convert it to a transition
system with multiple final states.
And then the behavior of this
process that we have modeled
can be enumerated as a set of traces
that move from one of the initial
states to to one of final states and
in this case these are these four traces.
Transition systems may be exponential
in the size of a Petri net.
And you can see that if you model
concurrency, as you can see here,
the corresponding transition system
will have two to the power k,
where k is the number of transitions
states.
We can also look at the situation where
we have multiple tokens in the place, and
in this case we also have many
more states than we have places.
So if you put 1,000 tokens in,
the input place,
we have 1,001 reachable states.
It's also easy to construct petri nets
that are extremely small that have
infinitely many states.
So c is just producing tokens,
and it can produce any number of tokens.
So the size of the petri net
may be much smaller than the size
of your transition system.
So, please take a look at this example.
And again take a moment to construct
the corresponding transition system.
Note that the final marking is
the marking with the token in p6.
Make the transition system and
then look at all the complete traces.
There is no loop in this model so
it has to be finite.
Okay lets take a look at
the resulting transition system and
then at the set of traces so
given this petri net.
We can construct this transition system.
And it may look quite involved, but
if you systematically look at what
are the states that are reachable and
what kind of transitions are enabled in
the state, this is what you will get.
Once you have this transition system,
you can look at all the paths that
go from the initial state
to the final state.
And these give you the complete traces.
And in this example,
there are 16 complete traces.
And it may be a bit difficult
to see on this slide, so
we can zoom in into a particular trace.
In this case the trace (a,b,d,c,e,f).
And we can see this is one of the 16
traces,and indeed it is a path
through our reachability graph going from
the initial state to the final state.
So this concludes the introduction
to the topic of Petri net and
the corresponding properties and
also the relation to transition systems.
This will be very important if we
start talking about process discovery.
Thank you for watching and
hope to see you next time.
[MUSIC]