[MUSIC]
A very warm welcome to this
lecture of the course on
Process Mining: Data Science in Action.
This week will focus on process discovery.
But to do this,
we first need to understand the input and
output of process discovery.
That is why today we start
looking at event logs and models.
In one of the earlier lectures,
we spoke about relating process models to
event logs, and we spoke about play out,
play in, and replay.
Now let me briefly recall the things
that we have discussed before.
First, we have play-out.
From a model we generate behavior, and
if we are doing simulation that is
the typical thing that we are doing.
Also if we build a workflow system
configured on the basis of models, we're
also playing out model generating behavior
based on what we have modeled before.
There are many other management
games model checking, and
all kinds of other things where we take
a model and generate behavior from it.
Then we spoke about play-in.
Play-In is the reverse.
We start from behavior, and
we automatically generate
models based on that.
We also talk about process discovery.
Learning what is really
happening in organizations and
in systems,
based on analyzing the event logs.
Finally we have replay.
We take a model and we take behavior and
this is the most important form
of process mining because we
confront model and reality.
And this is useful for
conformance checking, for
prediction, for bottleneck analysis,
and many other purposes.
This picture again summarizes
the main idea of process mining and
highlights the three main
types of process mining.
Process discovery conforms
to playing in a model.
Conformance checking is a form of
replay aimed at finding deviations.
Then we have enhancement.
It's also a form of replay with
the goal to find bottlenecks and
other types of problems or
ideas for improvement.
So after looking at this
overall model we are going to look at
a problem of getting the right data.
And in one of the earlier lectures I
already explained what an event log is.
But let me briefly state that again.
So we assume that there is an event
log where each event refers to a case,
to an activity, and a point in time.
A timestamp.
An event log can be seen as
a collection of cases which we
sometimes also refer to as traces.
So each case corresponds to
a sequence of events and, as I said,
is often called a trace.
Where may event data come from?
From a variety of sources.
So we can look at the database system.
If we go to a hospital,
we will easily find hundreds of
tables with patient data that
we can use for process mining.
We can also look at simple data
sources like a CSV file or
an Excel spreadsheet that have the
information needed to do process mining.
There may be transaction logs.
We can look at the data in SAP.
We can look at the data
used in middleware systems.
Or we can
use for example, the data which
you can find in Twitter or Facebook.
So event data may come from
many different sources and
these are some examples that
I already showed you earlier.
So we have different columns, every row
corresponds to an event and we always need
to identify what is the case ID, what is
the activity, and what is the timestamp.
So here we see one example
of students taking a course.
Here we see another
example of order handling.
And again we need to identify what is the
case id, what is the activity name, and
what is the timestamp.
And we can find such information in
many places, as I explained before.
For example, in a hospital,
you will easily find hundreds of
tables containing patient data, having
exactly the information that is needed.
But, it is not always as
clear as was the case in
examples that I just explained to you.
For example, we can look at your mailbox.
We can think of every email as an event,
and an email has a sender field,
a receiver field, a to field, a subject,
a timestamp, a body, etcetera.
So think now about the following question,
if an email represents an event, what
would be the role of the different types
of information that you find in an email?
So what is the case ID?
What is the activity?
What is the timestamp?
So take a moment to think about this.
There are several answers possible.
What you see here on this slide is that
I'm showing you a particular mapping where
I consider the subject of an email
message to be the case id.
So we want to group all emails having
a particular subject into a single trace.
We do this based on the subject field.
We use the timestamps to sort
the events within a case.
And in this case we see the sender
field as the activity name.
The other fields, we consider
that to be other data variables.
And we can interpret the sender
field also as the resource.
But there are many other
mappings possible.
For example, we could consider
the sender to be the case and
the subject to be the activity name.
Many mappings are possible and
it depends on the context and the
question, what is the best thing to do.
We can look at another question.
This is related to an example
that I showed to you before.
We again look at student data and
looking at this type of data.
What is the case field?
What is the timestamp field?
What is the activity name field?
Again think a bit about this for a moment.
And if we look at a possible
solution we see this.
So the student id is the case id
the course is the activity name,
and the date of the course is
considered to be the timestamp.
The student id is also the resource.
the other fields correspond to optional
information that we can use in
process mining.
Again, other alternative
mappings are possible.
And it depends on the question
what you need to take.
For example one could also think of
the course as being the case and
the student as being the activity,
and so many mappings are possible.
It is not just basic information,
sometimes we
have event logs that contain
much more extensive information.
In all the examples that we have seen so
far, we just see an event
as an atomic activity.
But in some cases activities take time and
we can see an explicit start and
complete event.
So many event logs have this type
of transactional information.
And if we have this information we can for
example measure
duration of an activity.
Also if we look at the attributes.
So far we considered all
the attributes to be event attributes.
But also at the case level
there may be attributes, and
these are the attributes that don't change
while executing the particular case.
And so these extensions can also
be used for process mining and
structure the input format in a better way.
The XES standard, XES stands for
Extensible Event Stream,
is a standard adopted by the IEEE
task force on process mining.
And it is a format supported by the tools
that you are using in this course.
It, unlike CSV files, it already
interprets all the different columns and
you can load these files into process
mining tools like ProM and Disco.
And there is nothing that
you need to do further.
You can immediately start the analysis.
If you want to know more about
the standard, please visit this URL and
you can find lots of examples.
So, we assume that we
have XES information.
It's really easy to get
because the conversions are often
just of a syntactical nature.
After having the event data,
we want to look at the process models.
Again, just like with event data,
I will give some examples of what kind
of process models we are talking about.
Before we have seen simple process models,
typically focusing on the control flow.
Here you see a Petri net model which
describes the sequence of activities.
What are activity
sequences that are allowed,
not elaborating on all
the other perspectives.
So this is just control flow.
But next to control flow, one can
look at all kinds of other elements.
Like, for example, we can look at
data elements that are driving
particular decisions in the process.
We can look at timing information and
somehow model time in the process
models that we are generating.
We can enrich process models with
resource information, cost, risks,
and all kinds of other perspectives.
We will deal with this in later weeks.
In this week we will
focus on control-flow and
on the discovery of just
control-flow models.
But it's important to know that
process models can also express all of
these other perspectives.
There are many process model notations.
Here you see a long list on this slide.
And some of these notations we
will revisit in later lectures.
What is crucial to see is that
the representation is important for
two different purposes.
The first purpose is that the
representation that you are using while,
for example, doing process discovery,
is driving your search process.
So you need to have
a representation that helps you to
find the model that captures reality well.
This is internal in the process
discovery technique.
At the same time you want to visualize
models in a particular way so you need to
think what kind of process model
notation does the end user want to see?
So.
It's important to realize that
the notation used during discovery may be
different than the notation that you're
using to present the end results.
That's why we revisit and
look at many different process
model notations in this lecture.
For example if you look at disco it
is using so-called fuzzy models and
here you can see an example of that.
All the squares represent activities,
the arcs represent causal penalties.
But unlike petri nets, we do not exactly
specify in the graphical notation
whether something is an and join,
and split, x or split, x or join.
We allow for all kinds of mixtures and
do not explicitly express that.
We don't get an executable model, but
we get a model that is much simpler and
maybe much more intuitive.
I already mentioned several times
in this lecture the tool ProM,
the tools ProM and Disco.
I think now is the right time for
you to install these tools, so
please take a look at the instructions.
We will look at these
tools in much more detail later.
What you have to realize
now is that ProM is a very
extensive tool which allows for
dozens of different model types.
It allows for many different
input formats and it allows for
many different types of process mining.
So it's a tool that is quite complicated
to use but very powerful and very broad.
Disco, on the other hand, is a commercial
tool which is simple, fast, and
easy to use.
But in terms of functionality covers
only smaller parts of this this course.
But advantages by that it is much
easier and much more pleasant to use.
It is mainly using fuzzy models in
the way that I've just described.
So this ends this lecture.
If you would like to read more
about these things, take a look at
the chapters that are highlighted here.
You can read about process models and
you can read about event logs.
Thank you very much for
watching and hope to see you soon.
[MUSIC]