[MUSIC]
Glad to see you again.
Today we will continue with Petri Nets,
a foundation of process modeling notation,
that you need to understand first before
we can look at process mining approaches.
In the last lecture, we took a look at
these two Petri Nets that both
model a safe traffic light.
And they both have the property,
that at any point in time at least
one of the two traffic lights is red.
One is alternating,
the other is non-deterministic.
If we take a look at the non-deterministic
model of these two safe traffic lights,
we can see that initial marking
is a multi-set of tokens.
There is one token in place r1.
One token in place r2,
and one token in place x.
Then we can talk about a set
of reachable markings, and
we will find several reachable markings.
Each represented as has a multi-set.
And so here, on this slide,
there are enumerated and
we can see all the reachable markings.
If we want to know what
are the reachable markings,
we typically construct
a reachability graph, and
a reachability graph can be seen as
a particular type of transition system.
A transition system with
one initial state, and
with an undefined number
of final markings.
So for the traffic lights, this is
the corresponding reachability graph, and
it is showing the five reachable
states that I showed earlier.
So the arrow indicates that the traffic
light starts in the state with
the token in r1, r2, and x.
And from that state,
two transitions are possible.
One is rg1, one is rg2.
And by just simply trying
all possibilities we get
this reachability graph showing
all the reachable markings.
So, let's take a look at another example.
So, here you see a Petri
net with two transitions.
There are two tokens in p1.
There's one token in p3.
And we can look at what
are the reachable markings,
by creating the reachability graph.
This is the reachability graph.
So let's take a look at it.
We start in the initial states,
where there is a token in p3,
and there are two tokens in p1,
indicated by the small 2.
So we are talking about
the multi-set of tokens in places.
In this particular initial marking,
transition t1,
is enabled and transition t2 is enabled.
Assume that we execute transition t1,
then we consume a token from p1,
and produce a token for p2.
So the resulting marking is
the marking with a token in p1,
a token in p2, and a token in p3.
So in the reachability graph,
we add this particular marking.
Then in this marking,
we can again look what are the transitions
that are enabled t1 is still enabled,
because there were two tokens is p1, and
now one remains and t2 is also enabled.
Assume that t1 occurs,
then we end up in this,
in the marking with two tokens in p2,
and one token in p3.
And now there is only one possibility,
namely that t2 fires,
removing the token from p3,
and putting a token in p4.
This is just one of several
possible scenarios when we start in
the initial state.
We could also have executed first t2,
ending up in this marking.
And then we would have to execute t1 once,
and t1 for the second time.
Another scenario would have been that
we would have executed t1 first,
then t2 and then t1.
And then we have explored all
possibilities and we get a reachability
graph that you see here, which is simply
showing all the reachable markings,
and showing the transitions from
one marking to another marking.
And this is also called
a transition system.
Let's take a look at the slightly
more complicated situation,
where t2 is also consuming tokens from p1.
So they are competing for
the tokens in p1.
So construct the reachability graph.
If you construct it, this is what you see.
So initially both t1 and t2 are enabled.
If t2 occurs, then a token is removed
from p3, and a token is removed from p1.
And that results in the state with
the token in p1, and a token in p4.
In that state, the only thing that
can happen is that we execute t1,
and then we end up in the state p2, p4.
But there is another scenario
that we first execute t1.
If we execute t1,
we end up in a state where there is
still a choice between t1 and t2.
And then we have explored
all possibilities.
So this is the reachability graph
of this particular Petri net.
So far, we only looked at Petri nets,
where there is just a single arc between
a place and a transition, but
in a Petri net, if you want,
it can also be multiple arcs.
So in this particular example,
t2 requires two tokens from p1,
t2 if it occurs,
it will produce three tokens for p2.
So t1 has three output
arcs to the same place,
t2 has two input arcs from the same place,
and the meaning is obvious.
It indicates a number of
tokens to be consumed and
the number of tokens to be produced.
So if we construct a reachability graph,
this is what we get.
So again, if we look at initial situation,
both t1 and t2 are enabled.
If we execute t2,
we remove two tokens from p1,
and one token from p3,
and produce one token for
p4, as is indicated in
the reachability graph.
If on the other hand t1 executes,
then we consume a token from p1,
and produce three tokens for p3.
Sorry, for p2.
So in this model,
it is possible that t1 fires once.
Fires again.
And fires for a third time.
Resulting in nine tokens in p2.
So this shows that in a Petri net,
arcs can have multiplicities and
their meaning is obvious.
And we can still construct
the reachability graph.
One of the interesting features
of a reachability graph is
that given a small Petri net
like the one that is shown here,
the corresponding reachability
graph may be infinitely large.
So if you would construct
the reachability graph of this model,
you would end up in a process
that would never terminate.
If you look at the model carefully,
you will see that you can execute t1,
you can execute t2.
And if you execute t2,
you also put a token in p3.
And again, you can execute t1,
t2, t1, t2.
And you can repeat this as
many times as you want.
And in every round,
there will be a token in p3.
And this will continue
until you execute t3.
And in each round that you execute t1 and
t2, you will put
an additional token in p3.
So the number of reachable
markings is infinite.
So this gave you some idea that given
a Petri net generate behavior, and
that behavior can be expressed in
terms of a reachability graph,
which is actually a transition system.
Now let us take a look at a slightly
more involved Petri net, and
then you can see that
modeling is very challenging.
And that is why you need to make
exercises to really understand
the process of modeling a process,
because this is far from trivial.
Let us take a look at an example and
I should warn you,
this is not a trivial exercise.
You will need quite some time
to model this from scratch.
If you are not used to
the Petri net notation or
you are not experienced in
process modeling in general.
So suppose that we have one train.
And that we would like to model a circular
railway system, with four stations.
We also have passengers and
they may hop on or
hop off at the various stations,
but they can only hop on or
hop off, if the train is standing
still in one of the four stations.
The train has a capacity of 50 persons.
So if the train is full,
no passengers can hop on.
And, of course, no passengers can
hop off if the train is empty.
So I would like to ask you to model
the above process in terms of a Petri net.
And after you have answered that question,
please tell me what a number
of reachable states is.
And again, this will take some time for
you to model.
I hope you've tried to make this model.
Let's now take a look at the solution and
let me start by giving a couple of hints.
So, how to describe
the state of the train?
The state of the train is
determined by the location, and
by the number of passengers it holds.
How to model that?
What are possible actions?
A train can move and
people can hop on and hop off.
And you also need to think
when they are possible.
If you model this small process in terms
of a Petri net, it looks like this.
And this solution may
look a bit intimidating,
if you're not used to things like this.
But let me try to explain it step by step.
So let's first take a look,
at the state of the train.
And now I mean by the state of the train,
the location where it is.
It is in one of the four stations, or it
is moving from one station to another one.
So you get to circular Petri net
with one token representing the train and
indicating where it is.
So I think everybody can understand
this model in isolation.
We didn't model any of the passengers,
so let's try to model the passengers.
So that is indicated by this small model.
So what this model is indicating
is that there are tokens
that either represent
a free slot in the train,
a free position or that represent
a passenger being on that train.
So there are 50 tokens distributed
over two places.
Now all the 50 tokens, are in the place
indicating that there
is still three places.
But these tokens can also be in
the other place indicating that
there are passengers on this train.
The transitions model hopping on and
hopping off, at the different stations.
So I hope that everybody
can understand this model.
And now we can merge these two simpler
models, into this overall model.
So I've merged the two models
that I've showed to you before.
And it is important that you
take a look at the green arcs,
that actually represent two arcs.
One arc for consumption,
and one arc for production.
And together, they provide
a solution of the overall exercise.
It is now enforced that
passengers can only hop on and
hop off, in stations when the train
is standing still, and they
cannot do this when the train is moving
from one station to another station.
Another part of the question was,
how many reachable states there are?
In total there are 51 times 8.
So we can look at the location
of the train, and
we can look at the number of passengers.
And there are 51 possible states when
we look at the number of passengers.
We count from 0 to 50.
So there are 408 reachable markings.
And this example illustrates that
very quickly you cannot model
things anymore in terms of reachability
graph, a computer can compute
the reachability graphs in a matter of
milliseconds for such a small example.
But when you try to draw it,
it's already very large.
And this shows the power of higher
level models like Petri net.
So let's go back to the,
to the process mining challenge, and
look at Petri nets in the context
of play-in, play-out and replay.
So this is the classical use of models,
Play-Out and we see nothing surprising.
Now you have a background in Petri nets,
and
you can easily see that this is
a possible trace of this model.
But now you need to think in of it
in terms of, creating an event log.
By playing out the model,
we can create an event log.
So, that's play-out.
Play-In, we get a bunch of traces, and
we automatically would
like to construct a model.
Later, we will see for example,
the alpha algorithm,
which will produce exactly this model
given this set of example traces.
Then we have Replay.
It looks very much the same
as what I showed you before.
So, we are now replaying a trace that
we saw in a reality on top of a model.
Now we illustrate it in
terms of a Petri net.
So we did not find any deviations.
We can look at another example,
where we execute a trace a, e, d.
And again,
we find no surprises whatsoever.
So again, we see no deviations.
But the replay becomes very interesting,
if reality deviates from the model.
So now we look at the trace a, c, d.
And it does not fit into this model.
And we can very easily see that using
the firing rule of Petri nets and
just by playing the token game,
we can see that there is a problem.
So we, we did a, we executed transition c.
Now in the trace, it is indicated
that in reality d happened,
whereas in the model this is not possible,
because place p3 is empty.
So we can mark that we
have a problem here.
We are missing a token.
We can simply add it, and
execute the code to the final state.
And what we seen then is that there
is a token remaining in place p1.
So we can see two problems.
We missed a token and in the end,
the token is remaining.
Indicating that b should
have been executed.
So we can use, replay on top of
a Petri net to detect problems.
We are still talking very
much about process models, so
please take a look at chapter two
to see more of the details of
the things that I've
discussed in this lecture.
Thank you very much for watching,
and hope to see you soon.
[MUSIC]