[MUSIC]
In the last lecture we learned
that it may be very challenging to
extract event logs from
today's data sources.
This lecture presents 12 guidelines
to improve the logging of events.
So today, just like the last lecture,
we focus again on the input
side of process mining.
But now we do not identify
the problems that we may encounter.
But we provide guidelines to
get a better kind of logging.
We have seen that there may be
many data quality problems and
these are caused by an incorrect
recording of events.
The data is missing,
it may be at a wrong level of detail, or
it may be simply incorrect.
So the guidelines of logging
focus on these issues.
To explain the guidelines,
we are using the following terms.
So events are things that happen and
they are described by references and
attributes.
So an event reference
points to some object.
A person, a case, a ticket, a room.
It is referring to an entity
that exists in the real world.
An attribute is a name value pair.
So for example, an activity has a name.
An event may refer to
the age of a patient or
an attribute may refer to
a particular point in time.
So these are the terms that we
use to explain the 12 guidelines.
So lets start.
So the first guideline for
logging looks at
the semantics of events and
the reference and
attribute names, they should have
the same meaning for all people involved.
It cannot be that a particular
attribute means something different for
different stakeholders involved in the
recording and analysis of the event data.
The second guideline refers to that
there should be a structured and
managed collection of reference and
attribute names.
It cannot be the case that somebody that
is programming an information system
in an ad hoc manner inserts
statements in the code.
To start recording things without
really having a discussion and
an explicit decision before.
So any new event,
any new reference or attribute name
should only be added if there is
consensus about that it is relevant.
And that it has a particular meaning.
The third guideline refers to the fact
that references should be stable.
They should not be context dependent.
It cannot be the case that if we
change the language setting of
a machine that things will change.
Or that over time things change.
So a stability of
references is important.
Attribute names should also
be as precise as possible.
As an example that we have used before
when we were talking about data
quality problems is that the many event
logs we do not know the exact timestamp.
We only know the date.
If we have that and we have the difficulty
of ordering events that take place on
the same date because we do not
know their order in a reliable way.
So if data is imprecise,
in some cases it's unavoidable,
it should be indicated explicitly.
A related guideline is guideline five,
that refers to uncertainty.
If events, reference, or
attributes are uncertain to some degree,
it should be stated explicitly.
So if we are not sure about the time.
If you are not sure about which
resource executed something and
we make an educated guess.
It should be indicated so
in the event log.
So that we can use this
information during analysis.
The sixth guideline refers to the fact
that events data should be ordered,
and there are two ways of doing that.
There can be timestamps and
these timestamps are used for ordering.
Or the order is stored explicitly
in terms of a list of,
or if it's a partial order
in terms of a graph.
If we, for example, have timestamps
that just refer to the day,
then we may have difficulties
reconstructing the order.
But there are dedicated analysis
techniques to still try to
capture the order,
even though we have such problems.
Guideline seven refers to
transactional information.
If possible, we should not just
record the completion of an activity,
we should try to get the start and
the completion.
If things are aborted, suspended, or
resumed, all this transaction information,
if we can record it we should,
because it will help us, for
example, to compute what
the duration of the activity is, but
also what the utilization is
of a particular resource.
The eighth guideline refers to
the fact that guarding
the quality of event data
is a continuous process there should
be regular checks of the logging.
Should not be done just at
the beginning but while the process and
the system is evolving.
We should repeatedly check whether
the logging is up to date.
The ninth guideline
refers to comparability.
The logging itself should
not change over time and
should not depend
on the particular context.
For example, suppose that in
a process at some point in time we
stop recording a particular activity.
We may make the conclusion that,
that activity was first executed and
later in time, it is no longer executed.
But at conclusion would be wrong because
it's just a change in recording.
The same as if you would for
example, you would like to compare
the performance of two departments
if one department is logging in
a different way than the other department.
You would conclude that there are certain
differences that do not really exist.
So comparability is key.
When we were discussing process mining in
the context of data warehouses and OLAP
we made the point that we should
avoid aggregating event data which is
often done in these types of systems.
Aggregation should
be done during analysis and
not before because it cannot be undone.
So
event data should be as raw as possible.
Guideline 11.
We should not remove
events that have happened.
For example,
if we would analyze student data and
we would remove all the students that
dropped out of a particular program,
we will get very misleading
analysis results.
For example if you would
look at concerts,
we should not delete a concert
if the concert is cancelled.
We should not delete an employee if
the employee is fired because we
are removing information and
that is endangering provenance.
The last guideline is about privacy.
And here there is a very delicate balance
between on the one hand ensuring privacy.
And on the other hand still being
able to do meaningful analysis.
So often there is no
interest whatsoever to
record that cases refer
to a particular person.
However, we would like to correlate events
that are referring to the same person.
So hashing is a way to make
data anonymous while still
being able to make conclusions and
relating different events.
If we make information too abstract we
may remove these correlations and it will
be difficult to do any type of analysis.
So these were the 12 guidelines for
logging and they show you that
the points that you should look at
when you are designing a system.
What are the things
that you should record?
And this is very important for
further analysis.
Because garbage in, garbage out.
If we start by recording
events in the wrong way, or
in an inconsistent way,
it will be very difficult to get
meaningful analysis results from that.
To read more about the guidelines for
logging,
you can take a look at the article
shown here at the bottom of the slide.
Thank you for watching this lecture.
See you next time.
[MUSIC]