[MUSIC]
Welcome to this lecture of the course on
Process Mining: Data Science in Action.
Today we will provide an overview of
available process mining software.
We will also relate process
mining tools like ProM and
Disco, to other data sign tools.
Data scientists need to have data,
tools, and preferably also questions.
In the previous lectures
we focused very much on
the event data needed
to do process mining.
Today we will focus on the tools.
And of course, we have been playing with
tools like ProM and Disco, so we already
have a good understanding of process
mining functionality by tools like these.
However, today we would like
to expand this spectrum and
also look at other tools.
Here in this diagram you see Disco and
ProM.
So both Disco and
ProM are process mining specific tools.
They have been developed for
the purpose of doing process mining.
Disco is simple, easy to use,
very fast, very convenient.
ProM is more powerful,
provides much more types of analysis, but
it also, much more difficult to use.
Both are not part of any bigger suite,
like a complete BPM tool or
something like that.
Next to process mining software you have
the classic called data mining software.
Like RapidMiner, R and Knime.
These do not provide process
mining capabilities.
There are also other
commercial tools other than
Disco like Perceptive Process Mining and
Celonis Discovery.
And that is an interesting
combination of RapidMiner and
ProM, which is called RapidProM.
We'll look at these systems
later in a bit more detail.
So this is the spectrum of
tools that one can use.
If one would like to select
a process mining tool
then the refined reference
model can help you.
The first question you
should ask yourself.
Which of the ten process mining
activities are important for
me, and which are supported.
So is discovery supported?
Is conformance checking supported?
And for example, do we need to be able
to predict the remaining flow time?
Another question is, what
are the perspectives that are supported?
Are resources supported?
Is the data perspective supported?
How are things related to time?
Another question is,
what modeling notations are supported?
Petri nets, BPMN, or what other
notations that you find relevant?
And last but
not least, what are the import and export
formats that are supported for event logs,
models, alignments and
all kinds of other artifacts?
So, this is a checklist when you want
to select a process mining tool.
For example, if you look at ProM, and
look at the the red area here.
It aims to support the entire
process mining spectrum.
It supports many different types of
notations ranging from Petri nets and
BPMN, to more exotic formats like
the declarative language Declare.
ProM also supports
conformance checking and
operational support,
unlike many of the commercial tools.
There are a hundreds of
plug-ins available, but
many of them are experimental and
not always user friendly.
On the other end of the spectrum,
one can find tools like Disco.
The tool that you've also
been using in this course.
Here the focus is not on the entire
spectrum, but on discovery and
performance analysis including animation.
Disco provides very powerful
filtering capabilities and
you can use these to do
comparative process mining.
You can also do very basic forms
of conformance checking by
checking whether a certain
behavioral pattern appears or not.
It uses a variant of fuzzy models.
So it doesn't have
an executable model underneath it.
And it does not support things
like conformance checking and
operational support.
But it is very easy to use, and
it has an excellent performance.
Much faster than many of
the mature data mining tools.
So, these are two ends of the spectrum.
There are several other commercial tools.
Here you can see some of them.
In my teaching in Eindhoven,
I'm using, for
example, also Perceptive Process Mining,
and Celonis Discovery.
But there are many other tools available.
If one looks at these commercial tools,
they are similar to
Disco in terms of scope.
Often they are not as user friendly,
and often also a bit slower, but
in terms of scope they
are very comparable.
They focus on control flow and
performance analysis.
There is no support for conformance
checking, operational support and
many more of the sophisticated
features that you can find in ProM.
Let's take a look at three
concrete examples of
tools other than this current ProM.
Let's first take a look at RapidProM.
So this is a combination of ProM and
RapidMiner.
And so ProM is in a way embedded in
RapidMiner, and one gets a graphical
environment where one has dozens of
process mining related building blocks.
And one can build an analysis flow.
If you would like to learn more about
this, you can visit the URL on this slide.
It's also available through
the RapidMiner marketplace.
So what can you do in RapidProM?
You can build your own
process mining workflow, and
then execute it on any data set.
So we can take as an example
this very simple process mining workflow.
And let's take a look
at the building blocks.
First we need to create the ProM context.
In other words, we need to start up ProM.
And relate all the other building
blocks to this instance of ProM.
If we want to copy something we need
to use this building block for that.
But it's just a technicality.
The real work starts with this building
block, where we read the event log.
The output of this building block is
an event log in the RapidProM environment.
And then this event log can
be taken by a building block
that represents the alpha algorithm.
So it takes an event lock,
and produces a Petri net.
Subsequently, we have a building block for
doing conformance checking
based on alignments.
So now we can
run this workflow on any event log.
And here you see example
output in RapidProM.
That's why here you see the discovered
process model by the alpha algorithm.
And here you can see
the conformance check done by
the conformance checking building block,
based on alignment.
This is an example of another
process mining workflow.
What are the building blocks?
We first load an event log.
We then in parallel create a dotted chart.
We create a Petri net
using the inductive miner.
And we create a social network based
on the handover of work approach.
And if we run this workflow
on a particular event log,
we get results like a dotted chart,
a Petri net model, and a social network.
And if we would like to apply this
workflow to another event log
it is very simple.
So.
Using RapidProM, we can repeat process
mining analysis very quickly.
This is very useful for
scientific experiments where one would
like to play with the parameter.
But also if one would like to
reuse prepackaged analysis.
It can also be used to combine process
mining with other forms of data mining.
It can also be combined with text mining,
by combining building blocks of
ProM with the building blocks
that are already on rapidminer.
So that was one example.
Another example of another tool
is Celonis Discovery a commercial
process mining tool.
It is web-based.
It supports process discovery, but
unfortunately it doesn't
support concurrency.
So, the models that are discovered are,
in essence, transition systems.
It can show frequencies,
how frequently a case is flowing from
one activity to another activity.
It can show time information,
so where are the bottlenecks?
All the things that we have
also seen in Disco before.
It also supports animation.
You can animate a log on top
of a discovered model, and
it supports seamless abstraction.
And so there is again
the slider like functionality.
Here we see all the details
of a particular event log and
by moving the slider we can make
the process model more simple,
until we get something that
is easy to understand.
There are also all kinds of
performance-related dashboards.
So in scope, it is very similar to the
things which we have seen in this Disco.
Another example of a commercial process
mining tool is Perceptive Process Mining.
It can be used in conjunction with
the BPM product of perceptive.
So models that have been discovered can be
automatically uploaded in the business
process management system of perceptive.
It is also web-based.
It supports process discovery.
And it supports two types of discovery.
One type is fast, but
cannot discover concurrency.
So again,
the output is a transition system.
There is also a more sophisticated mining
algorithm, based on the genetic process
mining techniques discussed earlier,
that is able to discover concurrency.
Again, we can filter the event log and
the model in various ways, for
example based on frequency.
We can replay the event log.
And a nice feature in the perceptive
software is that you can color the tokens
based on attributes of
the corresponding event or case.
So here tokens are colored
based on their flowtime.
So you can see whether certain very slow
cases take a particular
path through the model.
You can also change the perspective and
look at resources.
So here you see the social network of
the three most frequent resources.
And you can see how tokens are flowing
from one resource to the other resource.
Now tokens are colored based on
the activity being executed.
And, again, there are all kinds
of performance related charts and
you can find these in any
of the commercial tools.
So after showing some commercial
process mining products,
it's interesting to
broaden the scope a bit.
For example, we can look at BPM systems.
What can be expected is that
in the future, more and
more BPM systems will
support process mining.
At this point in time,
very few BPM systems actually support
things like process discovery and
conformance checking.
One can also look at existing
data mining techniques.
And software, and
machine learning software.
They are very related but at the same
time, if you look at existing software,
they typically do not support
any form of process mining.
We can also look at predictive analytics,
but
you can see that the software there
is often not process oriented at all.
A question could be how about BI tools?
So what is BI?
What is Business Intelligence?
A possible definition given
by somebody from Forester is,
BI is a set of methodologies,
processes, architectures and
technologies that transform raw data
into meaningful and useful information.
Used to enable more effective,
strategic, tactical and
operational insights and decision making.
So this is a mouthful and
if you read it, I think everybody will
agree that process mining is part of it.
However, if you look at the existing BI
products that one can find on the market.
None of these products is actually
supporting process mining.
so, process mining is still functionality
that needs to be added to these tools.
What do these tools offer?
They offer typical functionality like ETL,
extract, transform and load functionality,
querying, reporting, interactive
dashboards like the one that you see here
and generating alerts if thing starts
to occur differently than planned.
So, such functionality is typically not
process oriented, and despite the name,
the type of analysis is typically quite
simplistic, more spreadsheet-like.
So, in conclusion, there are several
process mining tools available,
but it is still
a relatively young discipline.
So, we expect that in the future
many more process mining tools
will become available, and that they
will become standard, embedded, in BI,
BPM, and data mining suites.
One should avoid a trap,
based on definitions that process
mining is a part of data mining.
By definition it is true.
But data mining software typically does
not provide things like process discovery,
conformance checking, and
the forms of operational support
that we have been looking at.
The same holds for BI.
So one you avoid this trap and use
the checklist that I've explained earlier.
If you would like to read more
on tools please take a look at
chapter 10 of the process mining book.
Thank you for watching this lecture,
see you next time.
[MUSIC]