[MUSIC]
Welcome to this lecture of the course on
Process Mining: Data Science in Action.
This is the first lecture of the sixth and
last week.
Today we will learn about
operational support techniques.
For example, we'll show that we are able
to predict the remaining flow time of
a case.
The other lectures in this week will
focus more on the practical aspects of
process mining.
In the first week of this
course we talked about
the four generic data science questions.
And today we are going to revisit them.
The first generic data science
question is what happened?
Through process discovery and
many of the other techniques that we
looked at we can clearly
answer such a question.
We are analyzing the past and can show
what are the things that happened?
What are the order in which
people have executed activities?
Where were the bottlenecks and
things like that?
The second generic data science
question is why did it happen?
And if we are analyzing bottlenecks,
this is exactly the type of question
that we are trying to answer.
So true decision mining and all the mining
techniques focused more on performance,
we often try to understand what
the reason is why things have happened.
The first two questions are very
much focused on the past.
Understanding the past and
learning things for the future.
Operational support, however,
is focusing on questions three and
four of the generic
data science questions.
So the question,
what will happen is about prediction.
Can we predict what is going
to happen in the future?
For example, for a running case, when
do we think the case will be finished?
Or, will the case be rejected?
This is the type of question
that we will look at in
the context of operational support.
If we can make predictions we can
also answer the fourth question.
And that is what is
the best that can happen?
Based on experiences from
the past we can recommend certain
actions to be taken to optimize
a process in terms of cost,
time, risks, compliance,
and other types of things.
So, the last two data science
questions are the questions that we
focus on today in the context
of operational support.
Operational support starts
from pre mortem data,
data about cases that are still running.
So what are, then,
the three process mining activities
that we execute in this context?
The first one is detect.
Detection is about finding out
that something is happening at
this point in time.
So for example, a case is deviating.
A deadline has just expired.
And we don't want to do this afterwards.
We want to do it at
the moment that it happens.
Then we have prediction.
When will a case finish?
Will the case be rejected?
Will a case deviate?
We would like to predict
these types of things.
And last but not least, we would like
to recommend what a suitable next
activity is, or what a best resource is
that can execute a particular activity.
So these are the questions
that we will look at.
Now let's look at these three process
mining activities in a bit more detail.
So assume the scenario where
we are executing a case and
we have already executed activities a and
b and
we are now in a state where we do not
know what will happen in the future.
Many things can happen.
So, at this point in time what
does operational support mean?
If we talk about detection, we may, for
example, generate an alert,
because b just happened and
it was not supposed to happen according
to some normative process model.
That's an example of an alert.
Another alert could be that something is
executed, and it should be executed, but
it was executed too late.
So, things like too late, but
also things like done by the wrong
resource are the types of
things that we would like to detect and
generate alerts while the case is running.
Then we have prediction.
Suppose that a and
b have happened, and we would like to
predict when the process will be finished.
We can learn from experiences in
the past and give a good estimate for
the remaining processing time of a case.
But we may also want to predict
the outcome of a process.
If we can do predictions, we can
automatically also do recommendations.
Based on past experiences, we may for
example recommend executing
activity c at this point in time.
Or we may recommend that an activity
is done by
a particular resource.
That has shown to be able to
execute that activity well.
So these are the types of activities
that we will focus on today.
So we will use a running example that
we have seen several times before.
So here you can see
a fragment of the event log,
you can see the corresponding
process model.
We leave out all the other attributes.
We just focus on activities and time.
But it's important to realize that
operational support also relates to all of
the other perspectives that we have been
discussing in the last couple of lectures.
If we have such a process model
we can automatically convert it
to a transition system
as we have seen before.
What you should note is that for
every activity we have a start
event and a complete event.
So we also identify the states
of an activity running.
And if you look at the states of
the transition system, you can see that,
that is indeed the case.
So we will use this example, but
first let's show an overview
of how detection works.
So there is a person working on the case
at the particular point in time.
At the same time,
before a normative model has been made.
Then the information system and
the operational support
system are interacting.
The moment a person is executing
work a partial trace is sent to
the operational support system.
And if this trace deviates from the
normative model a violation is detected.
And the user or the manager is informed
that such a detection,
that such a deviation has taken place.
So violations can be detected, and
this can be the wrong activity,
an activity executed too late,
and things like this.
So let's take a look at an example.
So here we have a process model.
Suppose that we have already
started working on a.
A was completed at time 19.
Then at time 25 we started b.
At time 27 we started d.
At this point in time there is no
reason to generate any type of alert,
because this is perfectly
conforming to the process model.
Now suppose that at time 28,
somebody starts working on
activity e, but b and
d have not yet completed.
So at that point in time,
when somebody starts working on e,
we would like to generate an alert and
detect the violation with respect
to the normative process model.
So this is what detection is all about.
The second type of operational
support is prediction.
Again people are working on cases,
they are interacting with
an information system.
And it may be that at some point in
time they would like to know what is
the remaining processing time,
or what is a likely outcome for
this particular process instance.
Then a predictive model can be used.
Such a predictive model is learned
over historic information.
So learned over an event log
as is shown on this slide.
This is input for
the operational support system that
combines the partial trace together
with the predictive model and
makes a prediction about what is
going to happen in the future.
And this prediction is passed
on to the user who will
know what estimated completion
time of a case will be.
So let's take a look at some
examples of predictions.
So the example that we just saw
is about the remaining flow time.
But we can predict many other things.
Will we be able to meet a deadline or not?
We can attach a probability to it.
We can look at will
a particular person or
a particular group of persons
work on a particular case.
Will it be routed to
a particular department?
We can attach a probability to that.
We can look at whether a certain
activity is likely to be executed or
not in the future.
We can look at costs, and we can also
look at the outcome of the process.
Is this a case that is likely
to be rejected or not?
These can all be, these predictions can
all be made by combining a predictive
model and a partial trace.
So let us take a look at an annotated
transition system where we
take the original transition system and
annotate it with time information.
So here you see the execution of
two traces, and for every case and
for every state that the case visits, we
record the time that the state is entered.
The elapsed time until
the moment that the state is entered,
the remaining time and the sojourn time.
So how much time is spent
in that particular state.
So here you can see the annotated
transition system in more detail.
So we have two cases and if we focus
on the first case, the one in blue,
then we can see that at time 12 it entered
the state where activity a started to run.
The elapsed time at that point in time
was 0, and the remaining time was 42.
And the sojourn time
in this state is 7.
We can look at this particular event.
A was completed at time 19.
The elapsed time in the state that
we are looking at now is 7.
And so 7 time units have passed
since the beginning of the case,
the remaining time is 35 and
the sojourn time is 6.
We can look at the end
of this particular case.
At time 54 it enters the last state, then
the elapsed time has been 42 time units.
The remaining time is of course 0.
So this is the way that we can annotate
transition system using the replay
techniques that we have seen before.
We can do this for many cases and
then collect the results per state.
So every state in the transition
system has a bunch of elapsed times,
remaining times, and sojourn times.
And we can compute the average,
the variance, and
all kinds of other properties
over these states.
Now, suppose that we
are executing a case and
that case is in the state where
there is a token in p3 and p4.
Then based on historic information we can,
for
example, predict that the average
remaining time is 42 time units.
So this is the way that
we can make predictions,
based on things that we have
learned over past executions.
What is very important is
to understand that for
predictions, we should not
just focus on the case itself.
In the previous example,
we just looked at the case in isolation.
But you have to realize that
in real life processes,
it is very important to use context
when you are predicting things.
If you are standing in a long
queue of people then you
cannot ignore all the other
cases that are around you.
Your waiting time will depend on
how many other cases there are.
There's a very simple example
showing that you need to
incorporate context information, and
this is a topic that we have discussed
in one of the earlier lectures.
The last type of operational
support is recommending.
And what kind of things
would we like to recommend?
We would like to recommend what
is the best next activity,
what is a suitable resource,
things like this.
So how does this work?
Again, there is a user interacting with an
information system, and on the other side
we have a model that we have
learned over event logs.
So we have a recommendation model,
it's similar to a predictive model,
that is used by the operational support
system to recommend the best action
that can be taken by comparing a partial
trace to the recommendation model.
And then, for example,
it can say it is best that
you now execute this activity and
it should be done by this person.
A recommendation is always given
with respect to a specific goal.
So, we may want to minimize costs.
We may want to minimize
the remaining flow time.
We may want to maximize the service level,
and so
the fraction of cases handled
within a particular time.
We may want to maximize a certain outcome
of the process or minimize resource usage.
So, predictive model should look at
history, having a particular goal in mind.
What is interesting to see
is that the moment you have
a predictive model you can
automatically turn that
predictive model in a model that
you can use to recommend things.
This is illustrated on this slide.
So if we are in a particular state we
can make a prediction about the future.
In this state,
based on the process model we know what
the actions are that may take
place in this particular state.
What we can then do is that we can
just add them to the event log and
then make a prediction.
We do not really execute these activities,
but we add them to event log,
then make a prediction, in the way
that we did before, and we do that for
all possible actions, and then we
compare the different possible futures.
And then, based on this information,
we can recommend one or
multiple actions to take place.
So if we are able to predict,
we are also able to recommend.
And this a very powerful
feature we can exploit.
So in this lecture we looked
at operational support.
It's the transition from offline process
mining to online process mining.
And this way we enable predictive
analytics for processes.
If you would like to read more
about operational support,
chapter nine is focusing on this topic.
Thank you for watching this lecture.
See you next time.
[MUSIC]