[MUSIC]
Welcome to this lecture.
Today we will focus on the input
side of process mining.
How to get and preprocess the event data.
How to flatten this
information into an event log.
What are possible data quality problems?
These are the questions that
we would like to answer today.
So, we will focus on the input side
of process mining, the event data.
In earlier lectures we
gave some examples of
sources of information that can
be used to extract event logs.
We can look at an ERP system like SAP.
Which has many tables
filled with information.
We can look at middlewear for
example from IBM WebSphere.
We can also look at simple sources
of information like a CSV file.
We can look at social media and the data
that is provided by these open APIs.
We can look at the transaction
log of a financial system.
So there are all these
sources of information.
And when we were talking
about the internet of events,
we saw that in the future, there will be
many more ways to generate events.
For example, through the internet
of things where all kinds of
devices will emit events.
So there are all these
sources of information.
And the question is, how to convert them
into event logs that can be used for
process mining?
If you would like to do process mining,
we need to have an event log.
And this is the conceptual model
that describes the input needed.
We have seen this model before.
So it is describing that
a process consists of cases,
each case consists of events,
events may have attributes.
There are special attributes
like a time stamp and
a resource,
also cases may have attributes.
And because there can be start and
complete events, suspend and
resume, we may also want to identify
so-called activity instances.
And so, groups of events corresponding
to the execution of a single activity.
So this is the type of data that we need,
and how to convert the data from
the sources that were mentioned on
the previous slide to this type of data.
Well, many people think that
this is difficult because you
need to do a syntactical conversion.
Translate for example one XML
format into another XML format.
But this is not the challenge.
The challenge is to locate
the relevant data, to identify what
the process instances are that you would
like to analyze, to scope the problem.
Also to get authorization to
use particular types of data.
So it's not in the syntactical conversion,
the problem is at a different level.
For example, if people ask,
can you mine SAP?
Of course you can mine an SAP system.
It contains lots of
event-related information.
However if you look at SAP, a typical
installation has thousands of tables.
So you need to know
where you are starting.
What is the process that
you would like to analyze?
So it's about identifying the data,
locating it, and extracting it.
If you look at a hospital,
you can easily find 1,000 tables
with patient-related information.
This is again an example, but it is not a
question, can you apply process mining in
a hospital, but know, what is the process
that you would like to analyze and
how can you get the corresponding data?
So you need to understand
the underlying data model and scope and
select event data.
That is the key thing
that needs to be done.
And there are many challenges.
One of the most difficult challenges
is that process models are flat,
and what I mean by that I
will explain in a minute.
But the basic idea is that you have this
data scattered over multiple tables.
And if you would like to do process
mining, you need to flatten that
data in such a way that you can
extract a process model from it, or
check conformance, or analyze bottlenecks.
Then if you take a look
at a process model.
It is about handling instances.
So, events refer to cases.
Here we see an event log that we
have seen several times before.
Every event refers to a case, and
has an activity name associated to it.
Why is this?
We need to have such information
because if we look at process models,
in notations like BPMN, but
also if we look at Petri nets,
UML diagrams, all kinds of other
notations, you will see that
process models model the life cycle
of a process instance in isolation.
So here you see the handling
of a request for compensation.
So every activity is about such a case.
There are few other notations,
like proclets and artifact-centric models,
that describe multiple
instances at the same time.
But typically mainstream notations like
the ones that we see in this course,
like BPMN, what you see in this diagram.
They describe the life cycle
of an instance in isolation.
So we need to flatten the event data and
decide, for events, what is
the corresponding process instance?
This may sound trivial, but it's actually
quite challenging in many real life cases.
To illustrate this, let's take a look
at a database for booking tickets.
Here we see different entities like
a ticket and a booking and
a concert, and a payment and a customer.
And all of these different entities have
events, or actions associated to it.
And we assume that every change
to this database we can monitor.
For example using redo logs.
If we can see changes to
these objects then the question is
how do we now turn this type of
information, into an event log?
And then the foundational question is,
what is the process instance?
What is the case?
So here you can see in a bit more
detail what a data model is all about.
So we have the notion of a ticket.
We have the notion of a concert.
We have a notion of a
seat in a particular hall.
And if we move down the diagram,
we can see that we can have bookings,
bookings have associated payments and
they refer to a particular customer.
So this is the type of
data that we start with.
And then we need to convert such
information into an event log.
So the first decision that we need to
make is what is the process instance?
And we see eight different
entities here and
the question is,
which entity is the process?
What is the process model about?
Is it about the ticket?
Is it about booking?
Is it about a band?
Is it about the concert or
the concert hall?
Is it about the payment?
What is the process model about?
Suppose that we say, okay.
We want to have a process model that
describes the life cycle of a ticket.
Then we need to think,
what are the corresponding activities?
And then we can see that
multiple process instances,
multiple tickets,
may share the same booking or
payment event, because in one booking,
we can order multiple tickets.
So, many different process instances
refer to the same booking.
We could also have taken as a perspective
that the process model should be
about the booking.
We want to model the life
cycle of a booking, and
again we have the question,
what are activities?
We can see that it is not as clear-cut
as one may afford from the beginning
because the same booking instance
may have multiple tickets or
payment-related events.
So one booking may refer
to ten tickets and
there may have been two
payments to pay for it.
Also, if we look at an event like
the cancellation of a concert,
then that is impacting all the tickets and
all the bookings related
to that particular concert.
So there is not a simple one
to one correspondence
between things, and
you need to pre-process the data to get
the event log that you would like to have.
The situation that I'm
describing here is not unique.
You can find it in any
real life situation.
Suppose that you are ordering
books from Amazon.
And suppose that on one
day you order two books.
The next day, you order, again, two books.
So we have two orders and,
in total we have four orderlines.
Two books that we ordered
on the first day,
and the two books that we ordered
on the second day.
Then there may be a delivery.
And suppose that one book of
the first order is in stock, and
the other book is not in stock.
On the order that we placed in the second
day, the first book is in stock but
the second book is not.
Then there may be a delivery that is
referring to one book of the first order.
And another book of the second order.
So there is a many to many relationship
between orders and deliveries.
And things are partially overlapping.
So if you would like to create
a process model from such event
related data, then you carefully have
to think, what is the process instance?
Is it the order?
Is it the orderline?
Or is it the delivery?
And this is a challenging task.
But it's not the only
challenge that we have.
Next to selection and mapping problems,
there may be many data quality issues.
So what kind of problems can there be?
If we look at event data,
there may be missing data.
Things are not recorded.
And one can think of things as things like
cases, events, attributes of an event.
The data may be incorrect.
For example we see an event, and
with the event it is recorded that it
was executed by
a particular resource but
it may have been that it was actually
executed by another resource.
So this is incorrect data.
Data may also be imprecise.
It's not at a desired level of detail.
Another problem is that there may
be lots of irrelevant data, making it
very difficult to see the relevant
things that you would like to analyze.
You need to spend lots of time on
cleaning the data to get to the data that
really matters.
So this matrix is identifying some of
the typical problems that we
encounter if we look at event logs.
Data quality problems related
to the input of process mining.
On the one dimension, we can see missing
data, incorrect data, imprecise data, and
irrelevant data, as just explained.
In the other dimension we see
the typical elements of a log.
So we have cases.
We have events.
We have the different types of attributes.
We have, for example,
time stamps, resources.
And if you look at the combination
of these two dimensions,
we can kind of characterize different
data quality-related problems.
As an example,
let's focus on the the timestamp column.
So, if we look at missing data
in combination with timestamps,
then this refers to timestamps
of events are missing.
Clearly this is a problem.
Timestamps can also be incorrect.
So the time that something was
recorded is different from
the time at which it actually happened.
For example,
in a hospital, a nurse is entering
information in an information system
at a different time from the time at which
the activity was actually performed.
Data may also be imprecise.
Again if we look at the hospital,
there may be events, for
example, in a lab that are recorded
with millisecond precision.
There may be other events where we
just know on which day it happened and
not the particular time at that day.
So this is a very difficult problem for,
for
process mining, because we,
we'd like to order the different events.
We can also look at the resource column.
Missing data means that we do not know
which resource executed the activity.
Incorrect data means that, for
example, it is recorded that one nurse
executed the particular activity, but
it was actually done by a different nurse.
Or the granularity of logging is not
suitable for the questions that we have.
Or for example we do not see which nurse,
we just see at which department in
the hospital something was executed.
So this illustrates the typical
data quality problems that
one may encounter in
a practical situation.
So in this lecture,
we focused on challenges related
to the input of process mining.
The first challenge is to find and select
the data, there may be thousands of tables
so you need to
understand the underlying data model in
order to identify what the data
is that you actually need.
The second problem is that you need to
flatten event data each time you want to
generate a particular process model.
So you need to choose a particular view,
and given certain event data,
you may choose to have different views.
We may view it from the viewpoint
of an order, from an order line or
from a delivery.
We may view it from the perspective
of the concert as a whole.
Or we may look at it from the viewpoint
of a booking on a particular ticket.
And, last but not least,
we focused on data quality problems.
In the next lecture we will
look at guidelines for
logging to address some of the issues
that we see in existing systems.
If you would like to read
more on this in Chapter 4,
we describe the nature of event data.
Where we explain some of the problems
that we have seen in this lecture.
You can also look at the paper
that is highlighted here at
the bottom which talks specifically about
the matrix with data quality problems.
Thank you for watching and
hope to see you soon.
[MUSIC]