[MUSIC]
Today we focus on the analysis of
so-called spaghetti processes.
We cannot apply all
the techniques discussed in
this course to such processes.
However spaghetti processes often allow
for major improvements in terms of speed,
cost and compliance, thus making
process mining extremely valuable.
The last lecture we explained
that there is a spectrum.
Ranging from spaghetti
processes to lasagna processes.
Spaghetti processes
are highly unstructured,
irregular, flexible, variable.
Whereas lasagna processes
are the opposite.
They are structured, regular,
and very repetitive.
So, in this spectrum, today, we will
look on the side of spaghetti processes.
Why are they called spaghetti processes?
I think this picture says it all.
And so, many connections and it is very
unclear what the actual structure is.
Here you can see another
example of a spaghetti process.
It is taken from a Dutch hospital,
an event log with information about
almost 3,000 patients generating
more than 100,000 events.
There are 619 different activities.
So it's clear that if you try
to plot them all in one diagram,
you will get something
that is very confusing.
There were also 266 different
resources involved.
So it's clear that these processes
are more complicated than the lasagna
process that we saw in
the previous lecture.
Here is another example.
This is the testing of wafer scanners.
This is the test process.
And if we zoom in to
parts of this process.
You can see that it is
indeed very spaghetti like.
If we look at spaghetti processes,
we unfortunately cannot execute the later
stages of the L* lifecycle model because
there is not a stable control flow model.
Where each of the states of
the model is visited frequently.
So we can forget about operational
support and prediction, recommendation and
these type of things.
There is simply not enough data to justify
a reliable prediction or recommendation.
So the earlier stages may
also be more challenging, but
on the other hand the improvement
potential in such processes maybe much
higher than in lasagna processes
because of their complexity,
their uncertainty and
the variability of things.
There is often room for improvement.
One should not be afraid of spaghetti.
First of all,
one can improve the process as explained.
On the other hand,
if you look at the spaghetti diagrams,
you can always make them simpler if they
are too intimidating for the end-user.
For example,
you can focus on a subset of activities.
Just look at the most frequent activities
or look at a selected part of the process.
For example, just the backoffice.
One can also focus on a subset of cases.
So for example, if a process in
a hospital is very confusing, you can
focus on a particular group of patients
that has some homogeneous behavior.
There are often natural subclasses,
like for example, gold customers.
The students that have passed.
One can think of all kinds
of homogeneous sets of
cases that are easier to analyze
than all the cases together.
Last but not least one can
focus on a subset of paths.
Here we typically focus on
the most frequent paths.
What are the highways in the process?
And in this way we can make
spaghetti models much simpler.
Let's take an example in disco.
So this is if we look at all the paths and
all the activities.
The model is very confusing.
However we can focus on
the most frequent activities.
And then this is the model that we get.
We can also focus on all activities.
But at the same time just look
at the most frequent paths.
Or we can do both.
We can focus just on the most
frequent activities and
the most frequent paths, and
then we get a simple model.
So we can always make spaghetti
models simpler by looking at
the most frequent behavior.
So we have been discussing about lasagna
processes and spaghetti processes.
So where do they appear?
Here you see the functional areas
within a typical organization.
For example one can look at procurement,
getting the products.
For example needed for production.
One can look at product development,
financial things, resource management,
like HRM.
One can look at sales and CRM,
so the things that happen before
you sell something to the customer.
And you can look at service.
And, so, activities that happen
after the products has been sold and
delivered to the customer.
So if we look at these functional areas,
then there are natural areas
where we find lasagna processes.
The things highlighted in blue
are typical areas where we can find
a substantial number of lasagna processes.
We can also look at where can
we find spaghetti processes and
then we find the areas
highlighted here in purple.
So there are areas like, for
example, service where we can find
both spaghetti and lasagna processes.
So to conclude we have been
talking about lasagna processes.
Structure processes of
a repetitive nature.
There we can easily detect and
remove bottlenecks.
We can analyze root causes for deviations,
we can compare different processes,
for example, processes in two
different departments, or for
two different types of customer groups.
And we can even do operational support
like prediction, recommendation, and
checking things online.
For spaghetti processes,
many of these things are impossible.
However, process discovery is
incredibly valuable for spaghetti
processes because they show a mirror,
they show what is actually happening and
they are revealing that things are not as
simple as they may seem at first glance.
It can be used to highlight important
problems in spaghetti processes and
there is often room for
a lot of improvement.
And we can go from
management by PowerPoint to
evidence-based process improvement.
So this is very valuable.
If you would like to read more
about the spaghetti processes.
Please take a look at chapter 12.
Thank you for watching this lecture.
See you next time.
[MUSIC]