[MUSIC]
Welcome to the last lecture of the course
on Process Mining: Data Science in Action.
Today, we recap the main
ingredients of this course.
Our world is driven by data.
In one of the first lectures,
we discussed the internet of events.
So we can find event data everywhere, and
the challenge is to use it in a good way.
This is a primary task for
the data scientist.
So data scientist should know about
statistic, should know about economics and
all kinds of aspect and
it's very important that such a data
scientist also knows about processes
because it's not just about static data,
in the end, you would like to
improve real processes and
products as they are being
used in the field.
So therefore, this combination is crucial.
One can see process mining as
something that bridges the gap
between process oriented techniques and
data oriented techniques.
So business process management, process
modeling and model-based analysis can be
combined with techniques like data mining,
business intelligence and statistics.
But for this, we need to have new
approaches, new techniques and
these have been discussed in this course.
One could say well, what's different
from business intelligence?
But if you would compare it
to business intelligence and
you would view analysis as
seeing a child that has fever,
then business intelligence will only be
able to tell you that the child has fever.
You can measure it and
put it in a nice dashboard.
However, process mining is able to
look inside the process itself.
So, BI is very different from process
mining as we have seen in this course.
Using tools like ProM and Disco and all
kinds of other tools, we are able to look
inside a process by analyzing the event
data that is widely available today.
If you look at the classical use of
models, it is often used for play out.
You have a model and
you generate behavior from it.
This is what happens if
you're doing simulation or
if you're using a BPMN system.
In this course, we focused on play-in and
replay, the confrontation between
models and
data where the actual behavior is leading.
This way, we can relate
process models to event logs.
We started with this very simple
model which identifies three
types of process mining.
Discovery, which can be seen as play-in.
Learning, a model from event data.
Conformance checking,
which requires a form of replay.
By replaying reality on top of the model,
we can see where reality is different
from the things that have been modeled.
And last but not least, enhancement.
Again, we replay the model, but
now with the purpose of repairing a model,
improving it, or extending it
with other perspectives like for
example, bottleneck information.
This is the simple model
that we started with.
In later lectures, we extended this
simple model just identifying three types
of process mining into something that
identified ten process mining activities,
but also distinguishing between offline
process mining and online process mining.
Things like operational support,
prediction, recommendation,
detecting deviations as they occur.
This refined process mining framework
also shows other perspectives like time,
resources and data.
These can be connected by using
the control flow backbone.
We also identified the difference
between normative and
descriptive models and
how this fits into this overall framework.
So process mining is much
more than process discovery.
It's about conformance analysis,
performance analysis,
decision point mining.
So if you see that in a process,
there is a part where some of
the customers go left and
some of the customers go right,
you would like to understand why
there are these differences.
Organizational mining,
which people are doing what?
Which people are most effective
in doing particular things?
Comparative process mining.
For example,
comparing different groups of customers or
comparing different departments to
operational support like things like
predication, recommendation, etc.
But process discovery is
still the starting point and
it is something that is fascinating.
It's extremely useful.
You start from raw event data and
you automatically construct
control flow models.
It's often challenging, but always
possible, you can always simplify models,
spaghetti-like models into simpler models
by looking at the most frequent behavior,
but it requires expertise, the expertise
that you've learned in this course.
Which algorithm to apply?
What is the effect of using
a particular representational bias?
And we have also seen that it is difficult
because we never know the real process and
we only can see positive examples in the
event log that we are using for analysis.
So it's a fascinating area with many
open problems and many opportunities.
If you do process discovery,
you will find out that
there are actually multiple forces
that are competing with one another,
fitness versus simplicity,
generalization versus precision.
There are metrics available for
all of these four dimensions, and if you
are using a process discovery technique,
you need to identify how important
are all these different dimensions.
We also discussed tooling.
In this course,
we have been heavily using ProM and
Disco as an example of an academic open
source tool and a commercial tool.
This way you get some feeling of
the available functionality in
existing software.
In this last week, we also looked at
running a process mining project.
We looked at the L * life cycle
model identifying different stages of
a process mining project.
We've also seen that if we talk about
processes, there is a spectrum going from
lasagna processes that are highly
structured that we can apply the entire L *
life cycle model to spaghetti like
processes which are less structured, more
variable but where the potential value
of process mining can be much higher.
This course was designed around
the book Process Mining: Discovery,
Conformance Checking and
Enhancement of Business Processes.
In the different lectures, we visited
all of the chapters of this book.
Sometimes, we had some excursions
to neighboring fields or
recent developments, but it is a very
good reference for this course.
What one should realize
is that in this course,
we have only seen the tip of the iceberg.
There are many more process
mining techniques and
questions possible and available.
And you're encouraged to
visit websites like the
one shown here to explore
this field in more detail.
We are now coming to
a conclusion of this course on
Process Mining: Data Science in Action.
You should realize that there
are opportunities everywhere.
There is event data everywhere, so you can
apply the things that you've learned in
this course at many, many places.
Experience the magic of process mining,
discovering and
improving processes based on
facts rather than fiction.
Thank you for watching this lecture and
all the other lectures.
I hope you enjoyed this course.
I also hope that you will continue
to apply the things you've learned.
Opportunities are endless.
All the best!
[MUSIC]