[MUSIC]
Today, we focus on the analysis of so
called lasagna processes.
We can apply all the techniques discussed
in this course to such processes.
In fact, for lasagna processes,
control for discovery only serves as
a starting point for
more advanced process mining techniques.
We've used the term spaghetti and
lasagna processes several times before.
So what does it actually mean?
If we use the term spaghetti processes,
we are referring to
processes that are unstructured,
that have irregular behavior,
that are characterized by words
like flexible and variable.
Lasagna processes on the other hand.
Correspond to processes that
are structured, repetitive, regular, and
that can be controlled.
Of course, these are two extremes.
In fact,
one can talk about a spectrum of processes
ranging from very unstructured
to very structured processes.
Today, we focus on lasagna processes.
Processes that are repetitive and
well structured.
How can we define lasagna processes,
here is an attempt at the rule of thumb.
Saying that for
a lasagna process you should be able to
create a model that has
a fitness of at least 0.8, and
the stakeholders can confirm
the validity of the model.
So this excludes a model
like a flower model.
The mainstream behavior should fit
into a relatively simple model.
This is an example of a lasagna process.
It's taken from a Dutch municipality and
it corresponds to
event data in the context of people
requesting for household helps.
So the event log here is
using over 500 requests,
500 cases, generating approximately
five and a half thousand events.
From the dotted chart you can
already see that this process has
a rather regular behavior.
There is a continuous
flow of new cases and
cases typically take relatively
short amount of time.
If you look at the color of the dots you
can also see that there
are relatively few activities.
If we use the inductive miner then
this is the model that is discovered.
We can convert it to a Petri net or
a BPMN model.
And they all show the same
relatively simple process.
If you look at the fitness
of this discovered process.
The fitness is almost perfect, in fact 505
of the 528 cases fit
perfectly into this model.
So we can do performance analysis.
And the activity highlighted
here in red is the bottleneck.
It's an optional activity
that often takes a long time.
If you use Disco rather than ProM,
we find exactly the same results.
And so here in blue you can
see frequencies, in red,
yellow you can see the time
spent in the various phases.
And we find the same bottlenecks.
All the stages of the L* lifecycle model
can be visited for such Lasagna processes.
And so we can even do operational support
because the behavior is very regular,
and therefore, for example, we can
predict things based on historic data.
Also, all the ten process mining
activities in the refined reference model
can actually be applied in
the context of lasagna processes.
So lasagna processes are easy to discover,
but
the drawback is that it is less
interesting to discover the real process.
Because typically people know what
a real process because it is so regular.
So the added value is that the whole
process mining tool box can be applied.
So typically replay techniques are very
important to understand bottlenecks,
to understand decisions in the process
to see which customers take longer,
which customers take shorter.
So the advanced types of process
mining based on alignments
with respect to a relatively simple model,
is where the value lies.
If you would like to read more
on these types of processes,
lasagna processes,
take a look at chapter 11.
Thank you for watching this lecture,
see you next time.
[MUSIC]