[MUSIC]
Welcome to this lecture of the course on
Process Mining: Data Science in Action.
We are coming closer to
the end of this course.
So it's time for some reflections.
Today we compare process models to maps.
We use this metaphor to better
understand the role of process mining.
There is a long tradition in making maps.
And here you can see a nice example.
At the same time, we can view
process models as maps of processes.
So it's interesting to see
what we can learn from maps.
This is a map showing
the center of Moscow.
If you look at such a map we can
see that abstraction is being used.
Insignificant roads are left
out to not clutter the diagram.
At the time, smaller entities
are aggregated into larger ones.
For example, if we would draw 'em out,
we would see individual cities.
If we look at one city in itself,
we can see suburbs.
Also, maps play with size and color.
These are not the size and
the color of the real entities, but they
highlight the things that are important.
For example, highways will
have a different color than other roads,
to signify their importance.
Moreover, the layout of things has a clear
meaning that everybody can understand.
So this is what we can learn from maps.
If we now compare maps to process models.
And, here you can see three examples.
Then, we can see that process
models are actually very poor.
So, where is abstraction?
Where is aggregation?
How are size and color being used?
What does the layout of
the different activities in
a process model actually mean?
There are no strong conventions for this.
Take for
example a look at this process model.
The activities,
which activities correspond to
metropolis which activities
correspond to small village?
Which connections correspond to highways?
Which connections
correspond to dirt roads?
We cannot see these types of things.
So if we do process mining, we would
like to learn from cartography and
add that to the diagrams.
It's also very important
to realize that there is
no such thing as the map
of a process model.
One would give in one reality,
there may be different process models
depending on the purpose for
which one is the making the map.
Take for example again a look at
this map of the center of Moscow.
We may want to zoom in into
a particular area around the Kremlin.
It's the same reality, but if we zoom in,
we see that a different map is
useful to look at this reality.
We may want to look at this
diagram if we are interested, for
example, to see where there
are trees in the center of Moscow.
If we travel by a subway,
we need another map.
This is the subway map of Moscow.
Completely different map
than the maps that we have seen before but
still looking at the same reality.
If we take a bicycle we
would prefer using this map.
So there are different maps depending
on the purpose one is after.
This shows that
a map is a view on reality.
It's an abstraction that has to be useful.
The map itself is not the same as reality.
Therefore one should not seek in
finding the map, or the process model.
All these things that we can learn from
maps also apply to process models.
Here you see my glasses
on top of an event log.
A model can be seen as a pair of glasses.
By using these glasses, one can see
relevant information in the raw data,
and there is not just one view there may
be multiple views, as is illustrated here.
So depending on the purpose one
needs to look at the event data
from a particular angle, and different
models are useful for this purpose.
It's also important to see process
models not as static entities.
One should breathe life into process
models using the event data available.
If one does not do this,
these process models will be,
will end up in some drawer, and
nobody will ever look at it.
So we need to connect process models
to data as we have seen in this course.
Again, we see the map of
the center of Moscow, and
now highlighted in red are the places
where there are traffic jams.
And so the streets that are green,
that the traffic is flowing well,
the streets that are red are highlighted
bottlenecks, indicating congestion.
So on maps one can project traffic jams.
One can also project real estate,
which are the houses that are for
sale in the center of Moscow.
We can highlight the location of vehicles,
like trucks or trains.
One can project crime rates.
One can project all kinds
of things on top of maps.
The same one can do by combining
process models with event data.
In a process model one can also
highlight the bottlenecks.
One can also highlight where
the model is deviating from reality.
Where the biggest cost appear,
where there are risks.
All of these things can be
projected on process models,
thereby breathing life in
these otherwise static models.
Here you can see some
examples,using the tools that we
have been seeing in this course.
So here you see a replay
of an event log on top of
a process model that was discovered.
And at any point in time the animation
is showing a particular state.
And for example one can see traffic
jams in a process model in this way.
The same holds for Disco, and many of
the other process mining tools that we
have been discussing in one
of the recent lectures.
Projecting information
on maps is not that new.
Here you can see a very nice example
of a map showing Napoleon's army.
What you can see is that the Army
starts with over 400,000 soldiers,
and then while approaching Moscow,
more and more soldiers die.
In the middle there are 175,000 people,
soldiers still alive.
In the end 100,000 soldiers reached
Moscow, but then they need to retreat.
And in the end only
10,000 soldiers return.
So this is an early example
of information visualization.
And it's exactly the same ideas
that we are applying when we
are applying when we are projecting
event data on top of process models.
It is not sufficient to breathe life
into these models by projecting
event data in a smart way.
We should also try to actively use
the process my, models, for example, for
operational support.
So we should use these
models on a daily basis.
This is very similar to
using a navigation device.
If one looks at a navigation
device for example from TomTom.
Then these devices are showing
you recommendations.
Take the next street and turn left.
We can look at predictions.
What is the estimated arrival time?
It's also warning us if we are driving
too fast at the particular location.
So if you look at these things, you can
clearly recognize the operational support
features that we
have been discussing before.
So how can a navigation device do that?
It's the smart combination of maps,
historic information,
where are typically traffic jams and
things like that, and current information.
The combination of these things
allows the navigation device
to predict and recommend.
And when we do process mining we would
like to do exactly the same thing.
Note that the navigation
device is also very flexible.
If a driver ignores the instructions,
the navigation device will still
try to support the driver.
And so if the driver goes right rather
than left on the next intersection,
the navigation will try to pick up on
what the driver is trying to do and
support the driver in the actions
that he or she wants to do.
Many information systems are unable
to do these types of things.
They're not combining these different
types of information and
they are typically very inflexible,
or not providing any support at all.
So we can learn from
these types of things.
So in conclusion,
process models are like maps.
We can learn from cartography
to improve our process models.
Smartly using color and
size to indicate the parts
of the process model which are important
or where there is congestion.
We need to highlight this type of
information on top of process models,
otherwise nobody will care.
Often multiple maps are needed, depending
on the goal that we have in mind.
The same if you go by bicycle or you
go by subway, or you go by train.
You need to have a different map.
The same holds for process models.
We need to connect maps to real
data to show traffic jams and
all kinds of other information.
And last but not least,
information systems that we developed
should be more like navigation devices.
Flexible and adaptive.
If you would like to learn
more about this map metaphor.
What we can learn from maps and
navigation devices.
Please take a look at chapter
13 of the Process Mining book.
Thank you for watching this lecture.
See you soon for
the last lecture of this course.
[MUSIC]