[MUSIC]
Welcome to this lecture.
Today we will introduce the L *
lifestyle model for process mining.
It identifies the main stages
of a process mining project, and
aims to guide the analyst conducting
a process improvement project.
Organizations are drowning in data.
So the challenge is, how to conduct
a process mining project so that you
can deal with these large amounts of data
and get valuable information out of them.
One way to view a process
mining project is to
view it as a collection of use cases.
So use cases have a set of goals and
corresponding actions, so
let's take a look at the goals.
Typically, you are doing process
mining because you would like to
improve some key performance indicator,
or a set of key performance indicators.
Things related to time, cost, risk,
quality, all kinds of aspects.
Let's focus at time.
For example, one may want to minimize
the mean flow time, the waiting time,
or the response time.
It may also be the case that one is not so
interested in the mean time, but
one would like to maximize
the service level.
That is, the percentage handled
within an agreed upon period.
If you look at the action side then we
are not doing process mining just for
the analysis itself, we would like
to have actionable information.
Information that we can
do something with and
that we can actually use
to improve the process.
There can be actions related to
a redesign, a structural change of
the process based on the insights
generated by process mining.
It can also be that process mining
triggers adjustments of the process.
These are non-structural changes,
like changing a parameter.
A typical example is if there
is a fluctuation in case volume.
That you may want to add,
temporarily, a few resources.
These are at the process level.
one may also want
to intervene at the level of individual
cases or individual resources based on
the insights generated by process mining.
The most sophisticated form of
process mining is operational support.
Then you are systematically using
current event data, for example,
to recommend the best activity or the best
resource at a particular point in time.
Here you can see a list of
typical process mining use cases.
For example, there may be the goal
to reduce the flow time by 30%,
and one would like to know
what are the changes in
the process that should be
made to achieve this goal.
Lets now take a look at the L *
lifecycle model for process mining.
It is a model that describes different
stages of a process mining project.
In a way it is describing
an ideal process mining project.
This is aiming at lasagna processes,
so highly structured processes,
not the chaotic spaghetti-like processes
that we will also discuss later.
It is related to existing lifecycle models
in the context of data mining and BI.
Here we can see two
existing lifecycle models.
For example CRISP-DM and SEMMA.
They describe lifecycle models for
a data mining project.
They are not process mining specific.
And they are of a rather high level.
The L * lifecycle model
is much more detailed and
tailored towards the needs
of process mining.
So what are the stages of
the L * lifecycle model?
In stage 0, we plan and justify.
In many cases it's crucial
to have a business case
to see possible improvements
that justify doing the analysis.
One should bear in mind that in general,
there are three types of projects,
data-driven projects, projects that
are driven by the availability of data,
organizations that say, we are flooded by
data, we do not know what to do with it,
but we are sure that there is some value
in the information that we have and
we are not tapping into it yet.
A second type of process mining
project is question-driven.
People would like to understand
why there are certain problems in
particular areas of the process.
The third type is goal-driven.
There the goal is simply to
improve a particular KPI.
So these contextual factors
are very important,
to see and understand before you
start doing process mining analysis.
Then in stage 1, after you planned and
justified your activities,
one needs to locate, extract, and
transform the event data available.
This is a non-trivial task.
In previous lectures, we have
discussed how to extract the data and
what the factors are that you should note.
But it's not just event data
that you should collect,
you should also collect existing models.
For example, if you would like to do
conformance checking with respect to
some nominative model,
you should collect a model before
doing the actual process mining.
There may be all kinds of other
artifacts that are useful input for
the analysis process.
One should think about objectives and the
questions that one would like to answer.
In general one should exploit
as much domain knowledge and
knowledge which is in the heads
of people as possible.
After extracting the data and
all the other artifacts, in stage 2,
you create a control-flow model and
connect it to the event log.
As we have seen before, control-flow
is the backbone of every process.
So, we should first create
a suitable control-flow model and
connect it to event data.
The notion of alignments
discussed in the context of
conformance checking is key here.
We would like to relate observed
behavior to modeled behavior.
This is a highly iterative process,
so all the stages are iterative,
but in particular, this stage typically
requires several iterations until we
have a control-flow model well-connected
to the available event data.
After having the control-flow model,
we can start looking at
the other perspectives.
So we can replay event data,
on the model, and then
extend the model with other perspectives,
as we have seen in earlier lectures.
The result is an overall model capturing
all the different perspectives.
Finally, we have stage 4,
operational support.
This is the situation where we are not
just looking at historic information but
where we are using process mining
in real-time in an online setting.
So we would like to detect
deviations as they occur.
We would like to make predictions, for
example, about the remaining flow time.
We would like to make recommendations,
like it's best to have this
activity executed by this person.
Note that the stage 4 is only
reachable for lasagna processes.
So processes that are repetitive and
have a stable structure.
What is now the relationship between
the L * model and the use cases?
Well, that the relationship is very easy.
First of all,
the goal in the use case correspond to
the things that we are doing in stage 1.
Second, process mining should
lead to actionable information and
this is relating to
the other side of use cases.
We can also relate the L* lifecycle model
to the refined process mining framework,
as is shown here.
For example, if you look at stage 2,
and stage 2 is
mainly concerned with things like
discovery, conformance checking.
Comparing models,
promoting changes in the defacto model to
the de jure model and
a general exploration of event data.
If you look at stage 3,
it is mainly related to the process
mining activity enhance.
By replaying the event log on the model,
we can extend the model using information
extracted from the event log.
Last but not least, if we look at stage 4,
we are talking about operational support.
And that corresponds to the process mining
activities predict, recommend, and detect.
In this lecture, we described the L*
lifecycle model for process mining.
As we have seen, the lifecycle model
consists of different stages that
one should go through to do
a successful process mining project.
The approach is highly iterative,
so it may be
that insights in a later stage lead
to changes in an earlier stage.
It is very important to
plan the project well.
First of all, you need to make
sure to get the event data needed.
Second, one should always
think about the business case.
What is one actually improve?
Because analysis is not a goal in itself.
If you would like to read more
on the L * lifecycle model,
please take a look at
chapter 11 of the book.
Thank you for watching and
hope to see you soon.
[MUSIC]