[MUSIC]
Glad to see you again.
In the last two lectures we showed
that decision tree analysis can be
used to enrich discovered process models.
We now use the timestamps in the
event logs to analyze performance and
suggest improvements.
If we have processes that
have no problems in them,
where everything is running smooth,
there are no bottlenecks,
then process mining may not
have a very large added value.
However, if you have processes like this
that have huge performance problems,
then process mining can be extremely
valuable because there're many ways in
which analyzing the process
may help to improve it.
In this lecture we will focus
on bottleneck analysis,
using the timestamps
that are present in logs.
We would like to find out where are the
bottlenecks, and why are they there.
To do this, we are using event logs.
Where events have timestamps.
But often, also transactional information.
Like start and complete.
For example, for case one activity,
a started at time 12 and ended at time 19.
And the same we can see for all the other
events for this particular case.
So this is the input that we would
like to use for performance analysis.
We can look at basic performance
information, like, for
example, the duration of cases.
When we look at such data we can see
when things start and when things end.
But you can do this with any BI tool.
What makes process mining different,
is that you can look inside the process,
other than just looking at
spreadsheet-like information that
you see in many of the BI tools.
So we would like to understand the more
detailed timed behavior of a process.
So this slide shows a lot of
information related to
the execution of just three cases.
So it is showing durations,
waiting times, and
all kinds of other things
that we can measure.
If we replay these three
cases on this process model.
Let's zoom in to some of the parts.
For example we can see that
case one started at time 12.
Then for case one,
activity a was being executed, and
that started at time 12 and
ended at time 19.
So we know that the duration of this
particular instance of activity a for
case one was seven time units.
We can also look at the time in
between a and b, the waiting time.
That is equivalent to six for
this particular instance.
If we look at the bottom part,
then we can see that through f,
one case was looping back.
Case number three.
So we can find two activity instances.
For activity d, for case three.
We can also see multiple
waiting times related to
this extra iteration of this case three.
We can also look at the end, and there
we can see the completion time of cases.
So this is the detailed information that
we can get by replaying the event log,
after alignment,
on top of the process model.
We can also take another view.
More like a Gantt chart
overview of the event log.
So in this diagram, we see for
every case what are the activities that
are being executed, and
what are the waiting times.
The black bars correspond to
the actual processing of an activity
instance, for a particular case.
The grey parts correspond
to waiting times.
So an activity instance is enabled,
but was not yet started.
If we look at case three, we can for
example see the interval of activity a for
case three.
And we can see that after a completed,
that the waiting time for c and d started.
And then after c and
d the waiting for e started.
Note that the waiting for e only starts
after d and c have both completed.
So this visualizes from a case
perspective, what has happened.
We can also take a resource perspective.
It's exactly the same, but
now along the y-axis, we see people.
So we can see what they are doing,
and when cases were waiting for
them to start executing
particular activity instances.
We can also mix these
two views using colors.
So now the red color for example refers
to activity instances of case one.
What you can see in this diagram,
that because of the extra loop,
the iteration of case three,
there are more activities for
case three than for
the other two activities.
So, after providing such a Gantt chart,
and the details replay of
the event log on top of the process model,
we can collect all kinds of statistics.
So we can see the waiting
times in between activities.
We can see the mean time, we can see
variations, and things like that.
We can also look at the service times.
So, if we have start and complete events,
we can measure how long activities take,
and we can again compute the average and
standard deviation over these times.
We can also compute routing probabilities.
So for example, in this particular
example, there was a 50:50
probability of choosing b over c.
And so both have an equal probability.
The choice after e.
You can see that a branch to
g has a probability of 0.5.
The other two branches have
a probability of 0.25.
So we can also learn this.
Let's take a look at another event
log to see another example of
this detailed replay and
corresponding performance.
Metrics that we can compute.
So if we take a look at this log,
then Pete started by
executing activity a at time ten,
and ended at time 12.
Then we can again take at a look
at the whole event log as a ref,
again referring to just very few cases.
For example, this event log ends
with Carol starting activity f for
case two at time 57 and
ending this activity instance at time 60.
So again we can take this, we can take the
event log, we can take the process model,
and we can again try to estimate service
times waiting times routing probabilities.
If we do this,
then we first do the detailed replay.
So these are the detailed
statistics that we can gather.
Note in this example that there
are two silent activities.
The end split before b and c,
and the end join after b and c.
We cannot see them in the log, but
through alignments we know when they
are being executed and
how to align them properly with the model.
So again, we can collect
statistics about waiting times.
We can look at the average, we can,
you can look at the standard deviation.
We can look at service times as you
can see here.
So we can collect all kinds of statistics
including routing probabilities.
So these are the things that
we can get from event logs.
When I tell this, I hope that you can
see that you have actually seen and
used this before.
When you are using tools like Disco.
They are replaying the event
log on top of the model,
to indicate what are the parts
where the biggest bottlenecks are.
So for example here, fix arcs
colored in red correspond to the main
bottlenecks in this particular process.
We've also seen this in
the context of ProM.
And so we can let things highlight in red
the moment that there is
a performance problem.
And so we have used these things before,
but now we
can see how these timestamps are actually
being used at a more detailed level.
Using process mining, we can
automatically discover process models.
We have seen that.
When we discuss conformance
checking we have shown
that you can relate an event log and
a model through the notion of alignment.
So even if the real process
deviates a bit from the model,
you can still relate real
behavior to a process model.
Once you have these alignments,
you can do a replay of the entire log.
And by doing that and
inspecting the timestamps you can identify
bottlenecks and measure all kinds of
other performance related things.
The result of all of
this is a process model
extended with performance information.
And such a process model can
be the starting point for
all kinds of process improvement and
operational support.
In one of the future lectures for example,
we will focus on predictions, and
these predictions are using exactly the
types of statistics that I showed today,
that you can collect from event logs.
In chapter eight, we are relating
timestamps to process models, and
you can read more about how to extend
models with this extra perspective.
Thank you for watching this lecture.
See you next time.
[MUSIC]