[MUSIC]
Welcome to this lecture.
After enriching models with time and
data related aspects we now focus
on the resource perspective.
We will learn to create resource
activity and hand over work matrices.
Moreover we will see that social
networks can be created from event data.
Events that we see in event logs,
they often capture human behavior and that
makes their analysis very interesting.
Humans leave all kinds of
trails in all kinds of systems.
The first week,
we spoke about the Internet of events.
One can look at what people are doing
socially, on Facebook or Twitter.
One can look at work-related systems.
And in the future, more and more devices
will be connected to the Internet, and
will collect data about human behavior.
So in this lecture, we will focus on
analyzing the social aspect of event logs.
And we will look at things
like social networks.
So, what is the input for such analysis?
We have event logs and these event
logs may refer to the actual people,
the actual actors, executing
the activities, as you can see here.
So events have a resource attribute, and
using these resource attributes,
we can do very simple forms of analysis.
For example if you look at this so-called
resource-activity matrix, we can see
how many times a resource is
executing particular activities.
So if you look at this particular example
extracted from the event log that we
have seen before,
we can see that activity a is
executed on average exactly once.
And we can see that by adding up
the numbers in this particular column.
What we can also see is that Pete,
Mike, and
Ellen are the only ones
executing this activity.
So in 30% of the cases,
a is being executed by Pete.
In 50% of the cases,
a is being executed by Mike, and
in the remaining 20% it
is executed by Ellen.
So we can read such information
from the resource activity metrics.
What we can also see is that Sara is
the only person able to execute activities
e and f based on the evidence that
we have seen in the event log.
On average, 2.3 times per case
activity e is executed by Sara.
So the resource-activity matrix
provides basic insights into who
is doing what in the event log.
But the information is very basic.
Let's take a look at this event log and
also try to create
a resource activity matrix.
So again in this log we see that Pete
starts by executing activity a for
case 1 at time 10.
If we look at the end of this
event log we can see that Carol
executes activity f for case 2.
Here we can see all the information.
So we can see the process model and
we can see the event log.
And now try to create a resource
activity matrix yourself.
This may take some time.
So the answer is shown here.
Based on the event log we can extract
this resource activity matrix.
So, what we can see is that Pete
is the only one able to execute a.
And for example, Carol is the only one
able to execute f, and on average,
this is done once per case.
The matrix that we just shown
is not really showing any
relationships between people.
For that we need to
create a social network.
So how does that work?
Let's first start by looking
at a real-life example.
So this is the social network of
the so-called Al-Qaeda network
after the 9/11 disaster.
So this social network was created
by analyzing newspaper articles.
Social network analysis, creating these
types of graphs is already very old.
Already in the 1930s Moreno
created such networks.
We can view them as a graph
with thicker and thinner lines
indicating the relationships, or
we can look at them in matrix form.
The nodes in such a diagram
that correspond to people or
groups of people or departments,
the arcs they indicate relationships
they have weights or
inverted notion of distance.
So what you can see in this social network
is that the strongest relationships
are indicated using thick lines.
We can also compute metrics over
such social networks to see
which are the people that
are most central in this network.
We can also identify cliques of people,
people that have many relationships among
them as a group, but with fewer
connections to the rest of the network.
So this the notation that we will use.
So the ovals correspond to
organizational entities.
These can be individual resources, people,
roles, but also things like departments.
The arcs correspond to relationships.
The thickness of an arc indicates how
strong this relationship is and
we can also vary the size
of the ovals to indicate
how frequent the entity is
executing particular activities.
There are many ways to measure
the importance of a node.
For example,
a person in such a social network.
There is the notion of degree centrality.
This simply counts,
if you look at the node,
how many arcs it has to other nodes,
so it's a very localized notion.
So, the things that are highlighted in red
indicate the nodes that have
the highest degree of centrality.
If you look at the diagram in the middle,
we can see closeness centrality.
So now the nodes in red
are most important.
Not because they have many direct
neighbors, but it is based on
one divided by the sum of all shorter
paths to this particular node.
So the things that are most
central are indicated in red.
A related notion is
betweenness centrality.
Now we count the fraction of
shortest paths between any two
nodes going through the nodes that
we are trying to analyze.
So you can see depending on
the notion that you choose
different entities will become central
in the network that we are considering.
This is a topic in itself.
There are many of such
definitions, and
it's a bit outside
the scope of this course.
However, based on event logs we can
create such networks and
apply standard techniques to analyze them.
So, based on an event log,
how can we create such a social network?
Well, this is done using
the handover of work matrix.
This is a matrix where we show,
how frequently work is handed over
from one person, to another person.
So to be more precise,
we count the number of times work is
handed over from one resource to
another resource on average per case.
So based on the event log
that we have seen earlier
we construct this handover of work
matrix where Pete is handing over
work to himself on average
0.135 times per case.
If we look at Sara and Mike,
their relationship, for
example Sara is handing over work to
Mike on the average 1.4 times per case.
So the higher these numbers,
the more frequently work is passed on
from one person to another person.
When we do this analysis,
we should of course take into
account the underlying process.
So if things are concurrent,
then we should not count handovers
between concurrent activities, because
they do not causally depend on each other.
So while creating this matrix we take
into account the control flow structure.
So based on this matrix,
we can create a graph where we
leave out the arcs which have
a weight that is too low.
So for example, if we look at the matrix,
we can see that there is
a relationship between Ellen and Pete.
But it is too weak to
be shown in this graph,
because we chose the threshold of 0.1.
So this is the social network based
on the handover of work matrix.
In this picture,
the thickness of the arc relates to
the number in the handover of work matrix.
All the ovals have the same size.
We are not using the feature that
we can make the size depending on
the frequency with which people
have executed activities for cases.
This diagram is at the level
of individual resources.
We can also create diagrams that
look at roles or departments.
In fact, if we look at an information
system of a typical organization,
there are lots of information
relating people to departments or
to particular roles in the organization.
In more advanced information
systems even the event log
itself has information about the role or
the department that people have when
they are executing a particular event.
In our small example, we are now
assuming that there are three roles,
the role of Assistant, the role of
Expert and the role of Manager.
For example Sara is the only person
that can play the role of Manager,
while we have three assistants,
Pete, Mike and, Ellen.
So if we have grouping of
resources in this way,
we can also create social networks
at the higher level of abstraction.
So now you can see the social
network relating assistance to
managers to experts.
And so, in this picture,
again the arcs show how frequent, for
example work is handed over
from a manager to an assistant.
But what we can also see is
that the size of the oval is
indicating how much work is done by
people having a particular role.
So this gives insights at the desired
level of abstraction that we
would like to use.
ProM supports the construction of such
social networks in many different ways.
So, here we see some examples.
So first of all there is a plug-in
that creates a social network based on
the handover of work.
This is exactly what we have seen before.
However, there are many other ways that we
can build a social network
based on event data.
One example is that we can consider
people to be close, to have a strong
relationship, if they typically execute
the same collection of activities.
And so people doing the same types of
things, are considered to be close.
People doing very different
things are considered to
be very far apart from each other.
We can do this at the level of activities.
We can also do this at the level of cases.
So people that often work together on
the same cases are considered to be close.
People never working together on the same
case are considered to be more distant.
So using these distance notions
we can create social networks.
And for example here you see a social
network based on the handover of
work metric, as we have seen before.
So the coloring can be
used to identify cliques.
We can remove arcs that are infrequent.
We can influence the size of the bubbles
based on particular characteristics so
it's a very flexible tool.
If we look at problem we can also analyze
resource behavior, social behavior,
by creatively replacing activity
names by resource names.
And some of the plugins
actually have a feature for
this, to do this automatically.
So for example,
if you look at inductive minor,
what you see here is the discovered
control flow process.
So now the nodes are activities,
but you can change the view and
create a model where the nodes correspond
not to activities but to people.
Now we see a different type of process and
it is showing how work is flowing
from one person to another person.
So in a way you can think of this, as a
kind of social network, but on top of it,
because it's like a process,
we can animate things over it.
So in summary, what we have seen is that
we can create a resource activity matrix,
showing who is doing what,
very basic information.
We can create a handover of
work matrix showing how work is
being transferred from one
person to another person.
And this can be used to
create a social network.
But the handover of work matrix is
just one of many possibilities that we
can use to create such a social network.
Event logs provide lots of information
that can be used to create
different views on the social
behavior inside work processes.
Once we have such a social network,
it can be analyzed in many different ways.
We can compute which
are the most central people,
what are cliques of people often
working together, etcetera.
So it is very important that
one is aware that one can
analyze the human behavior in these
processes that we are analyzing,
and this often provides clues
on how to do things better.
To read more about this,
please take a look at chapter 8.
Thank you for watching,
and hope to see you soon.
[MUSIC]