[MUSIC]
Welcome to this lecture.
Process mining extends far beyond
discovering control-flow models.
In recent lectures, we have seen that
we can mine different perspectives.
Today we will see that these perspectives
can be combined into more complete models.
Here you see a picture of an elephant,
but you see several people that
are blindfolded and they just see or
are able to touch part of the elephant.
So, the person that touches
the trunk may think it's a snake.
The person that touches the body
may think that it is a wall.
The person that is touching one
of the four feet may think it's
a tree, etcetera.
This is the same problem that we have
if we try to do process mining, and
we look at one perspective in isolation.
So if you look at process models,
it is not just control-flow, it is also
about data, it is also about time,
it's about resources,
it's about costs, it's about risk.
We need to combine all of these
different perspectives in a single model
to be able to really apply process
mining in a meaningful way.
So a process model is composed
of different perspectives and
what is always the backbone
is the control-flow.
So things are attached to the control-flow
and in that way they are related.
So activities in the control-flow, for
example, they are executed by particular
resources and take particular amounts of
time, and may have a particular guard.
So the control-flow is binding
all these things together.
This is a figure that we have seen before.
What we have seen earlier was that in
the beginning we focused very much on
control-flow and
just discovery and conformance.
And in recent lectures we have
extended the scope to also look at
other perspectives like time,
resources, and data.
And also look at things like enhancing
models with different perspectives.
So, this picture ties everything together.
So, how does it work?
We start with an event log.
Based on the event log we can create
a process model using process discovery
techniques or we can also make a model
by hand or a combination of both.
Then we connect the events in
the event log to this process model,
focusing mostly on the control-flow.
Once we have established that
connection we can start mining for
the other perspectives.
So, we try to find roles.
We try to find bottlenecks.
Where are particular
amounts of time being passed.
We try to identify guards.
And we put everything together in
an integrated model that we can return and
use for other types of analysis like,
for example, simulation.
So let's take a look at
the individual steps.
So start with the control-flow.
It is discovered or made by hand.
And what is very important
is that we should be able to
align it with the event log.
Once we do that, we can start looking for
the other perspectives.
We had two lectures on decision learning,
as a learning decision points.
What are the guards involved
in such a decision, and
we can add that to the process model.
Here in red, you can see the guards.
What is not shown are the variables,
and read and write arcs.
If we extend the model further,
we can also add such information.
We also looked at the time perspective,
finding out where are bottlenecks.
We can attach such
information to activities and
to the,
places in the corresponding Petri net.
We can also capture
routing probabilities so
this way we can enrich the model with
time and performance related information.
Last but not least we can extend
the model with information about
resources the people involved in
the process or the machines being used.
So here you see three roles that we
have learned automatically based
on the event log, and they serve
as the linking pin between activities in
the process model and individual workers.
So a role corresponds to
a set of activities that
require this role and
a set of people has this particular role.
So we can learn such things automatically,
as we have seen in the previous lecture,
or we can obtain them from
the information system.
And then we put everything together.
And such a more holistic model can
be used to diagnose the process.
It gives ideas on re-engineering,
how to improve the process.
It can also be used for
operational support.
One of the topics that we will
cover in a later lecture.
For example,
such a model can be used for simulation.
What is very important is that we are
aware of the limits of the models that we
are generating.
They may be over or under fitting.
The models tend to be descriptive.
They describe what has happened,
not what should happen.
So when using such more complicated
models, one should be very
much aware of the limitations of the
models that are automatically generated.
Often they are just a starting point for
further analysis.
And they require editing adding
additional assumptions etc.,
to be really used in subsequent steps.
If we do process mining we are often
focusing on the as is situation.
How are things now, where are the
problems, how can we understand, and
explain these problems?
But we would like to move from
as is to the to be situation.
One of the things that we can do for
example is to use operational support and
to give recommendations and
predictions to help people doing
the execution of the process better.
We can also use simulation.
And simulation aims to
answer what if questions.
So you have an as-is model and
you explore different to-be situations.
And using simulation you can do that.
So what is simulation?
It's just playing out a process model,
so you have a process model and
you just run the process as it has
been modeled you do that several times.
And you can, for example,
collect performance related information.
And this can be used to
explore alternative designs.
For example, designs where two activities
are no longer executed in sequence, but
they are executed concurrently.
You can also see what effect is of
adding resources or removing resources.
This requires us to have a model of
the process itself and it's environment.
And for example to model the availability
of resources and the arrival of new cases.
And process mining of course provides
exactly the input required to
create such simulation models.
Let's take a look at this
in a bit more detail.
This picture shows the different
ingredients of a simulation model.
For a simulation model, we should
not just know the control-flow, but
we also should have information
about environment of the process.
So how many resources are available
when are they available,
what can they do, at what speed.
We should also have information
about arrival process and
all kinds of other information
related to the context of the process.
We can learn much of such
information from process mining.
Process mining is providing information
for example about bottlenecks and
things like that.
We can add that to the process model.
To do simulation
experiments we also need to
decide on things like the number of sub
runs and the length of each sub run.
And the performance indicators
that we would like to measure.
So these are the ingredients.
But if you do a process mining
project in a classical way
you may encounter many problems.
So, this slide identified
ten different risks that you
typically encounter if you
do a simulation project.
So often simulation models have
hidden assumptions which are not
corresponding to reality.
Using process mining you can avoid many of
the risks that are being highlighted here.
The confrontation with event data helps to
improve the quality of simulation results.
It is very well known that
simulation and
other statistical
techniques can be misused.
And you often see that in
the context of simulation.
Where just by playing with a parameter
which is not really explicit for
the end user, one can influence
the results dramatically.
So one should be very careful when
applying simulation in reality.
Using process mining one can move
beyond traditional simulation.
So traditional business process simulation
often looks at processes in steady state.
In reality processes are often
not in steady state.
For example the arrival process may vary,
the availability of resources may vary,
and this should be
incorporated in the model.
And one can only do that by extracting
information from event logs
to be able to replay processes
in a more realistic manner.
And to explore different alternatives.
Classical simulation models also often
have a very naive view of resources.
Resources that are constantly available,
and are eager to work, and
always work at the same pace.
In reality this is not true.
Process mining helps
to find out these more
sophisticated phenomena in such a way
that they can be added to the model.
Traditional simulation typically
starts with an empty process.
If you are interested
in the transient behavior, so
what will happen tomorrow or what will
happen in a week, then it's very important
to also incorporate the initial state,
the current state into the model.
All of these things helped making
simulation more applicable and
more realistic.
What this diagram also shows is that
it provides very interesting means to
view a reality and
simulation in exactly the same way.
So simulation models can generate
event logs which are very
similar to the event logs that are
generated by the real information system.
And this really helps us
to do what if analysis and
compare reality to all kinds
of alternative scenarios.
In this lecture we have seen that
we can indeed combine the different
perspectives into one single
complete process model.
That discovering data, time,
resources all tied together using
the control-flow backbone.
Such complete models can be used for
simulation studies, but they
can also be used for operational support,
as we will see in a later lecture.
If you would like to read more
about these models that cover
different perspectives, please take
a look at the end of chapter eight,
which is describing the interrelationship
between all the different perspectives.
Thank you for watching,
and hope to see you soon.
[MUSIC]