[MUSIC]
Glad to see you again.
Until now,
we have been focusing on one process at
a time without comparing process variants,
organizations, or groups of cases.
Today we introduce process
cubes as a means to
support more systematic forms
of comparative process mining.
I'm sure that as a child
you have played this game.
You will compare two pictures and you need
to find the ten differences between them.
For example, you can see that
the cookie on one side is half eaten,
whereas on the other side, it is not.
If you are interested in comparing
different departments in a hospital.
If you are interested
in comparing different
locations of a car rental agency.
You would like to compare
different processes.
If you put these process
models on top of each other,
you can see where the differences are.
But if you look at processes,
it is not that simple.
We would like to find what
are differences in performance,
what are differences in conformance,
and how can they be explained.
To do this in a systematic manner
we use so called process cubes.
So, process cubes contain all event
data in a particular situation,
but the event data is organized
along a number of dimensions.
For example, time, department, in which
department does the event take place.
At which location.
What is the amount involved in
the case the event belongs to?
What is the gender of the student
studying a particular course?
What is the priority of a customer order?
Is the case compliant, or not?
All of these characteristics of events and
cases can be used to build
a multi-dimensional cube.
This cube helps us to compare event data
and processes along different dimensions,
in order to compare
different process variance,
different departments,
different types of customers.
So let's take a step back.
If we take a classical
data mining problem,
we start with data that looks like this.
And so we have a table
consisting of different rows.
The rows correspond to instances.
The columns correspond to variables.
We can look at predictor variables.
And if we do supervised learning, we
also need to select a response variable.
And given the same set of data,
we can one time select one
variable as a response variable.
For other types of analysis,
we will select another variable
as a response variable.
In the case of process mining,
it is very similar.
Again, we have input, but
now the input are events.
And events have very specific
characteristics different from
the input that we take for
a general data mining problem.
We need to select one of these columns,
one of these attributes,
as representing the case.
But that's not all,
we need to decide what is the activity.
We need to decide what
is the time attribute,
because we need to be able to
order events within a case.
We can also have optional attributes
like the resource executing
the corresponding activity.
There may be transactional information,
start and complete.
And there may be all kinds of other
attributes associated with an event or
the corresponding case.
So we have multiple dimensions,
and given one set of data,
we can do this type of mapping onto
process minings concepts multiple times.
For example, if you load a CSV file,
so a comma separated value file,
into Disco, when loading, you need
to decide what all the columns mean.
What is the column that
represents the case ID?
represents activity?
Multiple mappings are possible.
Depending on the type of analysis
that you would like to do,
you choose a different mapping.
Also, you often filter event
data in such a way that
you are able to compare different groups
of cases, or different group of events.
In a process cube, you try to do this
in a more systematic manner rather than
making ad hoc decisions
whenever we reload event data.
So if we group events in a so called
process cube then it will look like this.
So, this is a cube consisting
of three dimensions.
In general, if we look at process cubes,
we may have dozens of
different dimensions.
If you look at the car
rental agency like Hertz,
it has thousands of offices
all over the world.
Offices in Amsterdam, offices in Eindhoven,
offices in Paris, and
all kinds of other locations.
We have different types of customers.
There are gold customers,
silver customers, normal customers.
Also we can look at the process
at different points in time.
So we can look at
the events in January and
compare these events
with events in February.
And for each of the cells in
this multi-dimensional cube,
we can automatically construct
models using the techniques that we
have seen in earlier lectures.
And then it becomes very
interesting to compare these.
Did the process change,
moving from January to February?
Is the process for gold customers
different than the process for
silver customers?
Does the location in Amsterdam work
different than the location in Eindhoven.
Using comparative process mining,
you can answer such questions.
Let's take a look at another example.
In the Netherlands,
there are approximately 400
different municipalities, and
in each of these municipalities,
you can request a building permit.
Building permits may relate to very
large construction activities or
very small construction activities.
There are different municipalities.
There are also different periods.
And again, it is very interesting
to compare the process within one
municipality and
compare that to another one.
And to see what
are the typical differences.
Also we would like to
see changes over time.
This is often referred
to as concept drift.
You would like to understand
why did the process change at
a particular point in time.
Last example of a process cube.
Here, we look at student data.
Students are studying,
they generate all kinds of events.
For example, they make assignments,
they may make homework.
They take a final exam.
They may have different overall marks,
here from one to ten.
We can compare students that
studied the course in 2012 with
students that study a course in 2013.
And again it is very interesting to
compare all of these different processes.
So the basic idea of a process
cube is very simple.
We have this multi-dimensional data and
using slicing and dicing, drilling down,
drilling up, we can select, cells, and
these cells will correspond to events.
We can materialize these cells,
in other words,
we convert them to an ordinary event log,
and then we can do all kinds of analysis.
So we can do this for every cell,
we can focus on particular dimensions,
we can split cells,
we can group cells together.
So this is a very flexible way of
interacting with the event data.
At any point in time we can take
an array of cells and compare them.
We can look at the process models.
We can look at the dotted charts.
Let's take a look at a concrete example.
So, what you see here is a dotted chart
of students studying a particular
course in Eindhoven.
What you see is that every
row corresponds to a student.
Every dot corresponds to
some action of the student.
And you should know that in this course
students can watch video lectures.
So it is expected that students
over time will look at
lectures where whenever they
are ready to study a particular week.
The red dots in this diagram
correspond to exams.
So you can see that they
form straight lines.
These are the points in time
where students can take an exam.
You can see that,
often students fail an exam and
have to redo it at a later point in time.
Let's now zoom in into a particular
instance of this course running in 2011.
So we now zoom in into this data.
And when we zoom into this data,
we could compare the process, for
example, for
male students versus female students.
We could also look at
the study behavior and
try to compare the difference between
Dutch students and foreign students.
We can also compare the difference
between the behavior of students that
in the end pass the course, and the
students that in the end fail the course.
So if we take the last example, we can
automatically generate a process model for
the students that have passed, and
we can automatically generate a process
model for the students that have failed.
What you can see in this d,
this diagram is that these
processes look very different.
It's not important that you can
read the labels, but let me, for
example, explain one of
the characteristic differences.
So the students that pass, they typically,
the first event is typically
follow the lecture of week one.
If you look at the students that fail,
then the typical first activity
that they execute is make the exam.
So, before watching any of the lectures,
they try to make the exam and then fail.
We can also do conformance
checking of these two
sets of students with respect
to an ideal study model,
that would describe the ideal behavior
of a student following such a course.
What you then see is that
the conformance level of students that
are passing is much higher than
the conformance level of the students
that in the end fail the course.
So this is a nice illustration of
comparative process mining, and
you can quickly get to these types of
results by using the process cube notion.
So, using process cubes, we are able to
play with multi-dimensional event data.
And for people that have
a background in data warehouses or
in OLAP technologies, they will see
that certain things are very similar.
However, there is one
important difference.
If you look at data warehouses and
OLAP type of technologies.
Typically, the goal is to aggregate
things as fast as possible,
to come to clear-cut results.
This typically jeopardizes doing
process mining because the actual
events are being lost.
So if you use a process cube,
you're typically using data which is
at a lower level, let's say more raw,
than the typical information that
you will find in a data warehouse.
So we have been looking at event data
using a multidimensional process cube.
And we do this to be able to compare
different groups of customers,
different groups of patients,
different offices of the same company.
And this provides very
valuable information.
If would like
to learn more about this,
you will not find much about
process cubes in the book.
But you can read this article
that you see on the slide to
get more information about this approach
to look at comparative process mining.
Thank you for watching this lecture.
See you next time.
[MUSIC]