[MUSIC]
Welcome to this lecture of the course on
Process Mining: Data Science in Action.
Today we will focus on learning
organizational entities.
Using the resource activity matrix,
we can automatically learn roles and
extend the process model
with this information.
In the previous lecture,
we learned how to create a social network
by extracting information
from the event log.
We saw that it is possible to discover
relationships between people.
When do people work together?
How is work handed over from
one person to another person?
In this lecture, we will look at
analyzing event logs to automatically
infer role information and
add that to the process model.
In the last lecture we saw how to create
a so-called resource-activity matrix.
So we extract events and
we simply count the number of times
that a resource is executing a particular
activity and we normalize that per case.
So for example, Pete, on average,
executed a 0.3 times.
If we look at such a matrix, then the
question is, which resources are similar?
So please take a look at this example, and
try to discover yourself,
what are the underlying roles?
The answer to this
question is very simple.
In this particular example it is
very clear that Pete, Mike and
Ellen are very similar in terms of
the set of activities that they
are executing and how frequent they
are executing these activities.
Sue and Sean are the only people,
for example, executing activity b.
Sara is the only person executing e and f.
And so here it very clear.
But in general it is not that clear.
We can view every resource as a vector,
describing how often each
activity is executed per case.
And here you see, for example, the vectors
corresponding to Pete, Mike and Sara.
We can compute distances on these
vectors using classical notions like
the Euclidian distance,
Manhattan distance and all kinds of other
measures of deciding how far
apart different resources are.
And this information can be
used to infer a social network.
And in this social network,
we expect Pete and
Mike to be very close to each other
because their distances are very small.
Sara, on the other hand,
is quite different in terms of
the activities that she's executing,
than Pete and Mike.
So if we create a social network
based on this information,
we would get something like this.
Note that similarity is
the inverse of distance.
And so people that are at a short
distance are very similar so
are strongly related
in the social network.
Resources that execute similar
collections of activities are related.
For example,
here we can see that Sara is quite unique,
that is why she is not connected
to any of the other resources.
Note that we have removed
all the self-loops because,
of course,
every resource is very similar to itself.
And so that's why you don't
see any self-loops here.
Looking at similarity between
different resources to
identify roles in a process model
is very much related to clustering.
And in the first week we saw
techniques like k-means clustering.
How we can group things together
based on the vector representation.
So we can use that in
the context of process mining.
There are two typical uses.
One use is that we would like to
group cases which are very similar.
And then, per group of similar cases,
we can infer a process model.
So, if in this diagram all
the dots correspond to cases,
then we would find four groups of cases,
in other words we would find four
variants of the same process.
And the process model for each of
these variants is simpler than if we
would try to construct one overall
model for all the different groups.
In this lecture,
we focus on the grouping of resources.
So now all the dots are resources.
We look at their distances and
try to group them together.
Once we find a group of resources
we can attach a role to it and
use this to extend,
to enrich the process model.
Here you see a real-life examples.
The numbers that you see indicate how
frequent a particular user is
executing a particular activity.
This is taken from real life data.
And in this example you can see that
it is quite easy to find cliques,
clusters of people that
have a very similar
profile when we look at which activities
are being executed and how frequent.
So this result was obtained by ProM.
So using ProM, we can infer,
automatically roles.
Then the question is, if we have
identified these groups, these sets of
people having a similar work profile,
how can we add that to the model?
Well, that is very simple.
In the model we can simply
associate activities to roles.
So in this example we have three roles,
manager,
expert and the other three resources.
And we can relate these roles
to the process model and
we can relate the roles to
the individual worker in this case.
This view is a bit simplified because,
of course, roles can overlap.
One person may be able to
perform multiple roles and then this
picture will become a bit more involved,
but the basic idea is very simple.
Learning role information
is just a starting point.
And so we may be interested
in very different questions, but
also related to the behavior of
resources in the context of a process.
So when are resources available?
Do they work at particular
times during the week?
Are they shared among different processes?
When do resources collaborate well?
Are certain resources better to perform
specific activities than others?
We would like to learn such information
from event logs, and we can.
For example, a rather specific question
is investigating the relationship
between the work load of people and
how efficient, how fast they work.
And the so-called Yerkes-Dodson law
of arousal predicts that if people
get more work, that they start working
more efficient until a certain point,
after which performance will break down,
as you can see in this diagram.
If you are applying process
mining on real-life logs,
you are able to see these phenomena,
and you can learn from them.
They will tell you how to better run
a particular process or company.
So we need process models that
incorporate different perspectives.
In this lecture we focused on the
relationship between people and processes.
People have roles, are
member of particular departments and
we need to look at the relationship
between these two.
If you would like to
learn more about this,
you can read all about it in chapter 8.
Thank you for watching this lecture.
See you next time.
[MUSIC]