[MUSIC]
Welcome to this lecture.
In the last lecture, we showed that
the combination of process mining and
data mining can be used to learn
more about decision points.
The information can be used to
enrich the process model, and
serve as a starting point for
all kinds of process improvements.
So the focus of the last lecture
was on mining decision points.
We have one response variable.
Namely the activity that is being chosen
and we would like to understand this
response variable in terms of predictor
variables, like which was the person that
executed the last activity or what is the
type of customer that is being processed?
So this is just a starting point for
all kinds of
analysis where we combine data mining
together with process mining.
So today's focus is on
discovering the guards.
So taking the output
of a decision tree and
translating it to a data-aware Petri net,
so a process model extended with data.
So very concretely, if we take a look
at this example where there is a choice
between b and c, we would like
to create guards conditions for
b and c describing which cases,
under which circumstances we do b,
and under which circumstances we do c.
So how does it work?
If we focus on the choice between b and
c, following a,
we can take as response variable,
whether b or c is done.
And as predictor variables,
we can, for example,
look at the attributes of the event
corresponding to activity a.
We could also take other predictor
variables like the weather or
how busy things are.
But here we focus on the attributes
of the preceding event.
So here you see a table with data
describing events executing for
different cases.
So if we look at this table, we only
have to focus on activities a, b, and c.
We only have to look at
whether b of c is being executed.
We do not need to look at
the attributes associated to it.
With respect to a,
we need to look at the variables,
the attributes corresponding
to this a event.
We can combine such
information as is shown here.
So, for example for
case 1 John executed activity a, and
then this was followed by activity b.
So we can take this information and
convert it into
a new table that we can use
for the decision tree learning.
So here, if we take a look at the first
row, it corresponds to the choice for
activity b, which was following
activity a, which was executed by John,
done for a silver customer and
corresponding to an amount of 500 Euros.
So this is how we create
a decision tree learning problem.
If we do this, then using
the techniques that we saw in week 1,
we can create a decision tree.
So, for example, here we decided to
split on the attribute customer.
And we get a decision tree which
is classifying instances based
on whether they are silver customers or
gold customers.
And it turns out that silver and
gold customers typically have
different characteristics
when it comes to this choice.
We can encode the information that we see
in the decision tree in the process model.
And the process model now very clearly
shows that for silver customers, we do b.
For gold customers, we execute c.
So the result of doing this, and
if we do that for every choice,
is a data-
process model, where
we combine control flow with data flow.
So let's take a look
at another example and
see whether you understand these things.
So look at the second decision
point in the same process.
Take a look at the decision tree
which was discovered based on
a set of predicted valuables.
And convert this decision tree into
guards for the second decision point.
This slide shows the answer.
So what you see is that we add
conditions to all the different
transitions involved in
this particular choice.
And so we can see that there
are three classes, pay, reject, or
reinitiate the request.
And these correspond to different
leaves of this decision tree.
And if you follow the paths
in the decision tree and
convert them to logical expressions,
you will see that this is the case.
Note that there is at any point in time,
just one of the guards evaluates to true.
It cannot be that multiple
guards evaluate to true.
However if we look at the decision tree,
we can see that
there are certain leaves where we
are more certain about than other leaves.
So the
leaves that are indicated in red,
they are classified
according to a certain class.
But if you look at the underlying data
there is not consensus about these things.
And not enough information
gain could be achieved.
If we have such uncertainty, we can
also add that uncertainty to the model,
by making non-deterministic decisions.
So decisions where multiple transitions
are enabled and we can pick one of them.
So if we take a look at
this particular example.
All the leaves that correspond to red,
lead to the situation where all tree
transitions are enabled at the same
time but only one of them is chosen.
And so if you look at the guards,
you will see that they are now weaker and
therefore they are overlapping.
It can be the case that for some
cases, all tree guards evaluate to true.
We look at the decision tree and
the data underneath the decision tree,
we can also see that there is,
often no consensus.
And there are certain probabilities
associated to the leaves that are shown.
So we can encode also
this into the process model.
So then we get a process model that
depending on data attributes, assigns
certain probabilities to transitions,
and that is illustrated in this diagram.
It's a bit dense so if we zoom in and
we look at the guards corresponding
to the choice to pay the request.
Then you can see that the guard is
following the decision tree and
then looking at
the different probabilities.
So for example,
if examination is not okay,
then we can look at the decision
tree at the underlying data, and
then we can see that in one of the 30
cases, where examination was no okay.
Actually a payment took place, and
we can add this as a probability
to the process model.
We can see a combination of
probabilistic elements and
of using the data of the cases
associated to them.
The models that we learn
may sometimes look
a bit strange with very strange guards.
And therefore it's very important to
understand that the models that we
are discovering are descriptive.
They are describing what happened.
They're not describing what should happen.
If you have models that are describing
what should have happened,
we are looking at prescriptive models.
This is very important
to see this difference.
Both descriptive and
prescriptive models can be used for
conformance checking as
we have seen before.
And everything that was discussed in
the context of conformance checking can
also be applied to Petri net's bit data.
And so
if you take a look at this Petri net,
with these guards,
we can replay the event log and
we can detect where there are deviations
between reality and the model.
All of the things that we have discussed
so far are also supported by ProM.
For example here you see a screen shot
of ProM where we take an event log and
we take a control flow model,
not holding any information about data and
we combine them to discover
a data-aware Petri net.
So this is the result of applying
the plug-in on this event log and
this classical Petri net model.
And we get a Petri net extended with time.
So the two decision points
are highlighted here.
And if we zoom in,
we can see that there are two
variables that are influencing
the decisions that we see here.
The dashed lines correspond to writes and
reads, and the transitions
that are highlighted in red or have a red
name, they have guards associated to them.
So let's take a look at these guards.
If you look at the top guard,
you can see that we invite reviewers,
additional reviewers, if there are two or
less accepts or
there are two or less rejects.
If there are three or
more accepts or there are three or
more rejects,
we make the decision to accept or reject.
That is reflected by these guards.
We can also the second decision
point where the actual decision is
made to accept or reject.
We take one of the two paths and
then go to the end.
We can also use conformance
checking in conjunction with
these data-aware Petri nets.
So we take an event log and
a data-aware Petri net, and
we can do conformance checking and we can
show where the deviations take place.
And so here you can see
data-aware alignments also taking
into account possible
problems related to data.
So, in this lecture,
we have seen that we can combine data and
processes in a very natural way.
In that way, we can also clearly see that
there is a very nice interaction and
integration possible between data
mining and process mining, and
in the next couple of lectures,
we will see more examples of that.
If you would like to read more
about discovering guards and
the combination of data mining and
process mining, please read chapter 8.
Thank you for watching,
and hope to see you soon.
[MUSIC]