[MUSIC]
Welcome to this lecture of the course on
Process Mining: Data science in Action.
Process models, handmade or discovered,
may have many decision points.
For example, XOR splits.
In this lecture, we will show that by
replaying the event log on the model,
we can analyze these choices,
thereby exploiting the data
attributes in the event log.
This is a diagram that we have
seen several times before.
In earlier lectures, we focused on
discovery and conformance checking.
In the next couple of lectures,
we will look at the bottom arrow,
called enhancement.
So we want to improve
a model based on event data.
So, what types of enhancement are there?
The first type of
enhancement is extension.
So we take event data and add additional
elements to the process model.
We can also use event data
to repair an existing model.
Both extension and repair have in
common that we produce a new model,
which is either better or extended,
adding additional perspectives.
This is different from conformance
checking, where we were
generating diagnostics based on the fit
between the reality and the model.
In this lecture,
we will focus on extension.
There are different types of extensions.
We can extend the model with guards and
data related aspects.
We can extend the model with time related
aspects, with resource related aspects.
But the focus of today is on data.
We would like to add a data
perspective to process models.
For that,
we will focus on decision points.
In process models, there are many points
at which cases can go left or right.
And we would like to
understand these choices,
these decisions in such a process.
What do we need to do this?
First of all,
we need to have an event log.
And we need to have a process model.
The process model may have been
discovered, or made by hand.
And what is then very important is that,
through the notion of alignments,
we are able to relate the traces
that we saw in reality,
which are stored in the event log,
we can replay them on top of the model.
So every trace, seen in reality,
can be related to a path in the model.
So we need to match the names in
the event log and in the model.
This is a figure that we have seen
before showing the essence of alignment.
So, even if things do not fit perfectly
and we have move on model or
move on log type of problems, we can
still squeeze reality in the model and
then use this as a starting point for
analysis.
So in the remainder of this lecture,
I will not worry about
nonconformance because that has been taken
care of by true denotion of alignment.
So, after we have aligned
reality with a model,
we would like to understand why particular
choices are being made in a process model.
For example, we can accept a claim or
reject a claim.
This is a choice between two activities,
which cases are accepted,
which cases are rejected.
So this is an XOR split.
We choose one of the two
possible activities.
We also have the notion of OR splits.
Here, we have multiple activities, but
we sometimes may pick multiple
activities from the set of alternatives.
So, for example, in this case,
we can book a flight.
And we can book a hotel at the same time,
but we can also just book a flight.
That's why this is an OR split.
So we would also like to discover
these types of constructs.
Let's make it more concrete through a,
a very small example.
Suppose that we have so-called red cases.
These are cases that have
particular properties.
And assume that they always take
the path where they do A and
then B and C in some order, and finally D.
So E is not executed for the red cases.
On the other hand,
we also have blue cases.
And these blue cases,
they follow a different path.
So instead of doing B and
C, E is executed.
If we would now like to capture
information about red and
blue cases in a single process model,
we need to have a notion of guards.
So, here you see the process
model extended with guards.
And they are telling which
are the paths that red cases take.
And which are the paths
that blue cases take.
So, this is what we would like to discover
once we have a control flow model and
we have event data.
So what we are looking for
is learning more about decision points.
So in this Petri net model we see
that there are two decision points.
So in a Petri net in general,
places with multiple output
arcs model choices, decisions.
If we look at a BPMN diagram,
we have dedicated constructs
to model such choices.
In BPMN we have so-called XOR-split
gateways, OR-split gateways, and we can
also have the notion of a deferred choice
having an event-based XOR-split gateway.
So,these model decision points.
But we would not just like to see the
control flow, we would like to understand.
What are the cases that go left?
What are the cases that go right?
So decision point
analysis is an example of
a type of analysis where we need to
combine data mining and process mining.
And this combination provides
many powerful possibilities,
as we will see in this lecture,
and also in future lectures.
So, here,
we are using decision tree analysis,
as we have seen it in the first week.
We are looking at classifying cases
based on predictor variables.
So, in this particular example,
there is one response variable,
the variable that we are interested in,
will people claim or not.
And we would like to understand it
in terms of predictor variables,
in this case, the gender of the customer,
the age of the customer,
what kind of car the customer driving,
is driving, etc.
So we would like to explain
the response variable in terms of
relevant predictor variables.
We've seen how this works in week one.
And now we would like to apply
this to decision point analysis.
So the output of decision tree
learning is a decision tree.
Here you see one of the decision trees
that we discussed in the first week.
It is showing that female drivers
typically don't claim insurance.
Male Alfa Romeo drivers,
they claim insurance.
You can follow that by taking
the path from the root node to
the corresponding leaf node.
Male Volvo drivers younger
than 25 also claim insurance.
So this provides
information about choices.
And we can apply this in
the context of process models.
So what will it look like in the process
model, we will have a choice.
For example, the choice between claiming
insurance and not claiming insurance.
And then we could learn a guard for
example given a certain gender and
a certain type of car that people drive,
whether people claim insurance or not.
So we would like to create classification
problems based on decision points.
So let's focus on decision point one here,
where we are choosing between b and c.
So the response variable is whether
b is chosen or c is chosen.
And the predictor variables
are all the things that we know,
that are there in
the context of this choice.
So, very concretely, activity a was
executed before the choice to do b or c.
So the choice may depend, for example,
on which person executed activity a.
So that's an example of
a predictor variable.
But it could also be
the type of the customer,
the age of the customer, etcetera.
So, based on all
these times that the choice is being made,
we create instances that look like this,
having a set of predictor variables and
one response variable.
And that naturally defines
a decision tree problem.
So let's take a look at
some more examples.
So here we would like to understand what
is influencing the choice between y and z.
Here we have the corresponding data.
And if we look at this data, one could
come to the conclusion that these
are the guards that are explaining
the factors influencing this choice.
So, customers that are gold customers and
that claim an amount less
than 500 Euros always take y.
The other customers take z.
So if you look at the concrete example,
here we have our silver
customers from the Southern region
claiming an amount of more than 500.
And for this customer,
z was being executed, and
this is consistent with the guards
that we have discovered here.
Here we see this in terms of a Petri net.
We can have it in terms of any
other process model notation.
For example, here we see
a BPMN XOR-split gateway which is
expressing exactly the same
type of information.
In a BPMN model, but
in many other modelling notations we
also have OR-splits, inclusive OR-splits.
Here in this example, we can take just y,
just z, but we can also take both.
So this is a different type of
decision tree learning problem, but
it can be solved in exactly the same way.
So here we could learn these two guards.
And if you closely look at these guards,
you can see that they are overlapping.
So there are certain circumstances
where we will both take y and z.
So again,
we can look at a concrete example.
A silver customer from region west
claiming an amount less than 500 Euros.
For this particular customer,
y and z were being executed.
And if we look at
the corresponding BPMN fragment,
we can see that this consistent with
the guards that we have learned.
So, this what we would like to do.
So the response variable is
the decision that we are taking.
Do we take activity f or
some other activity?
We can look at the decision point,
and reasoning from the decision point
just before the choice is being made,
we can look at what are the variables
influencing this decision?
The so-called predictor variables.
It can be properties of the case itself.
So case variables are variables that
do not depend on a particular event.
They do not change over
the lifetime of a case.
So for example, a customer is a gold
customer from beginning to end.
We may also use attributes of the last
event executed before the decision.
In this case, e was the last event
before we had to make the decision.
We can look at the attributes
of this event.
Which person executed e, and
what kind of data was associated to e.
Rather than just looking
at the last event,
we can look at all the events executed
before the decision had to be made.
And this can serve as input to
the the decision tree learning problem.
In fact, we can also take all the events
also looking at things in the future.
For example,
we may want to relate a decision in
the middle to the process to
an outcome later in the process.
For example, will the case be too late?
Will the case be rejected,
and things like that.
The examples that I gave so
far are information predictor
variables associated to
a particular process instance.
But the context may be much broader.
For example, we can look at
the number of cases that are running,
and see whether this is
influencing a particular decision.
For example, if it is very busy,
then we typically skip an activity.
We can also look at the work
load of a resource,
how many resources are available.
In fact, we can even look at
the day of the week or the weather.
These may be factors
influencing the decision.
So we can all add them
as predictor variables.
However, there is one problem.
One needs to be very careful with this,
because there is the so-called
curse of dimensionality.
This means that the more
variables that you add,
the more possible combinations
of all these variables you get,
the fewer observations you have
per combination of variables.
So, the data gets extremely sparse and
we get the danger of overfitting.
So you carefully need to think about
what are the variables that one would
like to include.
In all the examples so far,
a decision point was defined as deciding
what is going to be the next activity.
And it's a very important problem
that needs to be addressed and
that needs to be understood well.
However, if you understand this,
the applicability is much broader.
Rather than having as a response
variable the next activity,
we can also take as a response
variable the remaining flow time,
the service level, costs,
risks, fraud, incidents, etc.
So for example, in a hospital,
you would be interested to see whether
deviations of the process lead
to incidents or higher costs.
Using exactly the same principles as
decision point analysis, you can also
understand these types of phenomena by
using exactly the same type of techniques.
In fact, in a later lecture,
we will also look into the future.
You can use these models
to make predictions, and
that is what we will discuss when
we talk about operational support.
If you would like to learn more
about decision point analysis,
please start reading in chapter 8.
Thank you for watching this lecture.
See you next time.
[MUSIC]