[MUSIC]
Welcome to this lecture.
Today I will provide a brief outlook
on the last two weeks of this course.
In the last four weeks we
have focused on control flow.
First we looked at process discovery.
Finding the ordering of activities.
And we use the metaphor of discovering
a desire line to see what the process of
discovery is actually all about.
In the last week we focused very
much on conformance checking.
We were comparing modeled and
observed behavior.
Thereby diagnosing
the deviations that took place.
Replaying an event log on
a control flow model allows us to
breath life into models that
are otherwise completely static.
You can see a nice example here of
breathing life into a static model.
And for that, event data, is crucial.
As we have seen before,
event data contains much more information.
For example,
if you look at the animation next to me,
this is only possible because we
have timestamps in event logs.
But in event logs we also have
information about resources.
We have information about.
The properties of customers, we have all
kind of other data attributes that we can use.
In the last two weeks we will focus on
these other perspectives, we will look
at new process mining tasks related
to these additional perspectives and
overall we will focus more on
the practical side of process mining.
Also the nature of this
course will change markedly.
Lectures will be shorter and
less technical.
And this is done to give you all the time
to do experiments using data and
the tools that are provided.
Please be aware of the fact that there
are lots and lots of event logs available,
and there is nothing stopping you from
actually starting analyzing event logs.
As a starting point,
you can go to processmining.org.
So this slide shows the focus so far.
We have been looking at discovery and
conformance checking.
For discovery we start from a log and
create a model.
For conformance checking we take a log and
a model.
And we provide diagnostics and
quantify differences between modeled and
observed behavior.
In all of these things we have been
focusing on control flow only.
But this is only part of the story.
For example, if you look at this matrix,
you can see the bigger picture.
Next to discovery and conformance
checking we also have enhancement.
So we take a log and
an initial model and we repair or
enrich the model with
additional information.
For example we can use conformance
checking to change the model in
such a way that it better fit reality.
Or we can exploit the time stamps to
extend the model with stochastic or
performance information.
To do these things we often
not just look at control flow,
but also include time, resources and data.
And here we often use techniques that,
are adopted from other areas.
Like data mining, for example we will
talk about decision mining in
processes and for that we will be using
standard data mining techniques that we
have seen in the first week.
We will analyze resource behavior for
that, we will look at techniques
related to social network analysis.
We often look at performance of processes.
Thereby we can relate techniques
from operations research like for
example, simulation or queuing
networks to process mining techniques.
So, what are typical topics that we
will talk about in the next two weeks?
We will talk about mining decision points,
understanding why
certain cases take a particular route,
other cases take another route.
We will mine for bottlenecks.
Where are the bottlenecks?
Why are they there?
We will mine social networks.
In general we will focus
on the resource behavior.
For example which people
are working together?
When are people most effective?
Do people start working faster
if they have more work?
We will also look at comparing processes.
For example,
what is the difference of the process for
gold customer, versus the process for
silver customers?
What are differences between the study
behavior of students that pass and
the study behavior of
students that fail a course?
For this,
we use comparative process mining.
We will look at operational support.
Everything we have done so
far was done offline.
For operational support, we go to
an online setting where we look at
techniques like detecting that things
go wrong, that there are deviations.
Not after the fact, but at a point in
time when these deviations happen.
We will look at predictions.
For example, what is the remaining
processing time of a particular case?
We will even look at
the recommendations where we
say based on historic information,
and information about
the current state of cases,
we recommend these are the best
activities to be executed.
Or that these are the best resources
to do a particular activity.
All these things lead to a more refined
process mining framework that will be
explained in detail.
We will also make a link
to other types of analysis.
Earlier I mentioned operations research.
For example,
we can use the discovered process models,
using process mining, to do simulation
experiments to do what if analysis.
We will look at the problem
of data extraction.
How can we convert data into event logs?
But we will also give guidelines for
logging.
If you are designing a new system, what
should you actually record to be able to
do process mining, and to,
to get the best analysis answers possible?
We will also talk about conducting
a process mining project.
What are the phases?
What are the
points that you should be aware of?
In the context of this, we will see
that there is a wide range of processes,
some processes we refer
to lasagna processes.
Structured processes,
where it is not that interesting to
do process discovery because we already
know what the process looks like.
But where we are very interested in
trying to see how we can improve it.
For example, through bottleneck analysis,
through understanding what are the best
resources at a particular point in time.
Well, at the other end of the spectrum
we will find spaghetti processes.
Processes that are very unstructured,
where it makes no sense to try to predict
what is going to happen tomorrow.
You first need to provide insights.
And process discovery itself
is already very valuable.
All of these things are related
to creating a toolbox for
the data scientist or
the process scientist of the future.
People need these types of instruments
to do analysis that really matters,
and that really helps organizations
to improve systems and processes.
As mentioned before,
the next two weeks will be very different.
They will be less technical.
The lectures will be shorter.
It will have a more applied flavor.
One of the reasons for having shorter
lectures is that we would like to
provide opportunities to actually use the,
the software.
Prom/Disco, and the data set, to get hands
on experience with the process mining.
Also, try to think beyond
the data sets that are provided.
If you go to processmining.org,
you can find many,
many data sets that you can use.
You can also look at,
process mining data used for competitions.
For example, the BPI challenges, where
you can apply process mining to real,
live, event logs.
You can also look at the many data
sets that are publicly available for
data mining.
Many of these data sets, one can see that
in some way, events are being described.
So you could convert them to event logs.
There is a, a large movement taking place
at this point in time, to make data open.
Many governments.
Are forced or
really want to provide data to the,
citizens, and that is creating new
possibilities for process mining.
Also, you can look at social media.
If you look at Twitter, Facebook, and
Google, they all provide open APIs.
So they allow you to extract event logs
from things that you find interesting.
These are the chapters that will be
covered in the next, couple of lectures.
And as I said before, the focus will now
be more on the practical side of things.
Thank you for watching this lecture.
Hope to see you soon.
[MUSIC]