[MUSIC]
Welcome to this lecture.
This short lecture presents the so
called refined process mining framework.
This framework aims to
provide an overview of
the different process mining activities.
This is a diagram that we have
seen several times before.
It is explaining the role of discovery,
conformance, and enhancement.
Today we will refine this framework
into a much more detailed framework.
Identifying ten different
process mining activities.
And, we will explain this more
complicated framework, step-by-step.
In the earlier lectures,
we focused on process discovery.
Only looking at control flow.
Then we looked at conformance checking.
And in the last couple of lectures
we have been extending this in
all kinds of directions.
We have been incorporating role
information about a resource involved in
a process.
We looked at decision point mining.
We looked at bottlenecks.
But this is just the tip of the iceberg.
There are many more process mining
techniques that one can use.
And there are much more
questions that one could ask.
For example, one can ask
questions related to performance.
If you are dealing with
terabytes of event data,
you need to distribute your
process mining activities.
Today's framework will
not focus in things like.
Distributed process mining.
But will look at the typical
activities that you may want to
do in the context of
a process mining project.
And for that we detail this
refined process mining framework.
Let's start with the top
of the refined framework.
You can see the word provenance here.
The word provenance refers to
the fact that event data that we
are collecting should be faithful.
It should describe what
has really happened.
Once we collect event data,
it should be safe.
Data should not just disappear,
preferably,
also not disappear selectively.
We should always be able to
reconstruct history based on
the event data that we have.
So this is something
that is very important.
So suppose now that we
have the event data,
then we can partition the event data.
Into pre mortem and
post mortem event data.
What does it mean?
If you look at post mortem event data,
we look at event data that refers to cases
that have already completely finished.
So these were cases that
were handled in the past.
We can no longer influence them.
If you look at pre mortem event data,
we refer to cases that are still running,
that are still alive.
And, if we look at these cases,
we may still want to influence them.
For example if we see a case and we can
we know that the case is running late.
We could for example try to involve
additional resources to make
sure that the case is handled in time.
So pre mortem event data refers to
cases that can still be influenced.
It's important to make this
distinction for
the rest of the framework.
Let's take a look at some examples.
So, here you can see three different
situations, students studying.
We can look at the sales process,
we can look at the hospital
with patient related data.
And if we look at post
mortem like questions,
we are interested in bottlenecks.
We are interested in seeing how we
could improve the process, not for
the case that is running now,
but for the process in general.
That's post-mortem data.
If we look at pre-mortem data,
we are particularly interested in
the cases that are running now,
and that can still be influenced.
So for example, if we see that a
particular student is likely to drop out,
we may still want to take some action.
Or if we see that students are not
engaged enough in a particular course,
we can take action.
We can also take action, for example,
if we look at a hospital and
we see certain non-conformance
of a particular patient.
That we want to take action to make
sure that no bigger problems will occur.
So pre mortem data refers to cases
that we can still influence.
At the bottom of the diagram of
the reference model we look at the models.
And the models may cover
multiple perspectives.
They typically always
cover control flow.
But with the control flow
backbone we may add data and
rules, information about resources,
about time, costs, etc.
At the bottom of the diagram you can also
see that we distinguish between the de
jure models and the de facto models.
Let's take a look at what that means.
The de facto model is descriptive,
the de facto model tries to
describe reality as it is.
It is not intended to
influence behavior or
to guide behavior but
just to describe what is happening.
When we do process discovery
we discover de facto models.
But we also have de jure models.
These models are typically normative.
They specify how things should be done or
handled.
For example if one is
using a workflow system or
a BPM system,
one is using normative models.
These models are driving the system to
force people to work in a particular way.
If we have models just on paper
they can still be normative.
However if they are not enforced
by a system people can choose to
deviate from them if they want.
So we have de facto and de jure models and
it's very important to see that our
roles may be completely different.
Based on the difference between
de jure and de facto models and
pre mortem and post mortem data
we can create this framework.
And this framework identifies ten
different activities by no means.
It is intended to be complete but
it gives a good feeling of the broadness
of the process mining spectrum.
Let's take a look at these
ten different activities.
The first group of activities
looks at process models as maps.
So the most typical example is discovery.
Control flow discovery or
discovery of other perspectives.
This is learning the model of
the process as it is really happening.
We can also combine an existing
model with event data, and
then extend or repair the model.
And models can also serve
a purpose just by themselves,
not directly connected to event data.
And so for example, the model that
was discovered at some point in time.
Can be used for
diagnosis purposes much later without
really looking at event data.
The activities in the middle,
they refer to auditing.
So here we are confronting
model with reality.
And we distinguish four
different activities.
The first activity is detect.
It is using pre mortem data.
So data related to cases
that are still running.
And they are compared
with the de jure models.
And each time there is a deviation
an alert is generated.
Note that we are now looking at
the online setting where want to
generate alert the moment
that thy take place.
A more common situation that we have
discussed many times in the past.
It's conformance checking,
simply called check here.
This is done in an offline setting,
so we look at the past, and
we compare event data
with the process model.
Detect and check, they have in common that
we compare event data with the model.
We can also compare two models.
For example, when we were discussing about
foot prints, we provided metrics for
comparing two different models.
This way we can again compare
the de jure with de facto model.
Or we can compare different
variants of the same process.
At the level of a model.
Last but not least,
we have the activity promote.
It means that we have elements of a de
facto model that we want to
transfer to a de jure model.
So if you look at model repair,
that would be something, typical activity
that you could see in this context.
The last category of activities
are related to navigation, supporting, and
guiding process execution.
First of all,
using a combination of event data, and
models, we may explore
the process at run time.
It's just like a query language.
We can try to understand what is
happening now and should we do something.
Then there is the notion of prediction.
If you have learned the model
based on historic information.
And you combine that with pre mortem data,
data about running cases in the current
state, you can make predictions.
And if you can make predictions you
can also recommend certain actions.
And so
using information from the past you can
recommend a particular activity,
or a particular resource.
To execute the next activity.
So, these examples,
these ten different activities showed that
the process mining spectrum
is actually quite broad.
Much broader than just process discovery.
We are now in Chapter nine.
Operational support so
the refined process mining
framework was an introduction to the more
online setting of process mining.
And the next lecture we'll
talk about this in detail.
Thank you for watching and
hope to see you soon.
[MUSIC]