[MUSIC]
Hi there.
I'm Anne Rozinat from Fluxicon, and
I would like to welcome you
to this process mining MOOC.
Process mining is a very
interesting topic.
Very relevant for today's organizations.
Based on just data you can
automatically discover processes.
And this can be done very fast and
very quickly and for
many different processes
in these organizations.
There are so many processes and
so much data is around.
Well, process mining is already picking
up in several companies nowadays,
and those companies who are using it,
they get lots of value out of it and
are expanding their usage.
But many more companies will start
using process mining in the future and
will become an indispensable tool for
process analysts, process managers, and
auditors, and, and
many other process roles.
So, it's not just a very interesting
topic that you chose, but
also a very relevant one.
And, there's no better person
to learn process mining from
than professor Bill Finoust, who is also
called the godfather of process mining.
Well, as for
us at Fluxicon, we caught the process
mining back more than ten years ago.
When we were still studying in Germany we
came across this topic and then we went to
Eindhoven to do PhD in the process mining
group of And this was a really great time.
Well, first of all,
lots of other colleagues also working
on different process mining topics, but
also we had the chance to work with
industry partners such as and Phillips.
And in those projects
what we learned first of
all is that the processes were
really much more complex.
And we had the chance to develop
our algorithms to meet those,
yeah, complex processes in the real world.
Back then most things were really
just working based on toy examples.
So for example, the fuzzy miner was one
of the first algorithms that, yeah,
really was able to deal with very
complex and heterogeneous processes.
So that was one thing.
But, at the same time, what we notice is
that people were always really amazed and
enthusiastic about what we could show
them when we took their data and
made their processes visible for them.
They couldn't believe
that that was possible.
So there was this huge gap between
what we were able to do, and
what they thought were possible, or what
they were doing in their everyday life.
So, for
us that was the trigger that we said,
well we have to do something with it.
And we started Fluxicon as
a company to make business, yeah,
process mining software for
business users.
and, yeah, with the goal to really
make this technology accessible to
businesses around the world.
And well, when we started out we
just started doing consulting for
Jake's with prom, and
the academic tool set.
yeah, under, under, under our arms,
which we knew very well because we
had developed large parts of it.
And we learned what kind
of questions people had and
what kind of problems they wanted
to solve with process mining.
And then, we started developing
our own software [COUGH] to,
to address those needs and
to kind of build the perfect tool for
those business users that
we met in those projects.
So, this is what Disco is about,
Disco stands for discovery.
And Disco it's on the market now for,
yeah, since 2012.
And [COUGH].
So, our prom is really a great academic
tool set, which makes it very easy for
our researchers develop,
to develop new algorithms.
For example, Disco's really meant for
a business professional,
who does not need to know anything about
how these algorithms works, work, and
how the technology looks
like under the hood.
We have hidden that away from them.
But we make it available for them, so
that based on their domain knowledge and
process knowledge, they can yeah,
use these results and
draw the right conclusions and
interpretations from it.
Now with Disco,
process mining becomes really easy.
You have an Excel sheet for
example, with some data, and
you can sim, simply import the CSV or
Excel sheet in a visual way,
map the different columns to
case ID activity name and
time stamp, and then once you import you
are directly taken into the process map.
You can interactively determine the level
of detail that you want to look at
the process map.
And then you can interactively very
easily answer different questions about
the process through filters.
For example, performance filter that
focuses on the long running cases,
taking longer than an expected time.
And focus in on those bottlenecks
that you can then find and
see where things are really
taking very long in the process.
Now, you can even animate that process in
a, in a very easy way, and this brings
the process to life, and helps a lot in
communicating the problems at hand and, so
that people can point their finger on
the place where the problem occurs, and
discuss why this is happening,
and what they can do about it.
Now [COUGH].
well, with as a participant of this MOOC,
we make Disco available for
you for the time of the MOOC
with a training license.
You can use this license to import
data sets up to 1 million records.
And this is enough to do
all the exercises, but
you can also import some of
your own data if you have any.
And in fact,
we would encourage you to do that.
Because there's no better way to learn
about process mining than to, yeah,
to play around with some
of your own data and
to get a good understanding of what it
can really do for your own business.
And yeah.
So we really hope this will spread the,
the, the knowledge about this
technology which still very few people
know about, that it even exists.
And yeah, I just want to mention also that
we have an academic initiative with close
to 200 universities all around the world
where we provide lecture materials and
also free academic licenses.
So you can take a look at our website
to find more about it as well.
Now I would like you to realize that
process mining is really a very special
yeah, data science technique or
data analytics technique because yeah.
Most of those other data
analytics techniques they make
assumptions about the process.
Or, if you think of, for example BI,
business intelligence technology, you
have to set up an implementation project.
And it's all very heavyweight.
With process mining you just need to
get some data and you can start mining.
It's very lightweight and very powerful.
But, what is especially
interesting about process mining,
is what it makes possible for
the business user.
So, let's take a look at this graph.
Well, the business users what they have
access to typically is, well first of all,
specific reports and dashboards that
are made specifically for them.
They're very accessible for them,
but it's also kind of limited,
because those reports they include exactly
that kind of information that was pre-pro,
programmed for them to contain.
Well, Excel, on the other hand is a very
popular tool among professionals
not without reason.
Excel is a very powerful tool, and
you can do lots of things with it.
And it's something that the,
the business user can use themselves.
On the other end of the spectrum, you
have those data science techniques that
everyone talks about today
in the big data craze.
And well, that's,
those techniques are very powerful but
at the same time you really need to be
an engineer or a specialist to use them.
Now process mining,
on the other hand, is particularly
interesting because it's very powerful.
It's much more powerful for
analyzing processes than Excel, because
processes consist of multiple steps, and
that's a thing that's very
difficult to do in Excel.
But it's still accessible for
the business user.
So the business user who has the knowledge
about their business process and
about the problems in the process,
they can use process mining yeah,
in their own hands to really yeah,
get great results based on that analysis.
And so,
if you think that process mining is
just a way to automate something
that was being done manually before.
Like previously we were modeling
processes, manually modeling them by hand,
now we can do it automatically
with process mining.
That falls way too short.
Process mining can do much more than that.
And in a way, you can compare it with
spreadsheets because when, before
spreadsheets were around, people had to do
everything manually using a calculator.
So if you wanted to do a projection or
some kind of forecast, you had to type it
in and you had to manually calculate it.
But once spreadsheets were around,
it's not just that the things that you
did manually before those could now,
now be automated, but
much more things could be done.
Many more things could be done.
And yeah, so
it gave you much more power to do
all kinds of things that nobody
thought about were possible before.
Process mining works in the same way for
processors.
And is as revolutionary as
spreadsheets for, for numbers.
So, for business professionals,
who have the knowledge to
draw the right interpretation and make the
right decisions based on those results,
process mining really brings
kind of special powers to them.
So we kind of, that's how we like
to see our, our Disco users also,
that we can now give them super powers for
their own processes.
Well I'm really glad you're
participating in this MOOC.
I would like to welcome you to
the process mining community and
I'm sure you will love this
topic as much as we do.
And happy mining.
[MUSIC]