[MUSIC]
Welcome to this course, process mining,
data science in action.
The goal of this short movie is to provide
you with some background information on
the instructors, the organizations,
organizing this course, and
some practical information.
TU/e is the university
organizing this MOOC.
TU/e is one of the leading technical
universities in Europe and
it has a rich history in engineering.
For example, in computer science Dyskra a
famous touring award winner, worked here.
He was, for example, the person that
invented the shortest path algorithm.
But there are not only
scientists in this region.
In the broader Eindhoven region,
which is called Brainport,
there are many high tech companies
like Phillips, ASML and many others.
So it's a vibrant region with many
organizations producing and using data.
That is the reason why this university
started the Data Science Center in 2013.
The Data Science Center
is a virtual organization
consisting of 25 research groups
covering all aspect of data science.
So in the yellow box you see
the disciplines that are involved
to produce data and
to handle large volumes of events.
In the red box you see all
kinds of disciplines related to
analysing event data.
And of course, process mining,
the topic of this course,
is a very important ingredient in this.
In the green box, you can see
the context part of data signs.
So in the end, we would like data
signs to be used in practice.
So we need to think about ethical
aspects and the business value of data.
Let's tell a bit about myself.
So my name is Will van der Aalst.
You can see here a picture of my favorite
hobby, walking and climbing in the Alps.
I'm 48 years old.
I, I'm married.
I have four children.
And if I'm not walking
in the mountains and
spending time with my family,
I'm having these roles.
So, I'm a professor at
the Technical University of Einthoven.
I also have part-time appointments
off at the other side of the world.
For example I am a joint professor at QUT,
that"s Queenswood University
of Technology in Brisbane, and
I am the Scientific Director of a lab in
Moscow at the High School of Economics.
I am also the scientific director of
the data science center at Intel.
So in the last 25 years,
I've been working on these topics.
So I started working more in the area of
modeling and using models toward analysis.
And in recent years, I've moved more
to data driven types of analysis,
like process mining,
an essential ingredient for data sites.
Now I would like to hand
over to Joos Buijs,
who will tell you much more about the
practical things, related to this course.
>> Thank you very much Will, so
my name is Indie Joos Buijs,
I did my master's here in Angova, and
I recently defended my PHD thesis on
process mining also here in Angova.
And currently I'm a postdoctoral
researcher in a group of So
a little bit about my hobbies
outside of work and so
I like to watch Pixar movies and
everything involved.
I like to visit theme parks and
one of my reasons,
most recent hobbies is playing with
my eight month old daughter and
together with my wife and my daughter
explore the world a little bit.
But this is not about me.
Let's talk about the course.
So in the next couple of slides I'll
explain a little bit more about
the details of the course.
You can also find this in the study
guide and in the grading policy.
This video is just a brief introduction,
more details are in these documents.
And if there are any, if there's any
inconsistency the documents prevail.
But this is just to get you into the into
the course and what you can expect.
So there are six weeks of video lectures.
Per weeks we have roughly eight
videos of eight to 15 minutes each.
the, several topics that we discuss.
So there's a brief introduction and
general data mining things.
Then we go into the models and
pros of discovery.
Then in week three you get little
bit of better understanding of
the different types of
process models there are.
This is followed in week four
by more discovery techniques and
also conformance checking techniques.
In week five we look at how you can enrich
the process models, and in week six
we discuss operational support and we
also conclude this lecture, this course.
So learning objectives.
After this course I hope you see how
process mining fits in the big scheme.
Of all the techniques like simulation,
machine learning machine learning and
data mining.
but, and also we hope that you see what
different aspects process mining entails.
So you can do process discovery,
conformance checking, and
in the end,
hopefully you can also actually do
a process mining project from beginning to
end, including data gathering and such.
In this course you can
get two certificates.
So the normal certificate you
get when you have 35 out of
50 points you can get with the week and
the final quiz.
So every week there will be a week quiz
where you can get five points four, and
there's a final quiz worth 20 points, and
if you get enough points on these quizzes,
you get the normal certificate.
If you would like to obtain
the certificate with distinction then do,
do these week of final quizzes.
But also do a Tool Quiz where you
experiment with the tools that we use.
And also you have to do a Peer Assignment
which, which I will explain later.
And, if you want to get
the Certificate with Distinction,
you have to earn at least
80 out of 100 points.
So, in more detail that's several quizzes.
So every week there's a week quiz
covering the topics of that week.
Here you can earn five points per quiz.
And a quiz contains of ten
multiple choice questions.
There's no timing, and you get two
attempts and the highest score counts.
At the end of this course
you have a final quiz.
This allows you to earn 20 points.
it, you get 20 multiple choice questions
and there's one timed attempt.
Then if you want to go to, for
the certificate with distinction you
have a tool quiz worth 10 points,
which is an untimed quiz of 20 questions.
Then next to this is a peer assignment.
You can earn 40 points.
It will start end of week three
early week four, and the goal is to
write a process mining report using one
of the data sets that we will provide.
We will also proved a report template
in Boleta and Word document.
And you can use this to analyze
the data and write your findings.
Then you have to submit it.
And then you have to also evaluate
three other reports using criteria that
we provide.
And in a similar way,
your report is evaluated by three
peers based on the same criteria.
For the peer assignment,
you can use these two tools.
So on the one hand we
have the ProM framework.
This is an academic tool, with many
plug-ins and model types supported.
It started here at this University, but
many researchers and practitioners from
around the globe have contributed to it.
And you can obtain it at
the processmining.org web site.
On the other end, you have Disco,
which is a commercial tool.
It's simple, fast and easy and
it mainly supports fuzzy models.
And in another video I'll
explain more about Disco, but
you can install it from fluxicon.com.
Next to this we have also a forum,
please use this to ask for
any help and
report issues that you have with tools.
So use this to discuss any things or
insights that you've gained
also with fellow students.
Even also use this to arrange meetups so
arrange a local meetup
where you'll meet with other students
to discuss things in person.
We will monitor this forum, so
we hope that you among yourself start
a discussion and answer the questions.
But three of our PhDs in this group and
myself will monitor this.
So Eduardo, Shengnan, and
Maikel will answer any questions
that are remain, that remain open.
And I will also have a look on the forum.
So please use the forum to
kind of meet each other.
The scores is mainly based on
the process mining book, so in,
at the end of each video, we'll, we'll
point out which chapter we were covered.
Some chapters will be provided to you for
free.
But you can buy the whole
book either physical or
digital, using a discount
kindly offered by Springer.
Only for
students participating in this MOOC.
Well that's it from the more
organizational side
I really encourage you
to watch all the videos,
learn all the tools that we have so
can analyze your own data.
But please be aware this is
only the tip of the iceberg.
For each technique that is discussed, we
did a lot of reasearch, and there's a lot
of mu, more detail available in scientific
papers that you can, find online.
So if you find something that you want to
learn more about outside of this book,
then please, look online, and there's much
more knowledge that we can share with you.
So, to conclude to this
introductionary lecture have a lot of
fun in the coming six weeks.
Watch the videos, make the quizzes.
Do the assignment.
And I hope to meet you
a little bit on the forum.
Have fun.
[MUSIC]