[MUSIC]
Glad to see you again.
After introducing decision trees as a tool
for classification, we now focus on
an unsupervised data mining technique,
uncovering patterns in data.
In this lecture we will learn about
frequent item sets and association rules.
These will help us to find expected and
unexpected patterns.
Here you, again see an overview of the
different data mining techniques that we
are considering in relation to the topic
of process mining that we will be
exploring later.
After talking about decision
trees in two lectures, we now
move to association rules, and this is
an unsupervised learning technique.
In other words, we do not have label data.
There's no response variable.
To explain the topic,
it is best to start with an example.
One of the earlier applications of
association rule mining revealed
that people buying beer
often also bought diapers.
So it's a rule, taking one set of items,
implying another set of items.
So this is one example
of an association rule.
Another association rule could be cheese
and ham and bread implies butter.
So, in other words,
customers that buy these three products,
typically also buy butter.
Or, people that buy oregano,
often also buy spaghetti and tomato sauce.
So, one set of items implies
another set of items.
So, all these rules have
the form of x implies y,
where both x and y are item sets.
Sets of items.
Before we talk about how
you can compute them,
let's first define some quality measures.
And we start by explaining
the notion of support.
The idea of support is to
take the number of items,
that covers both x and y and divided by
the total number of instances we have.
So we look at the number of
instances that has both x and y,
and we divide that by
the total number of instances.
It's also always best to explain
these concepts by looking at an example.
So here we see a table
that we have seen before.
People ordering cappuccinos americanos,
and muffins.
And we can take such an example set and
automatically learn association rules.
We could for example find the rule
that people that buy tea and
latte, typically also buy muffins.
Note that the frequency in
the table doesn't matter.
We just look, is an item present or not?
So we do not look at quantities,
just at presence.
So what is support, now, for
this particular example?
If we compute a support of the rule,
tea and latte implies muffin,
we compute the number of instances
of customers, that bought tea,
latte and muffins and divide that
by the total number of customers.
And if we have a higher value that is
better than the lower value because there
is more support.
The second quality metric is confidence.
So if we look at the confidence of a rule,
we count the number of instances
which covers both x and y,
and we divide that by the number
of instances covering just x.
So in terms of our example, if we would
like to know the confidence of the rule
tea and latte implies muffin we count
the number of customers that ordered tea,
latte and muffins and
we divide that by the number of
customers that just ordered tea and
latte and not necessarily muffins.
We get another between zero and one, and
it's clear that the higher the number,
the more confident we can be about
the accuracy of such a rule.
The third quality metric
is the most difficult one.
It's called lift.
So we look at a fraction of
customers that cover both x and
y, and we divide that by the fraction
of customers that covers x and
the fraction of customers that covers y.
So, in terms of our example, and
we can write this in the two
ways that are indicated here.
In terms of our examples
this corresponds to
taking the number of customers that
order tea, latte, and muffins and
multiply that by the total number of
customers and diving this by the number of
customers that order tea and latte and the
number of customers that order muffins.
If we then look at this fraction and
we get a value
that is bigger than 1 then x and
y are positively correlated.
They frequently happen together.
If they are independent,
so they happen independent of each other,
then lift will be close to one.
If it's lower than one, we get such a
number if they are negatively correlated.
So how can these three measures be used.
They can be used to filter rules a priori.
And so to avoid from
a computational point of view
that we need to look at too many
rules at the same time.
But they can also be used
if we have a large number of
rules to sort them based on
the criteria that we find important.
These things are very important
because typically there is
an explosion of association rules.
So it's very important to be able
to prune the set of rules and
to look at the most interesting ones.
Typically one is most interested in the
rules that have a support that is as high
as possible, a confidence close to one.
And a lift higher than one,
indicating a positive correlation.
For example, if we have a rule with
the confidence of, let's say, 0.1, it
is typically not a very interesting rule,
because the confidence is really low.
Let's make this clear using an example.
So, we take an artificial
set of customers,
100 customers that buy diapers and beer.
There is just one type of diapers, Pampers.
And there are two types of
beer Hoegaarden and Dommelsch.
And here you can see what
these 100 customers bought.
We can use such a data set to compute
the notions that we have seen before.
So let's take a look at four
hypothetical association rules.
For example, the rule, people that
buy Pampers also buy Dommelsch, or
people that buy Pampers
also buy Hoegaarden, etc.
So let's start with a question
looking at the first rule.
So if we look at the rule,
people that bought Pampers typically
also bought Dommelsch beer.
What is the support, the confidence and
the lift?
Please take some time to
compute these values.
Here you can see a computation
of these values.
So the support is 0.51 because
there are 51 customers that bought
both Pampers and Dommelsch, and we divide
that by the total number of customers.
The confidence, is equal to the number
of customers that bought Pampers and
Dommelsch, divided by the number
of customers that bought Pampers,
which is equal to 91.
So the confidence is 0.56.
If we apply the formula for lift, we find
that there is a positive correlation.
Because we get a value higher than 1, 1.1.
Let's now take a look at the other rules.
For example, the last rule.
People that buy Pampers and
Dommelschs typically also buy Hoegaarden.
What is the quality of these rules in
terms of support, confidence and lift?
Well we can do the same computation
as what we have done before.
It is put in the table here.
The first row corresponds to the to the
first rule that we have explored before.
If we look at this table then we see
that some values are positive and
other values are not so positive.
For example, the ones that are highlighted
now in red, correspond to low values.
So, the rule Pampers,
implies Hoegaarden, is a bad rule,
in terms of support and confidence,
and also in terms of lift.
And so only 1% of the customers
is supporting this rule.
The confidence is also very low.
So only in 1% of the cases
the rule actually holds.
And there are many people that buy
Pampers, but that do not buy Hoegaarden.
The negative, the lift is lower than one,
indicating a negative correlation.
So let's load this data
set into RapidMiner so
we can load it into the tool
in terms of a CSV file.
Load it in the repository and
then do the experiment.
So here you see a description of the data.
Indeed we are looking at
100 customers and
we are looking at three different items
that people can or did not buy.
This is the analysis workflow.
So, we start by loading the data,
then we do a data transformation.
So we convert the numbers to true,
false values.
Then we compute frequent item sets.
And finally, based on these frequent
item sets we compute association rules
that describe the rules
that we are interested in.
There are two important parameters here.
One parameter is the minimal support.
So if you look at an item set.
What is the minimal number that
this item set should appear in?
Confidence is related to the confidence
metric that we have explained before.
If we use these parameters that
were set in the previous slide,
then we only find one rule.
People that buy Dommelsch
also buy Pampers.
If we look at the support of
this rule as we have computed by
hand before the support is 0.51
which is bigger than the threshold.
If you look at the confidence of the rule,
it's 1 which is also bigger than
the threshold that we have set.
How to compute this, first of all
one could use a brute force approach
using these two parameters
that you see here.
There is minimum support level and
there is a minimum confidence level.
And we could first compute
all the rules and
then prune the rules based
on these two parameters.
So a brute force approach could work like
this, generate all frequent item sets,
that have a support that is bigger than
this minsup, constant that we have chosen.
We also look at item sets
containing two elements,
because we are interested
in association rules.
And then we partition these frequent
item sets into smaller, dejoined sets,
and compute the confidence of these.
And everything that meets the threshold
is then returned as a rule
that has been discovered.
If you apply this approach,
there are two problems.
There is a computational problem,
that there may be an exponential number
of item sets that one needs
to consider leading to all
kinds of performance problems.
Another, perhaps more serious problem,
is an interpretation problem.
If we find many rules and
we return many rules to the user,
then the user will be completely confused.
So, how to address this problem?
Well, there are several techniques to
address computation and interpretation
problems, and many of them are based on
the observation that you can see here.
If we have an item set X that is frequent,
then all subsets of that
item set are also frequent.
If we have an item set that is
not frequent, then all supersets
are also infrequent, and
we not need to consider them.
So this can help us to
prune the search space and
to return the rules that
are most interesting.
So it can be exploited to
improve efficiency and
only return the strongest rules.
Let's go back to the Italian restaurant
that we have described before.
Again, we take the data
set of 5,000 parties.
They can eat these dishes.
And the question is, what are products?
So, dishes and
drinks that are often being combined.
Well, if we load the file again in the
repository just as we have done before we
can now discard the class and,
so, we are using unlabeled data.
It's an unsupervised
method that we are using,
we are just finding patterns
based on unlabeled data.
If we apply this technique of
finding association rules
on this data set, then, first of all,
we need to compute the frequent item sets.
We find 153 item sets having
a support of at least 0.1.
This yields more than 700 association
rules if we take a minimal
confidence of 0.5.
So this explosion of rules can
be very confusing to the user.
That is why we can increase the threshold.
So we set the threshold of minimal support
to 0.3, we set the confidence to 0.9,
and if we then again apply
the same analysis work flow,
we only get 61 association rules.
We can for
example look at the top three of them.
So the first rule says that
people that ordered espresso,
pizza Siciliana, pizza Romana
also ordered vino bianco.
We can see the support,
confidence, and lift levels here.
So it's a positive correlation,
the confidence is more than 0.9,
and the support is,
32% of all the customers.
This is another rule.
People that ordered vino rosso,
vino bianco, and
pizza romano, also ordered espresso and
pizza siciliana.
Again we have a confidence of 0.9.
Finally, we have the third
rule in this list.
People that ordered both types of
wine also ordered pizza siciliana,
and the confidence is again above 0.9.
And again there's a positive correlation
and a support that seems reasonable.
So this way we can discover
these rules from unlabeled data.
Association rules are particular
types of patterns.
There are other patterns
that one can consider.
For example one can apply
sequence mining techniques.
That are essentially the same
as association rules but
now also look at the ordering
of the different events.
We can also look at episode mining.
It's again similar to
association rules but
now taking into account
a partial order of items.
However all of these techniques,
do not consider end-to-end process models.
For that we need to really use
process mining techniques.
But often we can use data mining
techniques in conjunction with process
mining to exploit all the existing
techniques like decision trees and
association rules in
a process oriented manner.
Again, in chapter three, you can read more
about these basic data mining techniques.
Thank you for watching this lecture,
see you next time.
[MUSIC]