[MUSIC]
Welcome to the last lecture, of the first
week of this course on process mining.
In the previous lectures, we learned
about various data mining techniques.
Today, we discuss ways of measuring
the quality of data mining results.
We have seen techniques like
decision tree learning,
association rule learning, clustering,
sequence mining and many other techniques.
Later we will see techniques for
process discovery, conformance checking,
for predicting remaining flow times.
All of these techniques, produce results
of the models, and question is,
what is the quality of such models?
In the lecture today,
we will look at evaluating the quality of
data mining results, but many of the
ideas will also be applicable to evaluating
or at least discussing
the results of process mining.
The first topic, that we would like to
discuss today is the confusion matrix,
that we have seen before and
the measures based on it.
It is best to explain it simply
using a set of examples.
So this is, a decision tree, to learn
which students fail, pass or
pass cum laude,
based on the course grades that they have.
If we create the so-called
confusion matrix,
we plot the actual class against,
the predicted class.
So for example, if you look at this
matrix, we can see that there were
21 students that passed
as the actual class, but
the predicted class was that
they would have failed.
And so this is an incorrect prediction.
The green values, indicate
the positive results, the red values
indicate problems and the higher the red
numbers are, the bigger the problem is.
We can take another example.
So, we were trying to predict,
what was causing the fact that
certain customers got sick.
There were three classes of customers.
Customers that were not sick,
that were very sick, and
a group of customers that was nauseous.
The decision tree that we learnt,
had problems picking up,
patients that are nauseous.
And you can see that here,
if you take a look at the column
indicating the people that are nauseous.
If you look at the lower row, you see
the people that were actually very sick,
and they were all predicted correctly.
So all people that were, very sick,
were predicted to be sick.
On the other end as I just mentioned,
customers, that were nauseous,
and there were more than 300 of them,
were never predicted to be nauseous.
So this way we can see that the confusion
matrix gives an indication of
the quality of the decision tree.
If we take a look at
a binary classification,
the terms that we can
use are true positives.
These are the instances,
that are actually positive, for example,
becoming sick, and
are also predicted to be positive.
True negatives.
Negative instances,
predicted to be negative.
So, these are, highlighted in green,
because they are desirable values.
We would like them to
be as high as possible.
On the other hand, we also have
false positives and false negatives.
These correspond to instances,
that are classified incorrectly.
So either negative instances,
are predicted to be positive or
positive instances
are predicted to be negative.
If we apply it to the example of
the restaurant, then true positives,
would correspond to sick customers
that were predicted to be sick.
If we, for example, look at false
negatives, then this corresponds to,
sick customers that were
predicted to be not sick.
So this is indicating the, types of
problems that we would like to analyze.
We would like to capture
these problems in a number.
So, the error rate
corresponds to the number
of false positives and
the number of false negatives.
So all the problematic cases,
divided by the total number of instances.
Accuracy is exactly the reverse.
We take the number of true positives and
true negatives.
So all the correct predictions.
And we divide that
by the total number of instances.
Precision and recall are two important
metrics, that are often used.
So precision corresponds to
the number of true positives,
divided by the number of true positives
plus the number of false positives.
Recall, is a number of true
positives divided by the number of
true positive plus the number
of false negatives.
We would like precision and
recall to be as close to one as possible.
The F1 score,
is the harmonic mean of precision and
recall and we can compute it
using the formula shown here.
So let's apply this to
the following example.
So what you see here,
is the initial state of a decision tree,
before splitting any of the nodes
based on some attributes.
And a decision tree,
that we discover after splitting
based on the attribute smoker and
the attribute drinker.
We can see the,
confusion matrices of both decision trees.
So the one consisting of just one,
leaf node and
the one consisting of three leaf nodes.
And we would like to compare them based
on precision recall and F1 score.
So please compute these values.
These values can be computed by just
applying the formulas
that we have seen before.
So if we look at
the classification where all
the persons are predicted to die young.
And nobody is predicted to die old,
then precision is 0.63 because 63%
of the persons actually died young.
Recall is equal to one because we never
predict somebody to die at an older age,
and F1 score,
the harmonic mean of
these two values is 0.77.
If we look at a more refined decision
tree after splitting on these two
labels we can see that precision improved.
Recall was reduced slightly.
And that is due to the two young people
that died young, and were predicited
to die at an older age.
That is the two in the confusion matrix.
Recall, is slightly worse than before,
but precision is much better, and
also the F1-score is much better.
So, this is an objective means
to compare the two decision trees.
So, that was the confusion matrix and
metrics like precision and recall.
Let's now take a look at cross-validation.
Now, to explain why
cross-validation is important.
It helps to look at
the following sentence.
Take your ten best friends, and
suppose that you would create a decision
tree that accurately predicts the length
of a friend, based on the person's
birth date and eye color.
If you have a group of just ten
friends it is quite easy to
construct such a decision tree.
And it will perform perfectly
on your ten best friends.
But then if you would get
another friend, it is very
likely that the decision tree
will produce an incorrect value.
This is the problem of overfitting.
So we are overfitting the example set, and
by that, we cannot generalize properly.
So a definition of overfitting is
that the model is too specific for
the data set used, and will most likely
perform very poorly on new instances.
And here you see a rule that could be the
rule that would result from overfitting.
So people having a particular birth date
and a particular eye color would have
a particular length with
a very large precision.
Underfitting is the other problem.
You're not overfitting the data.
You're making conclusions that are so
general, that they don't say very much and
that they don't actually use the data.
For example, a rule like, if gender
is male, then length is larger than
one meter, is a rule that may often be
true, but it is severely underfitting,
because we, we didn't actually learn
from the data that we were analysing.
Because of these problems,
over-fitting and under-fitting,
we typically split the data set
into a training set and a test set.
Then we apply a learning algorithm
that will create a model, for
example, a decision tree.
Then we take the test set and
we try the test set on the model that we
have learned based on the training set.
And then we measure the performance.
So we are testing our
model on unseen data.
And this is the main
idea of cross validation.
If you do it like this
you're using your data
not in an optimal way because you didn't,
use all the data to learn
as much as possible.
That is why you can repeat the principal
that is shown here by partitioning
your data in k parts and then use
k minus 1 parts to learn the model and
use one of these k parts for
testing the quality of the model.
And you can repeat this experiment
k times, so then you are really using
all data available to both learn
the model and to test the result.
There are many possible complications.
So one of the complications
that we may face if we
are evaluating the quality of a model
that we have learned is concept drift.
Over time, the characteristics of
the underlying process may have changed.
And, this may, make things very difficult.
Another complication with respect
to evaluating data is that
often we do not have negative examples.
For example, if we look at our restaurant,
we only know about sick customers
that complain afterwards.
We do not know anything about that
customers that actually did not complain.
So often,
we have an unbalanced set that we
are using to learn without
any negative examples.
Also, in the context of process mining,
this problem is considerable.
Because we only see the traces that
have happened not the traces that
could not happen.
So we are facing similar problems.
The focus of this course is
clearly on process mining, but
we had to learn these basic data
mining techniques beforehand.
Because we can adopt
some of the ideas
from data mining.
And sometimes in the context of process
mining we are also locally using data
mining techniques.
For example,
if we have learned the process model.
And in that process
model there is a choice.
Then after learning the control flow,
we may want to use decision tree learning,
to see what is influencing the decision
in the process, but we can only do that
if we have beforehand discovered
the process model itself.
So in this way process mining
extends way beyond classical data
mining approaches that do not
consider process models at all.
So process mining is as a bridge
between classical data analysis and
classical process analysis.
After explaining the core
results in data mining,
we now move to the more
process-oriented part of this course.
So the next set of
lectures will be devoted
to process models and
learning these process models.
If you would like to read more on data
mining take a look at chapter three.
Thank you for
watching this lecture, see you next time.
[MUSIC]