[MUSIC]
Welcome to this lecture.
Today we will continue
with decision trees.
The last lecture presented
the main concepts.
Today, we show more examples and
focus on the application of
such classification techniques.
Here you can see the running example
that we have used in the last lecture.
Using the notion of entropy,
we were splitting notes into smaller
notes until they were more homogenous.
In such a way that we could understand
the data in a better way, and
we could make predictions.
Today we will look at much more
examples to get a better understanding,
what the decision tree is,
and how it can be used.
So let's take a look at this small
example, where we have a group of
160 students 100 of these 160
students passed, 60 failed.
Suppose that we know
the gender of these students.
We know whether they are smoking or no.
We know whether they
are attending lectures.
Can we then predict whether
students are going to pass or
fail based on these attributes?
We can do this by building
a decision tree and whenever we
want to split a node, in this case a root
node we want to know what the entropy is.
So if we would like to split
on the attribute smoker.
We are interested to see what
the information gain is.
On this slide you can see the numbers
indicating for the people that smoke and
do not smoke.
How many people passed and
how many people did not pass.
So please compute the information
gain of this split.
The answer can be computed as follows.
First we take a look at the root node,
we apply the standard formula for
entropy, and
we find that the entropy is 0.95.
Then we split based on
the attribute smoker.
We get two smaller groups and for
each group we compute the entropy.
So for one group it is 0.95.
For the other group it is also 0.95.
So the entropy values in both of the leaf
nodes did not go down,
compared to the root node.
To compute the overall entropy,
we need to take the weighted average, and
if we do that, we get the entropy for
the root node.
And of course it is also 0.95.
And if we compute the weighted
average of the entropy of the two
new leaf nodes we find
exactly the same value.
So there is no information gain, and
actually there was no need to do all of
these computations because we
could see that the fraction within
the two child nodes was exactly
the same as it was before, so
we did not gain any information.
Let us therefore take a look
at another attribute.
We can split the set of all students
into the students that are male and
the students that are female.
And we now can see that the fractions are
different from females compared to males.
So the question is,
what is the information gain?
To compute the answer we need to compare
the original entropy of the root
node with the weighted average
of the entropy of the two new leaf nodes.
This is the entropy of one leaf node.
This is the entropy of
the other leaf node.
We can take the weighted average
of these two values, and
if we do so we can see that there
is actually a change in entropy.
Unlike based on the label
smoker we can see that there
is a considerable information gain of 0.2.
And so, we are seeing here,
if we inspect the decision tree,
that females typically have
a better study result.
So by splitting on this label for
the group of females,
we know we can better predict
what their study results will be.
As a last label we look at
the attribute attended all lectures.
So people that attended all lectures
we make a prediction for those and
we also make a prediction for the people
that did not attend all lectures.
So the question is what is
the information gain?
Again, we can do the same computations.
So, we can compare the original
entropy of the root node
with the weighted average of
the entropies of the two child nodes.
So, for one child node it is 0.81.
For the other child node it's 0.
So people that attended all
lectures always passed so
that's why the entropy within
this group is equal to 0.
Again we need to compare the weighted
averages of the original situation and
the situation after splitting and
if we do that we get these values.
And we can see that there is
a considerable information gain
by splitting based on this
particular attribute.
So the information gain is 0.54.
If we now compare the three
attributes based on
which we could split,
it is clear that splitting based on
whether all lectures were attended
provides the best information.
So if we build a decision tree,
it is reasonable to start
with this particular attribute, and then
see whether we need to split other nodes.
So if we take a look at the decision tree
after one split, attended all lectures,
then we find one group which we
classify as pass where no further
information gain is possible because all
the instances are classified correctly.
If you take a look,
at the other group,
the people that did not attend all
lectures, we can still look at
the other attributes to see whether
we can achieve more information gain.
All of this can be seen best
by simply applying a tool.
So in this course we will often use
examples taken from RapidMiner.
The installation of RapidMiner
is optional, but
if you would like to play with these
ideas using software in the lecture
guide you can see how to install it,
where to get it, and how to use it.
RapidMiner is an integrated extendable
environment for machine learning and
all kinds of other types of
analysis that are focusing on data.
RapidMiner also has
a so-called marketplace.
And there you can also download to so
called ProM extension.
So in RapidMiner, you can also
do process mining using many of
the techniques that you
will see in later lectures.
There are two versions,
there are commercial and
open-source version and
we are using here the open-source version.
So, let's take a look at an example.
So we take a data set, you can see
it's a simple CSV file where we have
a column gender, a column age,
a column smoker, a column car brand,
and a column claim and
the latter deserves some explanation.
This is a variable indicating whether
somebody has claimed insurance,
car insurance, in the last year.
So for example the first row
in this table says there is a,
a female customer that has insurance,
age 47, is a smoker,
drives a Volvo, and she did not claim
any insurance in the last year.
So if we take such a data set,
we are interested in seeing which
people are claiming insurance.
Can we predict that?
So the,
we took a data set of 999 customers of
an insurance company to
learn these types of things.
So we would like to know which
customers claim insurance
by simply using this CSV file.
So, the response variable
is the column claim.
All the other columns correspond
to predicted variables.
And we would like to explain
the response variable in terms of
these predicted valuables.
So we can feed this to RapidMiner.
So we can simply take this CSV file,
download it in RapidMiner,
then we need to indicate what our
role is of all the different columns.
And after doing that we have loaded
it in the repository of RapidMiner.
And now we can apply all kinds
of analysis techniques to it.
For example,
a workflow to build a decision tree.
So here we see a sketch of this workflow,
in RapidMiner.
So we first load the data,
then we create a decision tree.
Then we apply the decision
tree to the data set.
And then we look at
the resulting performance.
So if we take this data set and
we apply the workflow just indicated,
this is the decision tree that we get.
So you can read this decision
tree just as you did before.
So for example, female drivers don't claim
insurance according to this decision tree.
Male Alfa Romeo drivers typically
claim insurance in the last year
as you can see in this decision tree.
Male Volvo drivers younger
than 25 claim insurance.
It's another fact that we can
read from this decision tree.
So the decision tree predicts for
certain groups of customers
whether they will claim or not.
So what is the quality
of this decision tree?
We were measuring the performance.
And if we, after learning the decision
tree, apply it to the same dataset.
We can see that of the 513 females,
498 actually did not claim.
So less than 3% was wrong.
If you look at Alfa Romeo drivers,
there were 90 male
Alfa Romeo drivers,
four did not claim, 86 claimed.
The label says they will claim.
So less than 5% is wrong.
If we look at the group
of male BMW drivers,
we can see that more than 20% is wrong.
So we can measure the quality of this
classification using the set that we
have used to learn this decision tree.
In this table you can
see again the data set.
But now there is an additional label
telling what the predicted class is.
So, this is the real class and
this the predicted class.
So, if we take a look at the smaller
fragment of this table one can look at it
and try to see, are there any instances
that are classified incorrectly here.
If you do so
you will see that row 11 shows an instance
that was classified incorrectly.
A male 43 year old
non-smoking Subaru driver was
predicted to claim but in reality did not.
If you look at row 12 you
will find a similar problem.
As our BMW driver that was predicted
not to claim but actually did claim.
So these are examples of where we
can see that the decision tree
is only making a prediction
that will hold for
probably the majority of instances, but
will not hold for all the instances.
You can show this using
a so-called confusion matrix.
So there were 761 customers that were
predicted not to claim and
actually did not claim.
There were 24 customers that did not
claim, but that were predicted to claim.
And so the numbers in the green cells,
they correspond to things that are good.
The numbers in the red cell,
they indicate two misclassifications
using the decision tree.
Let's take a look at a larger data set.
Consider an Italian restaurant, where we
have 5,000 parties that have a dinner.
The menu includes all of these
dishes that you see here.
But unfortunately of these 5,000 parties,
470 parties had
members that got very sick,
313 parties got nauseous,
and the remaining parties did
not experience any problems.
The question is now using
decision trees can we predict
which people will become
sick after eating what.
Or if we look at things in hindsight.
We would like to understand what
are people that got sick or
nauseous,
what they had in common.
What was the dish that caused
all of these problems?
Again we can formulate a problem
in terms of a CSV file.
So here you see a data set where all the
columns correspond to dishes and drinks.
The numbers indicate how many times that
particular dish or drink was ordered.
And all the row corresponds to a party.
And in total we have 5,000 parties.
This is the workflow that we have
to learn the decision tree problem.
Note that all of the parties were
labeled in one of these three groups.
Very sick, not sick, or nauseous.
And then we apply this
workflow on this data.
So first, we load the data,
then we create a decision tree.
Then we apply the decision
tree to the data set and
we measure conformance,
exactly as we did before.
We set the minimal
information gain to 0.1.
And so we are using this
parameter to see when
we need to stop
extending the decision tree.
If we do this the RapidMiner
returns this decision tree.
It's showing that people,
that ate this particular pizza
and were drinking beer that
they typically got very sick.
The other parties, according to this
decision tree, did not become sick.
And so people that did not eat
any pizza marinara were okay,
that just ate one pizza,
they're also still okay.
Also the people that were eating
this particular pizza and
not drinking beer,
they also did not get sick.
So this node corresponds to parties
that ate less than two pizzas marinara,
and they did not get sick.
This node corresponds to parties
that ate multiple pizzas marinara,
and that drank beer, and got very sick.
These are the people that did not
drink beer and also did not get sick.
Just like the people that
did not eat the pizza.
So, the decision tree
clearly indicates that
the combination of pizzas marinara and
beer caused the sickness.
What is remarkable if you look at
this decision tree is that there were
several parties that were
classified as nauseous.
But it is not, there's no class in this
decision tree that is labeled as such.
We can see this if we look
at the confusion matrix.
So in the confusion matrix we
can see that 307 of the 313
parties that were nauseous
were classified as non sick.
The other 6 were classified as very sick.
So the decision tree is unable
to identify this group.
Apparently there is not enough
that they have in common to make
a proper prediction for
this particular class.
We can change the information gain and
continue to split the tree further.
So if we set the information gain to
0.5, this is the decision tree that we get.
And you can see that it is
becoming very complicated and
also seems to over fit.
For example, if we look at the node
nauseous, that is labeled as nauseous now.
You can see that this refers
to a very particular group of
customers that ate a very
specific combination of things.
We get an improvement, but we get the
improvement only at the cost of severely
over fitting the data, a topic that will
be addressed also in later lectures.
So, we can either classify
everybody as not sick.
We can have a very detailed decision
tree if we set the information gain to
even lower values.
We get trees that are bigger and bigger.
But these bigger trees,
they are clearly overfitting.
And if we just predict for
everybody that they will not get sick
we have a tree that is underfitting.
So the idea of these parameters is to
balance between these two extremes.
It seems that the tree that
we showed at the beginning
provides a reasonable balance between
underfitting and overfitting.
It can be used to understand
what is happening and
it can be used to make predictions or
recommendations.
And this is exactly how we would
like to use these decision trees.
So the last two lectures were
devoted to decision tree learning.
We will look at two additional data
mining techniques, but much shorter.
That will be association rule learning and
clustering.
And these will be addressed in
the next couple of lectures.
As indicated before,
chapter three is devoted to these
different data mining techniques.
Thank you for watching and
hope to see you soon.
[MUSIC]