[MUSIC]
Welcome to this lecture.
Today we will look at another
unsupervised data mining technique.
We will show how instances
can be clustered
in homogenous groups using the so
called k-means technique.
Here again we see the overview of all the
different data mining techniques that we
are considering.
Decision tree learning was an example
of a supervised learning technique.
Association rules that we
discussed in the last lecture
is an unsupervised learning
techniques just like the clustering
approaches we will discuss today.
So, what is the basic idea of clustering?
We have,
instances that have different attributes.
Here, we only see two attributes, but
it could be hundreds or
thousands of attributes.
And we would like to group.
These instances in homogeneous groups,
just as is sketched here in this slide.
So, we have a cluster A,
a cluster B, and a cluster C
of points that are closer related to
each other than to the other instances.
So, how to compute these clusters?
One approach is the so
called k-means clustering,
where beforehand we need to
set the number of clusters.
In this case we set k
to 3 indicating that we would like
to extract three different clusters.
Again, I'm using a 2 dimensional diagram,
but this is very misleading.
Often, there are hundreds or
thousands of dimensions,
making clustering much more challenging.
So, how does k-means clustering work?
We start by, setting so called centroids.
These are points in this
n dimensional space.
These points could be set randomly, or
some other approach could be used
like, for example,
making it match to one of the instances.
After setting these three centroids,
what we do is that we decide for
every instance to which
centroid it is closest.
So if we do that we have a blue,
a red, and a green centroid.
And we start coloring the instances,
then this is what we get.
So we have assigned all instances
to the closest centroid.
After coloring the instances,
what we can do is that we
can look at the instance of a particular
color, and compute a new centroid.
The centroids that is
like the average of all
the different points
having a particular color.
If we do that,
then this is the situation that we get.
So for example,
if we look at the 3 green dots,
then they have a centroids which
is like the point in the middle.
The same holds for the blue
cluster, and the red cluster.
After recomputing the centroids,
we again start
coloring the different instances,
again based on the closest centroid.
If we do that, then this is the result.
So what we can see is that the one
instance highlighted here,
it is still closest to the blue centroid.
After doing this we, again, based on the
instances that have a particular color,
we again recompute the centroids.
And if we do that,
then this is the resulting situation.
Now take a look at the blue
dot closest to the bottom.
It is now closest to the red centroid, so
in the next iteration it will
be added to the red centroid.
Now we start recomputing,
the middle of all of the centroids, and
this is the result that we get.
The situation that we see
here is a so-called fixpoint.
If we now iterate further,
nothing will change anymore.
Note that approach is
non-deterministic if we
take a random initialization
of the centroids.
So, typically the experiment
is repeated multiple times.
We take the best clustering.
That results from all these random trials.
This is the way that we
can use k-means clustering
to find homogenous groups of instances.
So the main idea is that instances in
a cluster are more similar to each
other than those in other clusters.
And this has many applications.
So for example, we can try to find
homogenous groups of customers,
of patients, of sessions, of students.
Etcetera.
After creating these clusters,
we get smaller datasets.
So for example, now we have
partitioned the dataset that is
shown here into loyal customers,
discount customers, and impuls customers.
And now to each of these clusters,
we can apply.
Other data mining techniques or
process mining techniques.
For example, we could now build decision
trees, based on these individual clusters.
Or create association rules for
these different clusters.
Let's go back to the Italian restaurant
that we have used before, but
now to simplify things we have
restricted the menu to only 6 items.
In other ways we just abstract
from all the other items, and
just look at customers buying these
particular dishes and drinks.
We can now apply this mining technique.
This is the input that we get,
again we have a class label but
we can ignore it,
because this is an unsupervised method.
We would like to find patterns and
groups of,
customers that belong together
without labeling the data before.
So, to compute the clusters,
we use this, workflow in rapid miner.
We load the data sets,
we apply k-means clustering,
where we set k in this case to 2.
And then, at the end,
we measure performance.
And there are different ways of measuring.
The performance of clustering, but they
are outside of the scope of this course.
If we apply two means
clustering to this data set we
find two clusters that have
approximately the same size.
And if we look at the centroids of
these two clusters we can clearly see.
What these two clusters represent.
So, in cluster zero, we can find,
typically instances,
customers that have bought lasagna,
spaghetti carbonara, and drank beer.
In the other cluster,
we typically find people.
That have eaten pizza, pizza margherita or
pizza siciliana, and
that were drinking wine.
So, using clustering, we find two
homogeneous groups of customers.
Customers that drink beer, and
that eat lasagna and or spaghetti.
And customers that drink wine and
eat pizza.
Let's take a look at this in
rapid minor and where we try to
plot the data to create some additional
insights into these clusters and
to see that they
are actually valid clusters.
So here you see a scatter plot,
where every dot corresponds to a customer.
And we indicate the number
of pizza sicilliana that
the customer has ordered on the y axis.
On the x axis we plot the number of pizzas
margherita that people have bought.
The color.
Correspond to the clustering that
was automatically discovered.
What we see is that customers in cluster
zero, indicated by the blue dots.
These are typically not
ordering any pizzas.
But people in the red cluster,
typically, are ordering.
Just a pizza margherita, just a pizza
siciliana, or multiple pizzas.
Here we see another scatter plot.
So, on the y axis,
we are plotting the number of times
that spaghetti carbonara was ordered.
On the x axis, we plot the number
of times that lasagna was ordered.
If you look at the red and the blue dots,
they again correspond to the clusters
that we have discovered before.
So the blue dots are in cluster zero, and
they correspond to customers
that typically ordered at least.
One time spaghetti carbonara,
or one time lasagna,
or multiple items of lasagna and
spaghetti carbonara.
Customers in the red cluster,
they typically ordered no pasta.
We can also look at the dimension
of drinks, and again we
can clearly see that the customers in
the red cluster are drinking wine,
whereas the customer in the blue
cluster are drinking beer.
So this provides evidence that the
clustering we automatically discovered.
Actually make sense for this data set.
So, k-means is one of several
clustering techniques that one can use.
One of the drawbacks of k-means is that
you need to decide on the value of
k up front.
Like in the previous example,
we set k to 2.
If you would like to see whether there
are tree clusters that make sense,
we need to try the same approach
with the k set to tree.
Other clustering techniques may
provide a hierarchy of clusters.
And you can see an example here.
On the right hand side,
you see a so-called dendogram and
it is indicating a hierarchy of clusters.
On the other side,
you can see the corresponding clusters.
So how to read such a diagram,
such a hierarchy.
A group similar sets of instances
in a hierarchical manner.
And it can build it in this way in,
in an incremental way.
If we cut the hierarchy
at a particular place,
we find as many clusters as the number
of lines that we are crossing.
So if we take a higher abstraction
level, we will only find two clusters.
One cluster consisting of a,
b, c, and d, and
another cluster consisting of
the rest of the instances.
We can also go lower in the hierarchy,
and again if we cut the hierarchy,
we find different clusters.
So in the example now,
we find the cluster consisting of a and
b, the cluster consisting of c and d,
a cluster containing just e,
a cluster containing f and
g, a cluster containing h and
i, and a cluster containing j.
And so we can seamlessly decide
on the number of clusters that we
would like to have.
Clustering can also be
used to split event logs.
So suppose that we have event logs
referring to different types of customers.
We could first do clustering based on
the characteristics of the patients or
the customers.
And then we can automatically build
process models for each of the clusters.
So this way you can see
how process mining and
data mining techniques can be combined.
This was the last data mining technique
that we have discussed, in the next
lecture we will focus more on evaluating
the quality of data mining results.
And then we can switch to more
the process-oriented aspects of
process mining.
Thank you for watching, and
I hope to see you soon.
[MUSIC]