[MUSIC].
Welcome to this lecture of the course on
Process Mining: Data Science in Action.
Before we focus on process mining,
it is good t have a solid understanding
of the mainstream data mining techniques.
Hence, there will be several
lectures on data mining.
Today we start by presenting
a technique to learn decision trees.
This slide shows that process
mining is the linking pin
between data-oriented analysis,
and process-oriented analysis.
Before we focus on process discovery
techniques, conformance checking.
Predictive analytics, and
other forms of process mining.
We now look at so-called
decision tree learning,
which is one of many available
data mining techniques.
So what is a decision tree?
In a decision tree we have a number
of predictor variables, and
based on these predictor variables.
We try to predict,
what the so-called response variable is.
Decision tree learning is
a form of supervised learning,
because the data is labeled.
Labeled using the response variable.
In our case, this is categorical data.
Let's take a look at some examples.
For example, we would like
to know what the effect is of
lifestyle on how old people get.
One can take this as input data, so
we know whether people are drinking,
smoking, what their weight is.
And we know the age at
which people have died.
Now we try to predict, whether people will
die at an older age or at a younger age.
So as a response variable,
we take the age and we make it discrete.
We turn it into a categorical variable,
so people that die about 70.
Are labeled old, people that
die under the age of 70 are labeled young.
And the other variables are used
as predictor variables.
So we would like to predict
the response variable in terms of
these predictor variables.
This is a so called decision tree.
It is learned based on the data,
and what it tells you, for
example, that if people are smoking,
they are likely to die young.
If people are not smoking, they are not
drinking, then they are likely to die old.
We can also see numbers in
the leaves of such a tree.
This is explaining,
what was done with the training set
used to learn this decision tree.
In this case there were 195 smokers.
They were all classified as young,
but there were
11 smokers that actually died at an older
age so that are classified incorrectly.
The other leaves have similar numbers.
For example, there were two
people that were not drinking,
that were not smoking,
but still died young.
Okay.
Let's see whether we can
read such a decision tree.
Take Mary.
She is drinking, but she's not smoking.
Her weight is 70 kilos, and
she died at the age of 85.
So the question is, is Mary classified
correctly in this decision tree.
The answer is yes.
And the red path shows what
Mary's path is through this decision tree.
So Mary was not smoking, she was drinking,
and her weight was below 90,
so according to the decision tree
she should be classified as old,
dying above the age of 70.
And indeed she did.
Let's take a look at another person, Sue.
Is she classified correctly
according to this decision tree?
Again we follow the path.
So Sue is not a
smoker and is not a drinker.
So it is predicted that she will die at an
older age, above 70, but she died at 35.
So she's not classified correctly
according to this decision tree.
Let's take a look at another data set.
Suppose that we have data about.
The marks that student had for
individual courses.
If there is a dash in this table it means
that the course was actually not taken,
and so no result is known.
In all the other cases,
there's a number between one and
ten indicating how well somebody made
the exam for that particular course.
Then we could be interested in
the duration, or we could also be
interested in the fact whether people
pass, fail, or graduate cum laude.
If we are interested
in the latter column.
Then the response variable is the result,
which is cum laude, passed, or
failed, and the predictor variables are
the grades for all the individual courses.
Using such data,
we can again learn a decision tree, and
here you see an example of it.
So.
People that had a mark lower than 8 for
logic and had a mark of 6 or
higher for linear algebra, it is predicted
that they have, that they will pass.
People that did not make
the course on logic, or
did not have a grade for
it are predicted to fail.
So again, the decision tree makes
predictions by learning from
a larger set of examples.
Let's take a look at the third data set.
Here we see what people are buying
in a coffee shop, and so
people may order cappuccino.
latte, espresso.
Cafe Americano, tea, and
they may eat a muffin or a bagel.
As a response variable we
take the column muffin, and
we again make it discrete into a
categorical variable, muffin or no muffin.
And so
we ignore the numbers in this table.
Just whether things are present or not.
So this is decision tree that
we could learn over this data.
So what we see is that people
that drink tea according to
this decision tree also eat a muffin.
People that do not drink a tea,
do not drink latte.
Are predicted to not order a muffin.
So, let's take again
a look at some questions.
So here you see the check
of a visitor of this cafe.
And this visitor ordered 2 cappuccinos,
3 lattes, 1 muffin and 2 bagels.
Is this particular example classified
correctly according to the decision tree?
The answer is yes, and here in red,
you can see again the path.
People that, do not drink tea but
drink at least two lattes.
They are predicted to also order a muffin.
And that is the case in this situation.
Let's take a look at another example.
A person ordered a bagel,
a latte, and a ristretto.
The question is,
is this person classified correctly?
If we follow the path
through the decision tree,
it is predicted that such
a person would order a muffin.
But this is actually not the case.
And so this would be an instance that
would be classified incorrectly by this
decision tree.
We can use the decision tree to make
predictions over unseen instances.
So, suppose that we have this check,
we know that somebody ordered the bagel,
two lattes, and one cappuccino.
Then the question is, is it likely that
the person also ordered a muffin?
Then we can use a decision tree.
So, in this situation what
would a decision tree tell?
The decision tree would tell that this
person would indeed order a muffin,
and that is the case because
the person ordered no tea.
At least 2 lattes, and
people that fall into this class
are predicted to order a muffin.
So how does this work?
We now have seen what a decision tree is,
how we can use it.
It can be used for understanding data, for
predicting data, but how when can we
automatically learn such a decision tree.
Well, it is done by splitting nodes to
reduce the variability within every node.
So, if we look at this,
if we look at 6, persons, and
they are all in the same category,
3 are red and 3 are green.
Then we have a high entropy.
We are very uncertain,
wether it should be green or red.
The idea is that we split nodes
that we are uncertain about into
smaller sets,
smaller classes that are more homogenous.
So, for example, if we split a set of
people, into smokers and non-smokers,
and we find that the 2 smokers died
at a younger age labeled here as red
then we reduce the variation
within the individual subsets.
So, we are still uncertain
about people who do not smoke.
And we could again split the group
of non-smokers into two groups.
The people that drink, and
the people that do not drink.
What we then find is that
the variation within the group of
people that do not drink.
And do not smoke.
That all of these people live longer.
So, this overview slide shows that we
try to go from a bigger
class with high entropy,
a high degree of uncertainty, to smaller
classes where we are more certain about.
And, this way we can incrementally
build a decision tree.
What is crucial for
understanding decision trees,
is that you have a good understanding
of the notion of entropy.
So, entropy is the degree of uncertainty.
One can also think of entropy as
the inverse of compressibility.
Or zippability.
If there is very little
variation within a group,
then we can compress the data very much.
The goal is now to reduce the entropy
in the leaves of the decision tree.
And in this way we improve
the predictability.
Of elements that belong
to a particular class.
To formalize the notion of entropy,
we need to use logarithms.
And this is, basic high school math,
mathematics.
But still it is repeated so
that you easily can apply
the formulas on the coming slides.
For example if we take the logarithm of
2 to the power n, then the result is n.
If we take the logarithm of 1 divided
by 2 to the power n, we get minus n.
Here you can see some examples.
So for example,
the logarithm of 1 is equal to zero.
The logarithm of 1024 is equal to 10.
So what is not the formula for entropy?
The formula for entropy takes
the sum over a set of values.
So suppose that we have k possible values.
We enumerate them from 1 to k and
then pi is the probability
or in other words, the fraction
of elements having this value.
So we can estimate this pi,
this probability by taking the number.
Of elements that have that particular
value by the set of all elements.
As we divide ci by n, and
then we get the fraction pi.
And then we apply this formula.
So we take the sum over pi
times the logarithm of pi.
This looks very complicated,
but if one starts to apply it,
it will become more clear.
So, if we have two groups of people
that are represented in
a particular class, and of both
types of people we have the same amount,
then that is the worst case situation.
And so we have 3 reds, and 3 green dots.
So the entropy if we apply
this formula is equal to 1.
What this means is that we
need to have one bit to
encode whether a person belongs to the
red labeled class or
the green labeled class.
If we now split based on the attribute
smoker we get more homogeneous groups.
Let's see how this is
reflected in entropy.
So if we compute
the entropy of the smokers.
There are 2 smokers, and
they are both labeled red,
meaning that they both
die at a younger age.
If we now look at the entropy and
we fill out a formula,
the entropy is equal to zero.
We need no information.
We need no bits to encode.
What people in this class,
whether they are dying young or not.
Because that they all have the same label.
Now we can take a look at the class
of all people that do not smoke.
3 persons in the class, live longer.
1 person in this class live shorter.
If you now apply the formula,
then we get a value of 0.8.
And so we can see that the entropy,
we do not need to have one bit,
we can use slightly less.
We can split further based on
whether people are drinking or not.
So again, we have the class of smokers.
Still the entropy is equal to zero.
We can take a look at the people
that do not smoke but
that do drink, and
the entropy is equal to 1.
Because both groups
are equally represented.
It is a one-to-one relationship.
Finally, we have the people
who do not drink and
do not smoke,
the entropy of the group is equal to zero.
So this is the way that we
can compute entropy, and
here we can see all the numbers
that we have just computed.
Using this basic formula.
We can now take the weighted
average of these 3 decision trees.
So if we take a look at the first
decision tree there is just one leaf.
And in this leaf
the entropy is equal to 1.
And it is the complete fractions,
so 6 divided by 6.
So, the overall weighted average
of entropy is equal to 1.
If we take a look at the second
decision tree where we split
based on the label smoker, and we take
the weighted average of zero and 0.811.
Then we can see that the entropy is 0.54.
Note that 2 of the 6 persons ended up in
the class that had
an entropy equal to zero.
The rest.
Had an entropy of, 0.811.
That is why we need to apply
the formula in this way.
We can split based on the label smoker.
Now we have three, leaves.
Each of these leaves has a weight,
depending on the number of
people in that particular leaf.
We take the weighted average of
the different entropy values, and
we see that the resulting entropy is 0.33.
So what we can see is that
in the first decision tree,
the weighted average over all
these entropy values was 1, and
by splitting, based on the label smoker,
it went down from one to 0.54.
This means that we had
an information gain of 0.46.
If we take the tree in the middle,
we can split based on the level drinker.
And we get an entropy of one-third.
So now the information gain is 0.21.
So we would like to reduce the entropy.
And we would to split on the labels that
maximize the reduction of this entropy,
so that maximize information gain.
So the idea of the algorithm is now
that we continue splitting labels.
Trying to maximize information gain,
but stop if this is no longer possible.
So let's take a look at some
questions to see whether you
really understand the notion of entropy.
Here you see several
sets of colored balls.
And we would like to compute the entropy
of all the individual cells.
If you do that then you can
compute the overall entropy
of all of these 9 different squares.
And we can compare that with the overall.
Entropy if it would put all the balls in
1 big bin, and then compute the entropy.
And so please, try to compute these
values that are asked for here.
Okay, let's first take a look
at the cell in the middle.
If we look at the cell in the middle.
There are, 16 balls.
Two of each color.
And there are 8 different colors.
If we then apply the entropy formula, we
find that the entropy is equal to three.
So, we need to have 3 bits to
encode the color of a single ball.
In the square in the middle.
If we not take a look at the other cells,
they all contain 16 balls.
But they all have the same color.
So the entropy for
all these other cells is equal to zero.
And we can learn that by just filling out
the formula that we have seen before.
So, if we now look at the over all
entropy, we need to take the weighted
average of these 9 different squares and
we get an entropy of one-third.
That's right,
entropy of all cells is zero,
the cell in the middle
has an entropy of three.
There are nine cells, so
the resulting weighted average is 0.33.
What is the entropy after we take all
the different cells and mix them?
Then we have 144 balls
having 18 different colors.
So this is the distribution
that we then get, and
this corresponds to an entropy of three.
So if we now compare these 2 situations,
if we have these 9 different cells.
Where the cell in the middle
has all the colors, and
all the other cells have just 1 color,
we have a much lower entropy.
Then when we have one big
cell containing all balls,
because then the entropy is equal to 3.
So, if we move from
the situation with an entropy
of 3 to the entropy of one-third, we
have an information gain equal to 2.666.
So this is what is being used
when learning a decision tree.
So, you see another example.
We start by classifying
all people as dying young.
Then we split on the attribute smoker.
So we go from the attribute
that is listed here.
To these entropies for
the 2 new leaves that we find.
Then we can take the weighted average, and
compare this weighted average of the
overall entropy to the original entropy.
And we can see that there is indeed
an information gain of 0.107.
Although the classification did not
change there was information gain.
And this is because the group of smokers
is now more homogenous that it was before.
We can split further.
And again, we can look at
the original entropy values.
This is the weighted average.
And compare that to the new situation,
where we can basically apply
the formulas that we have seen before.
So these are the entropy values for
the different leaves.
We again take the weighted average.
We can compare both, and
we see that there is an information gain.
Of 0.07.
So, this shows you the basic idea
of the decision tree algorithm.
We start with the root node
that has all instances, and
then we iteratively go
through all the nodes.
And see whether we can
achieve an information gain.
We do that by trying to split on
all the possible attributes, and
see whether the entropy is indeed reduced.
So we select the attribute with
the biggest information gain,
above a certain threshold.
And then we split that node, and
we continue doing that until no
significant improvements are possible.
Then we return the decision tree.
So that's the basic idea of
learning a decision tree,
using the notion of entropy.
There are many parameters and
variations possible to do this.
For example one can define a minimal size
of a node before or after splitting,
to avoid overfitting, having all
kinds of leaves that correspond to for
example just a single instance.
We can set the threshold on
the minimal gain that is needed, and
stop splitting if this
gain cannot be achieved.
We can define a maximal depth of the tree.
We can also have, allow for
multiple times using a label.
Along a certain path.
Some decision tree algorithms
do not allow it, others do.
But rather than using entropy,
we can use alternative notions,
like the Gini index of diversity.
If we have a numerical variable,
we can make it.
Automatically categorical,
using particular types of techniques.
And so we split the domain of a numerical
variable to make it categorical.
We can also do a post pruning of the tree
to remove the leaf notes that do not
significantly increase the explanatory
power of the resulting decision trees.
Decision tree learning has many
applications also in the field of
process mining.
So for example,
if we take a look at this process model,
then we ask ourselves what
is driving these decisions?
These 2 decision points in this
process model, why are certain
instances going left and
our other instances going right.
What is the most likely path of
a running case giving it's attributes?
If we look at the particular case,
we would like to predict whether
it will be late or rejected.
Using decision tree learning on top
of process models, we can do that.
But it is crucial to see that these
questions require a discovered process,
otherwise none of this is possible.
So process discovery is necessary before
we can use decision tree learning.
Today was the first lecture that we start
talking about data mining techniques.
Please read chapter 3 to learn
more about decision tree learning.
Thank you for watching this lecture,
see you next time
[MUSIC].