[MUSIC]
Welcome to the second
lecture of the course on
process mining data science in action.
Today I provide an overview of
process mining by discussing three
types of mining.
Process discovery,
performance checking, and enhancement.
In my last lecture, I showed you that
we have large amounts of data, but
that it is not just about collecting data,
it's about analyzing processes.
That is one of the key things.
If you think about what process mining is,
then the next diagram provides
a nice illustration of that.
So process mining is bridging the gap
between classical process model analysis.
And data oriented analysis like
data mining and machine learning.
Process mining
is bridging this gap,
because it's focusing on processes.
But at the same time, using the real data.
In classical data mining,
people typically do not look at processes.
Especially not end to end processes.
In areas where people are concerned
with process model analysis,
they typically ignore the data.
Why are you doing process mining?
We are doing process mining to answer
performance related questions and
compliance related questions.
So why are there certain bottlenecks,
how can they be removed,
why do people deviate.
So the starting point for
process mining is event data.
What you see here is a table, and every
row in this table corresponds to an event.
An event has different properties, so
there are generic types of properties.
The first property is a case id.
In this case every record refers
to a student making an exam.
So the case id refers to the student.
The activity name refers to the exam.
And the timestamp in this
case is the date of the exam.
There can be additional data like, for
example, the mark, or
the grade that somebody got.
Let's take another example.
We are now looking at
the handling of orders.
Again every line, corresponds to an event.
If here we look at the first column,
we see the order number.
That is the case id.
The second column refers to
the activity that is being executed.
The third column,
again refers to the timestamp.
Then there is a column
referring to the resource.
The person executing
the corresponding activity.
And we can have all kinds of other columns
with other data like the products and
quantity and things like that.
Let's take a look at the third example.
Now we are in a hospital
we are treating patients.
And we look at an event log and
every row refers to a step in
the treatment of a particular patient.
So what you see is that, again, we see
a case id, activity name, and timestamp.
So the first column refers to the patient,
this case represented by a number.
The second column to the activity name,
the third column to the timestamp.
Again we see the resource,
in this case the doctor or
the nurse executing a particular activity,
and we can have all kinds of other data.
Like for example the age of the patient.
And all kinds of other properties of
the patient or the corresponding step.
So these are examples
of the kind of
event data that we would like to use for
analysis.
And we are focusing on the relationship
between process models and event data.
And I will talk about three types
of relationships between models and
event data.
Play-out, Play-in, and Replay.
Let's first take a look at Play-out.
Here the basic idea is that you start
from a model, and from that model,
you generate behavior.
And let me try to illustrate
this using a small example.
What you see here is
a so-called BPMN model.
And don't be scared off by it.
In later weeks we will discuss
these types of things in detail but
this model is describing
a particular work flow.
How things are executed, and
in what order they are being executed.
So, if we take one execution
of this process model,
which is about handling travel requests,
then it always starts with an activity a,
where we register the travel request.
It is done at a particular point in time,
and it is done by a particular person.
Then we start concurrently two paths.
In one path we execute activity d,
check budget.
And in another path we have a choice
between two different activities, b and c.
So let's assume that we do activity b,
get support from local manager.
And this is done at the particular
time and by a particular person.
Then, we have to do activity
d if we follow this model.
Check budget by finance.
Again, done at a particular point
in time by a particular person.
And then,
we can make a decision doing activity e.
Here we see an XOR-split.
So we need to make one of three
decisions accept, reject or there is
insufficient information and
we need to redo part of the process again.
If we decide to accept, we execute
activity g and the process ends.
So this is one possible scenario.
Let us now look at another possible
scenario following the same process.
So we first do an a we then,
again start two paths in parallel.
But now we do first d and
then we do c instead of b.
We then have to make a decision again.
But now there is not enough information.
We need to go back.
And if we go backwards, we
again need to execute d and b or c.
So we go back.
We execute b again.
We execute d.
Then we execute e.
And finally we make a decision.
And in this case the decision
is to reject the request.
So this shows you two possible paths.
But there are many more.
Now if we look at this process model
then these are possible ways of
playing out this model.
These are not the only ones because there
is a loop that are infinitely many.
So this is playing out a model.
And if you are using simulation or if you
are building an information system that
is driven by such models,
play-out is the thing that you are doing.
Let's now look at the reverse.
We are just reversing the arrow.
We now go from even data to
the corresponding process model.
And in later weeks we will look at
different algorithms to do this.
The basic idea is you look at
the number of example behaviors.
And you automatically
infer a model from it.
So here, if you look at the process,
if you look at the traces that you
see on top of this diagram, you can
see that it always starts with an a.
So we infer a model that
always starts with an a.
All the traces end with a g or and h, so
in the process model at the end there is a
choice between accept and reject, g and h.
This is a more complicated set of traces
and if we get this more complicated set of
traces, we get this
more complicated model.
So we are automatically
learning a model from examples.
And what is very important to understand
here is that no modeling is needed.
We are not making any models by hand.
We automatically infer
process models from
raw event data.
So let me ask you a question.
And of course you did not learn yet
process discovery techniques.
And later you will look
at algorithms to do so.
But take a look at these example traces.
And I ask you, can you create
a process model that allows for
the traces that you see here.
Think a bit about this for sometime.
And I'm quite sure that you probably
end up with a model like this.
So what is shown in this model.
That all the traces started with a.
And ends with an e or an f.
And in between we again have a choice
between B and C and we always do D.
And this can be done in any order that is
why we have an AND-split in this diagram.
So that was a toy example, we can
easily apply this to real world data.
So here you see an example.
That we will revisit several times
in the future.
Here we look at raw event data
from a Dutch housing agency.
And every row refers to an event
within this housing agency.
The first column refers to the number of
an apartment, the ID of an apartment.
The second column to the activity.
The third column to the time stamp.
Again, very similar to the things
that we have seen before.
If we take this raw event data, we infer
a process model that is describing
what happens when somebody that is
renting an apartment, cancels his rent.
Until the moment that apartment
is rented out to somebody else.
This is the full process model.
If we zoom into a particular part,
then you can see
a small fragment which is executed by,
let's say, approximately thirty, cases.
This case houses or apartments that
followed this sequential path.
Without modeling you are able to
see what is the process that is
really being executed.
Let's take a look at a more
complicated example.
We have been applying
this in probably 20 to
30 different hospitals where we can
take event data about patients.
So this is a homogeneous group of
patients within a Dutch hospital.
We can look at the audit trail of
a single patient of that patient,
we see all kinds of properties, and
we see the events that have been executed.
If we take 600 of such cases.
And we automatically infer a model.
We see this scary diagram
that you can see on one side.
It is showing that a treatment process of
this particular group of patients
is incredibly complicated.
Don't be scared off by this
spaghetti like diagram.
Later we will see all kinds of techniques
to simplify such diagrams, so that you
only have to look at the highways, or
the parts that you're interested in.
On the right-hand side of the screen,
you see also a graph-based model,
but it is now not showing activities,
but it is showing departments.
So rather than seeing the sequence from
one activity to the next activity we now
see how work is flowing from one
department to another department.
So these are some practical
examples showing you
how process mining can
be applied in practice.
But it doesn't stop here.
It is not enough to just learn the model,
the key element is that you can
replay a reality on top of models.
Whether you have made
these models by hand, or
whether you have automatically learned
them using process discovery is irrelevant.
What is important is that you try to
replay reality on top of the model.
So, at the top of the slide, you can
see a trace that happened in reality.
Again, this is an abstract example,
later I will show you a real example.
In reality, we saw the sequence a c d e g.
Let's try to replay this on this model.
And if we do this, we see a path through
the process model that is indeed possible.
So we replay reality on top of the model,
and while doing that we don't
encounter any problems.
So, nothing surprising yet
Let's now take a look at another case.
Where we see the sequence a c e g.
So this could be the path of a patient.
This could be the life
cycle of an apartment.
It could be somebody applying for
a mortgage.
It can be anything.
So we look a the sequence of events.
In this case in reality first a happens.
That is possible according to the model.
Then c happens, this is also
still possible in the model but
then in the reality e happened, and
according to the process model you can
only make a decision if also activity d
is being executed it is impossible
to execute d at this point in time.
So while replaying, we continue, but we
record the fact that there is a problem.
So here activity d,
check budget, is missing.
And then we continue and
in the remainder of the trace,
we don't see any surprising things.
So we can see where the deviations are.
Here I show you another example.
If we look at this example
first a then we do a c then
we see that in
reality h has happened.
So there was a rejection while
the process was still in the middle.
Again by doing replay we
can record a problem.
Provide diagnostics and
continue our replay.
This case, we make a decision and
finally we do the acceptance.
So again, we have found a deviation
between the reality and the model.
So, to check whether you have
understood these types of things.
Take a look at this model and
the corresponding tree traces.
Are these traces possible in this model or
not?
And if they are not possible, where
does reality deviate from this model?
Let's take a look at the answer.
If we take a look at the first trace.
a, b, d, c, e h.
Then we can see that this is impossible.
If we tried to replay it, we will see
that it is impossible to do both b and c.
When we take a look at the second trace,
we find kind of a reversed problem.
Now we don't have an activity too
much we have an activity too little.
Activity d is missing.
So it doesn't fit.
If you try to replay the last
trace you will see that you
don't encounter any problems so
indeed it is replayable.
So these examples show you
how you can apply yourself.
Conformance checking
techniques by doing replay.
Again, let us take a look
at a practical example.
This is a fragment of
a larger process model,
describing the handling of
complaints in a Dutch municipality.
These are people that are complaining
about the valuation of their house.
And because of that, they think
that they need to pay too much tax.
We take a look at this process and
we replay a reality on top of this model,
we will find interesting deviations.
Although the overall process
has a very good fitness,
the relationship between reality and
the model.
They are very close to one another.
We still find all kind of
interesting deviations.
So for example here the house
was reevaluated 23 times.
While it was not supposed to happen.
So something happened in reality.
Which was not possible
according to the model.
And by replaying reality on top of the
model, we can see these types of problems.
Replay is not just about conformance.
It's also about performance analysis.
We can easily replay an event logged that
has timestamps on top of such a model.
And each time we execute an activity.
We record the corresponding time
as you can see here on this slide.
So we just execute reality
on top of the model.
We record all the times.
And at the end we know exactly
how much time was spent in
all the different parts of the process.
And the black circles here indicate
delays between individual activities.
So we can do this for
a single execution, for a single trace.
But you can also do that for many traces.
If you do that for
many traces, you will see how often
an activity is being executed.
You will see how often a particular
path is being followed.
But you also see how long
activities have taken and
you will see what the delays
are in between these activities.
What are waiting times.
What are synchronization times.
You can record them for
hundreds of thousands or
perhaps even millions of cases.
And derive probability
distribution from them.
So again let us take a look
at a practical example.
Here we look again at a process
where people complain about
the valuation of their house.
We have derived automatically
a process model.
And these terms expressed as a petri net.
And now we can by replaying we
can see where the delays take place.
So if you look at this slide you can
see that certain places are
indicated in purple.
And these are the places
where we see a large delay.
So this is an indication where
possible performance problems are.
It can go one step further.
You can point at two arbitrary
points in the process.
You can see how many cases, in this case
how many objections are flowing from
this first red activity to the second red
activity, and we can see how long it took.
And you can see here
the corresponding statistics.
So by replaying you can see
exactly where delays take place.
You can start investigating
what is causing them.
So to provide an overview of
the things that I've been talking about
we have a real world where
things are happening.
We have a software system, that is,
somehow, recording events of
the things that take place.
People objecting to
the valuation of their house.
Patients being treated in a hospital.
Then we have these event data.
And we can do discovery,
automatically learning process models.
We can do conformance checking.
Comparing the event log
to the process model and
we can enrich, it's called enhancement here,
we can enrich the process
model with information about
deviations and performance.
For example the bottle necks
that I just showed you.
How does that relate to
the things that I've been talking about?
Play-out is about the classical use of
process models not
involving any event data.
Play-in corresponds to discovery.
You automatically learn a process model
without any modeling from raw event data.
And you have replay where you compare
a process model to an event log
to check conformance, to investigate
performance problems, etcetera.
So, I hope this gave you a good overview
of the three different types of,
process mining.
If you want to find more high-level
information about these three types,
please read chapter one.
Thank you very much for
watching and hope to see you soon.
[MUSIC]