[MUSIC]
Welcome to this first lecture of
the course on Process Mining: Data Science
in Action.
In this first week, we focus on the
relationship between Process Mining and
other types of data analytics.
Today, I start by discussing the broader
topic of Data Science and Big Data.
Today, many people say
data is the big oil.
And this is illustrating the incredible
amount of data that we are collecting and
the corresponding value.
If you would think about, how much data
was generated from pre-historic times,
until 2003.
And we think, what we can now do it at.
We are able to generate such
amounts of data in just 10 minutes.
So, in 10 minutes,
we are generating, as much data now.
As we were doing from
prehistoric times until 2003.
So this is
illustrating the incredible
growth of data.
So, what kind of data is this?
What kind of event data are we generating?
Well, we are generating, when we buy
a cup of coffee with our credit card.
When we make a phone call,
we are generating data.
When we are getting a speeding ticket.
And there are many other examples,
as you can see on this slide, showing
that we are generating all the time.
Even while, you are watching this MOOC,
you are generating data.
Because all kinds of
things are being recorded.
If you take another example and you look
at the simple telephone that now these
days everybody owns, then you can see that
such a phone has many different sensors.
There is a GPS sensor, telling you where
you are, but there are many other sensors,
for example, looking at your fingerprint,
and stuff like that.
These are all generating data, and
therefore we are talking
about the Internet of Events.
All the data that is being
recorded in all kinds of ways.
Let's look at this Internet
of Events in more detail.
What does it consist of?
One can talk about 4 different
sources of event data.
The first source of event data.
Is the Internet of Content.
This is the classical Internet that we
know, from Google and Wikipedia and
then people typically, talk about Big Data
they are talking about this Internet.
But next to this classical
Internet of Content,
we now also have an Internet People.
So we have Twitter messages.
We have Facebook.
All kinds of events,
social events that are generating data.
Then we have the Internet of Things.
It's another source of event data.
Today already many devices
are connected to the internet but
in the future many more devices
will be connected to the Internet.
For example your shaving device.
Your refrigerator, everything in
the future will be connected to
the Internet and
this will generate large amounts of data.
Last but not least, there is the Internet
of Places, when you are using your mobile
phone, as I just illustrated, the phone
contains all kinds of sensors that are
recording, where you are and
what you are doing and
this is another source of information.
So, this is why today many people talk,
about Big Data.
Incredible amounts of event
data that are being recorded.
When people talk about Big Data.
Talk about the exponential growth of data.
This picture looks very complicated but
don't be scared of by it.
It is showing the exponential growth
of the number of transistors on a chip.
And this was predicted by
the founder of Intel, Moore, and
we can see that this exponential growth
has continued over the last 40 years.
Every 2 years, the numbers of
transistors on a chip is doubling, so
that means that on a chip now there
are 1 million times the number of
Transistors as there was 40 years ago.
We not only see this in terms
of the number of transistors but
also in terms of computing speed.
The capacity of a hard disk and the number
of bytes, you get for a Dollar or Euro.
And so
this is showing this incredible growth.
If other fields would have
had the same growth of data,
we would see very surprising things.
For example, if I take the train.
From Eindhoven to Amsterdam, 40 years ago,
this would take approximately 1.5 hours.
The question is now, if transportation
would have followed more Moore's law,
how fast would we be able to go from
Eindhoven to Amsterdam by train today?
Please think about this question.
The answer to the question can
be computed in a very easy way.
We take one and a half hours times
60 minutes times 60 seconds and
divide it by 2 to the power 20.
And we would see that today we would
only need 5 milliseconds to travel
from Eindhoven to Amsterdam.
We can look at another example,
do exactly the same calculation.
If we would fly, from Amsterdam to
New York 40 years ago
it would take seven hours.
How long would it take today,
if transportation would
have followed Moore's law?
We can do exactly the same calculation.
We take the number of hours.
Times 60 minutes, times 60 seconds,
divided by 2 to the power 20.
And we would see that
only in 24 milliseconds,
we would be able to fly
from Amsterdam to New York.
As I said, the capacity on the hard
disk is also growing exponentially.
And also the costs per
byte are also
decreasing exponentially.
So what does this mean?
Let's compare it to fuel consumption.
If 40 years ago, we needed 4000 liters of
petrol to drive a car around the world,
how much petrol would we need today if
we would have followed Moore's Law?
The answer to this question.
Can be computed in exactly
the same way.
We take 4000 liters divided by 2 to
the power 20 and we would see that 4
milliliters of petrol would be sufficient
to travel all around the world.
These examples are showing
the incredible, growth of the data and
why people talk about Big Data.
The challenge today is not
to generate more data, but
the challenge today is to turn
this data into real value.
And this is a crucial topic.
People often talk about
the four V's of Big Data.
The first V.
I just explained that is the v of Volume.
So we are generating incredible amounts of
data, but that's not the only challenge.
The second challenge is Velocity.
We are not only generating large
amounts of data, data is
continuously being added.
And things are changing very rapidly.
So, velocity is the second challenge.
The third challenge is Variety.
So it's not one type of data.
We are confronted with many
different types of data.
Ranging from text,
to images, to audit trails.
And we need to combine all these
different sources of information.
Last but not least,
a problem of Big Data is Veracity.
And that means, that you can not be
completely sure that what you have
recorded is completely accurate.
For example, your shaving device of the
future will have an Internet connection.
Somebody has bought that shaving device.
And we are recording events from
that device, how it is being used.
But can we be sure that the person
who purchased the shaving
device is the actual person using it?
That is a kind of uncertainty that you see
if you collect data in a very large scale.
And you need to be able to deal with that.
I just spoke a lot about Big Data,
but data doesn't have to
be big to be challenging.
Data analytics questions
are everywhere and
that is why there is a very urgent
demand for data scientists.
So, what do these data scientists do?
What is their profession?
What is their task?
Well, their goal is to collect,
analyze, and
interpret data from a variety of sources.
I've given you already several examples.
That is why this will become a very
important profession in the future.
And the main goal is to
turn data into value.
And in this course,
we will focus on this particularity,
If you look at data science there
are 4 generic data science questions,
that you can ask in any situation.
The first data science
question is the question.
What happened?
If we see a bottle neck, if we see
deviations, we record event data and
we can actually,
see that these things have happened.
Then the second logical question,
is to ask yourself.
Why did it happen?
Why was there this delay?
Why did people deviate
from the expected path?
These things are just about the past, but
of course data science also aims to
answer questions about the future.
So, if you look at the future.
You also ask yourself the question,
what will happen?
What can we learn from historic
information to make predictions,
about what is happening at this
point in time. And then last, but
not least,
the fourth question of data science.
Is to ask yourself,
what is the best that can happen?
So, you want to use analytics
to recommend certain things that
will improve a situation.
Remove a bottleneck.
Make sure that people don't deviate or
provide a better service.
So these are the four questions
of data science.
And if we look for
example at the care flows in
a hospital we can as ourselves
some of these questions.
So for example, a hospital you
could ask yourself the question.
Why do patients have to wait so long?
What is causing these delays?
Do doctors follow the guidelines?
We have been doing a lot of analysis
in hospitals, and we see that
different doctors typically, process
things in a completely different way.
So why does one person do something
different than another person?
Can we predict waiting times for patients?
Can we predict how much
staff we will need tomorrow?
And last but not least,
very important in health care,
how can we reduce costs
without sacrificing quality?
So these questions are at, a level
of what we call a business process.
But even if you look at
the technical device, like for
example an X-ray machine in
exactly the same hospital,
we can also see that this X-ray
machine is generating lots of data.
And again, we can ask all
kinds of questions which you
can answer by analysing
this data carefully.
So for example.
How are the X-ray machines,
really used in the field?
There's a very important, question for
the people making these machines.
Why and
when do X-ray machines malfunction?
When do they break down, and why?
Which components should be replaced?
The machine doesn't work anymore.
Can we generate
diagnostic information telling
us which component is broken, so
that an engineer can go to the device and
repair it instantly.
Can we predict,
whether a machine will break down?
And last but not least, can we learn from
existing problems,
which parts need to be improved?
So these,
are all Data science questions and
you need very different skills to
address all of these questions.
So this picture tries to summarize
the various skills that are important for
data science.
There are obvious candidates
like Statistics and Data Mining.
You also need to be able to
visualize large amounts of data.
You need to be able to deal with
incredibly large databases.
But that's not the only thing.
You also need,
to have knowledge of social sciences to
talk about things like ethics and privacy.
You need to think about the value of data,
how you can extract value from it.
So Industrial Engineering
is also important.
And last but not least, and
that the core topic of this course,
you want to apply Process Mining
techniques to these data, to learn and
improve processes in the way
that I just described.
So the importance of Data science,
hopefully is obvious.
Many people say the Data scientist will
be the most sexy job of this century.
And that is why in Eindhoven we have
started The Data Science Center Eindhoven,
which groups specialists in the area.
And educate students in this exciting
new topic.
So far, I've been mainly talk about
Data science in a very general sense.
This course is about Data science,
but in particular, we will focus on
the analysis on process is based on data.
Processes are key.
You don't want to improve data.
You want to improve processes.
They are the thing that matter.
Not the data.
Not the software.
It's also different from data mining.
We are not interested in just isolated
decisions or low level patterns.
We are interested in improving
end-to-end processes.
That is a key thing.
So if you take this Process-centric
view on data science, and we
return to the examples that I gave before,
we can see that in a hospital setting,
there are many process related questions
that we can ask about care flows.
If we go to an X-ray machine,
we can see that in such a machine
there are many processes unfolding.
And you would like to analyze and
understand them.
And they are generating
terrabytes of data.
So we have a rich
source of information to do so.
So the focus of this course is on
the interplay between event data and
processes and process models.
And that is what the topic
of process mining, or
some people refer to it as business
process intelligence, is all about.
And so that is what we will focus
on in the next couple of weeks.
Let me sketch some use
cases for process mining.
The first use case is to
ask yourself the question,
what is the process that
people really follow?
What do they really do?
Not what they tell they do,
but what do they really do?
What are the bottlenecks?
Where are they?
What is causing them?
Where and why, do people or
machines deviate from an expected or
an idealized process?
These are key questions and
these are just a few examples.
There are many more examples.
What are the highways in my process?
Which factors are influencing
a bottleneck, etcetera.
And so these are the questions that we
will focus on in the next couple of weeks.
So, Process Mining is
Data Science in Action.
We are looking at
the dynamics of machines and
business processes and
try to learn from them and improve them.
So, if you want to read more about
this topic of Process Mining,
I would advise you to read chapter one of
the process mining book, and you will
will be able to
learn much more about this.
Thank you for watching and
hope to see you soon.
[MUSIC]