[MUSIC]
Welcome to this lecture.
Today we will focus on learning dependency
graphs using frequencies as input.
So this is a picture that I briefly
showed in the last lecture.
So we are now looking at a mining
approach that is using multiple phases.
And the first phase is
learning the dependency graph.
The approach that we sketch is
inspired by the heuristic miner, but
many mining techniques use
these two types of phases.
Also many of the commercial mining tools,
they use algorithms that actually just
show dependency graph and nothing more.
So, let's look at the problem
of learning a dependency graph.
So as a running example
I will use the C-net.
We have seen the C-net notation
in the last lecture, so
we have activities, we have dependencies
between different activities.
And every activity can have input and
output bindings that can be used
to model ANDs and ORs and XORs and
all kinds of routing constructs.
So, if we take this C-net model and
we would generate a simulation from it and
we would add some outliers.
Then this would be,
a possible log that we could get.
Note that deliberately there are two
traces in this event log a,b,e and
a,c,e which do not correspond to
valid binding sequences of the C-net.
But for all the other traces they
correspond to valid binding sequences.
So for example the trace that starts
with an e starts with an a and
ends with an e,
is one of these possible traces.
So, if we would take this event log and
apply the Alpha algorithm to it,
the Alpha algorithm would
have all kind of problems.
And here you see the model,
that it returns.
First of all, activity d is unconnected
to all the other activities.
Moreover, b and c always need to be
executed according to the model.
Whereas if we look at the event log,
that is clearly not the case,
because we can just do a,e.
Which is definitely not possible
according to this model.
So if we are using something like
the heuristic miner or
these are types of techniques.
They will not have these problems.
One of the important ingredients is that
we take into account frequencies and
only consider the causalities
which are important.
So here we see a formula
that counts the number of
times that a was followed
by b somewhere in the log.
So we sum over all traces.
And then within a trace we see how
many times a is followed by b.
So if we do that, we can count
the so-called direct succession.
So here you see an event log.
And for example, if you would look at
a and c, you can see that a is followed
directly by c 11 times in this event log.
So it's similar to what we were
using in the Alpha algorithm.
But there we were just looking at
whether something was followed by
something else at some
position in the log.
But now we look at how
frequent this is happening.
And we are using more information now.
So, one of the ingredients for learning
the dependency graph is direct succession.
How many times did one activity
follow another activity?
But we will also look at
a more sophisticated measure,
the so-called dependency measure,
which aims to discover causality.
If we have a model that
has concurrency in it,
accidentally things will
follow one another.
But we should not confuse
them with causalities.
So if you look at the formula that
you see here at the bottom, if a and
b are different.
We count how many times
is a followed by b,
minus the number of times
that b is followed by a.
And we divide that by the sum
of these two numbers plus 1.
And in this way we always get
a number between 0 and 1.
If the number is close to 1,
there is a very strong causality.
If the number is negative or
the number is close to 0, there is
a weak causality in that direction.
What this formula also shows you is that
we have a special case where a equals b.
Because, if we apply the formula that I
just mentioned to the situation where
a equals b, it would always yield 0.
And that's why you have a special formula.
It simply counts how many
times is a followed by itself,
divided by this number plus 1.
And again,
we get a number between 0 and 1.
The higher the number,
the more likely it is that there
is a dependency, a causality.
So what we see on this
slide is an example of
an arc in such a dependency graph,
annotated with two numbers.
The first number indicated in red,
45, indicates
how many times a was directly
followed by b somewhere in the log.
The other value,
indicated in blue, is the dependency
measure that we have just defined.
Right, so it's, it's computed using
the formula that we have seen earlier.
So let's take a look at these two numbers
in a set of specific situations.
So and in each situation we
will need to consider a threshold.
And both of these values, so
the value in red and the value in blue,
have to be above a certain threshold for
the arc to be included.
So we remove all arcs that do
not meet this requirement.
So, as I said, we look at a set of
patterns and see how this plays out.
So consider that we have a process
model where a is followed by b and
we see this 10 times.
So this picture is a bit misleading
because I am showing you a Petri net
to describe a set of traces.
So here we have 10 traces.
Where somewhere in the trace,
a is directly followed by b.
So, if we count the number of times that
a is followed by b, we get a number 10.
So, if we now apply the formula
of the dependency measure,
we get 10 minus 0 divided
by 10 plus 0 plus 1 is 11.
So the dependency measure between a and
b is 10 divided by 11.
If we look at the other direction, b is
never followed by a, so this number is 0.
And if we compute a dependency
measure between b and
a, so in the reverse direction.
We get a negative number,
namely minus 10 divided by 11.
So in this case because for
the connection between a and
b we meet both thresholds we say that
we want to include this causality.
So then we get this situation.
So the arc indicated in red is an arc that
meets the requirements of the thresholds.
So in this slide it shows that
we are now using a threshold of,
that a should be directly
followed by b at least once.
That is satisfied,
because we have seen it ten times, and
the dependency measure
should be at least half.
And in this case it's 0.9.
So this arc is definitely present.
Let's take a look at an XOR-split.
So, what we see now is
we see much more numbers.
So, the traces that we look at there
are a traces, where a is followed by b.
And there are two traces
where a is followed by c.
And then we can apply the formula
that has been described before,
and these are all the numbers that we get.
For example, a is followed by b eight times.
And if we look at the dependency
measure between a and
b we take 8 minus 0 divided
by 8 plus 0 plus 1 is 9.
So we get the dependency between a and
b is 8 divided by 9.
So, again, we can look at what are the
connections that meet the threshold.
And then we find that there is indeed
a connection between a and b and
between a and c.
Just as we expected.
So, in the dependency graph,
we add these two red arcs and
the numbers are the numbers
that we have computed before.
And so a is followed by b, eight times,
and a is followed by c two times.
And the dependency measures
are indicated in blue here.
And they all meet the threshold.
The XOR-join is very similar.
So, what you now see is,
again, a computation.
We look at the traces, a traces,
where a is followed by c,
two traces where b is followed by c,
and these are the numbers that we get.
And again we find that there are only
two connections that meet the threshold.
The connection between a and c and
the connection between b and c.
And again we add these arcs, the red arcs,
because they meet the two thresholds
that have been described before.
Let's take a look at concurrency.
We take the AND-split pattern,
now we look at traces where
a is followed by b and c, but sometimes
c is first and sometimes b is first.
And assume an evenly distributed log, so
we see as many traces a, b,
c as we see traces a, c, b.
And then these
are the numbers that we get.
Again we can simply apply the, the,
the two formulas that we have seen before.
And what we see is that indeed there
is a connection between a and b.
There is a connection between a and c.
What is very important to see here
is that if we look at the log,
b is five times followed by c.
And c is five times followed by b.
Because they are concurrent.
They can happen in any order.
So b and c follow one another, but
we don't want to create
a connection between them.
So that's why we need
the dependency measure.
The dependency measure here.
For example, if you look at
the connection between b and
c, we can see that the dependency
measure is 0 divided by 11.
Because we have 5 minus 5
divided by 5 plus 5 plus 1.
So we just fill out the formula and
we get 0 divided by 11.
So we know that there is no relationship,
no dependency between b and c.
because it doesn't meet the threshold.
So in this graph it's very
important to see that there is
no connection between b and c.
Because these connections do
not meet the threshold b and
c follow one another but
they are concurrent.
That's why we do not want
to see this connection.
The AND-join pattern is exactly the same
as you've seen numbers very similar to
what we have seen before.
We can fill out a formula and
get the numbers that you see here.
Again it's crucial that you
see that there should not
be a connection between a and b although
they follow each other five times.
And that is because if
we fill out the formula for
the dependence measure, in this case
we get 0 rather than some high number.
So we we approve
the connection between a and
c, and b and c, but
not between a and b, or b and a.
And this is, again, an illustration why we
need to have this dependency measure.
And these are the connections that we get
in the corresponding dependency graph.
So far we only consider the situation
where the two activities that we
were comparing were different activities.
Now for the loop pattern, we look at
a situation where one activity
should be connected to itself because
it is involved in some kind of loop.
So take a look at this Petri net
where we see a self loop involving b.
And, if we look at the corresponding traces
it's possible corresponding traces we can
see ac.
We can see abc.
But we can also see abbc.
So, in this small event log
that we will consider.
We assume for
example that abbc happens three times.
And so one activity follows itself.
If we apply the normal formula to this,
we would get a dependency measure of 0.
So we would never have
a connection of b with itself.
But as you can see from this example,
sometimes this is needed if
we are involved in a loop.
So, let's compute the measures for
this small event log.
The numbers that you see here in red,
they are exactly computed in
the way we have seen before.
The values that you see here in blue.
They correspond to
measures that are computed using
this special formula for loops.
So if we look at a, the dependency measure
of a with itself, it is 0 divided by 1.
And so, there is no connection
between a and itself.
If we look, however at b, b follows
itself three times in the event log.
And the dependency measure of b
with itself is 3 divided by 0.
And the reason is that if we apply the
formula we get 3 divided by 3 plus 1 is 4.
So this is how we can capture
the fact that there is a loop.
So we approve the connections including
the self loop involving b and
this is why we need to have this special
formula, because otherwise we would
lose this connection between b and
it would not be connected to the rest.
So if we apply all the formulas,
this is the dependency graph that we see.
And especially
the connection between b and
itself is important that you
understand how this was computed.
It meets the thresholds,
so we add the self-loop.
Let's take a look at the example
that we have seen before.
So, here we have the log including
two outliers and we can compute
how many times one activity is followed
by another, as you can see here.
So, the question is now
to see whether you
understand this dependency
measure given this event log.
What is the dependency measure for
the connection between a and b?
And what is the connection and
the value of the dependency measure of
the connection between d and itself?
So, take a moment to think about this.
This is the answer, it is showing all
the dependency measures computed for
all activity pairs.
And it is just computed by applying the
formula that we have described before.
So if we zoom in to the two activities.
The two dependency measures
that I've asked for.
The connection between a and
b and, and d and itself.
Then we can simply look
up the values in how many
times one activity was
followed by the other.
And we can apply the formula.
And we get this value.
If we look at how many times d was
followed by itself, we can look that up.
And we apply the second formula.
And then we get the number
that you can see here.
So this shows how you can
compute the dependency measures.
So, we have these thresholds.
There is a threshold for the number
of times that an activity should be
followed by another activity and
the strength of the dependency.
If both meet the thresholds,
arcs are included.
So, if we use the thresholds where
we set the threshold rather low,
then all of the connections that you
see here in the graph will be included.
If we increase the threshold a bit so
we have more stricter requirements
with respect to the dependency measure
and the frequency.
Then we can see that two
arcs are disappearing.
So compared to the previous slide,
we, for
example, now see that the self
loop involving d has disappeared.
And there is no longer a connection
between the first activity and
the last activity.
And so by playing with these thresholds
we can make the dependency graph simpler.
So what is the algorithm?
So first we set thresholds then
we count direct successions.
Then we compute the dependency measures
using the two formulas discussed and
then we draw the dependency
graph including only the arcs
that meet both thresholds and
then we get the dependency graph.
Please practice this yourself on small
example logs to see whether you
really understand how it works.
As I mentioned before many
algorithms use something very
similar to dependency graphs.
If you look at Disco,
you can think of the models that you see
as dependency graphs rather
than something more explicit,
having more explicit semantics like
a Petri net or a BPMN model.
So if you look at Disco,
you can play with the threshold.
So if you set the threshold very low,
as indicated high here,
you will see that all
the arcs are included.
If you then move the slider down you
will see that more and more connections
do not meet the thresholds and disappear.
So the model gets simpler and simpler.
So this is using exactly the same type
of ideas, although the underlying
algorithms are different than the things
that we have seen in this lecture.
So the next step that we will
look at in the next lecture
is once we have this dependency graph,
how can we
compute the split and
join behavior of all of these nodes.
So we aim at creating so called C-nets.
If you want to read more
about this in chapter six you
can read everything about
learning these dependency graphs.
Thank you for watching,
and hope to see you soon.
[MUSIC]