[MUSIC]
Welcome to this lecture.
In this course, we aim to show a variety
of process discovery techniques.
Today we will show that
transition systems can
often be folded in much more compact
process models that allow for concurrency.
In the last lecture we introduced
a two faced approach using regions.
The first lecture we focused on
constructing the transition system,
now we will focus on converting
the transition system into a Petri net,
thereby discovering concurrency.
So what's the basic idea?
The basic idea is that in
the transition system,
we identify a subset of states
that correspond exactly to a place.
And by doing this, we introduce places
that are like constraints on the behavior,
that capture the behavior
including concurrency.
So it may be the case that we have
a transition system with thousands of
states, and
by applying region theory we reduce it to
a Petri net with a very
small number of places.
So let's look at the definition of
the understanding of what
a state-based region is.
The idea is that we capture a set of states
and that if we look at the states and we
look at the corresponding arrows entering
the region, exiting the region, and
that remain inside or that remain outside,
we want the following property to hold.
For example all a activities,
if one of them is entering
as is the case here,
then all a arrows should enter the region.
They cannot exit, and
they cannot be inside and remain inside.
The same holds for b.
If one b is entering,
then all b's should enter.
If we look at c, c is exiting.
So if there is one c arrow
going out of the region,
then all c arrows should go out of
the region, and the same holds for d.
The other activities, they do not
cross the boundary of such a region.
So whenever there is consensus,
on entering, exiting, and
not crossing, if we find a set of
states that has these properties,
then we know that that is a region, and
that it potentially corresponds to
a place in the corresponding Petri net.
So the starting point as as mentioned
before is a transition system.
In the examples we will, always assume
that we have one initial state.
That is not necessarily always
the case but we can always add
an artificial start activity to ensure
that there is one initial state.
Typically we'll also prefer
to have one final state.
But this is not really a limitation of
the techniques that we are talking about.
All states in the transition system,
of course, need to be reachable.
So, here, we see the definition
that I mentioned before.
So if one a is exiting,
all a's are exiting.
If one a is entering,
then all a transitions should be entering.
If one a does not cross
the boundary of a region,
no a's should be allowed to
cross the boundary of a region.
And that should hold for all activities.
So that's the notion of a region.
It is best to just look at a number of
examples to really understand this notion.
So here the red states
together form a region.
There is one a arc, and
that a arc is entering.
So there is agreement on the a arc.
If we look at the b arcs,
in this diagram you can see four.
Then all the b arcs are going from
a red state to an uncolored state.
So they are all exiting.
So there is consensus on the exiting of b.
If you look at c, d and
e, they are either inside and
remain inside or they are outside and
remain outside, so they are not crossing.
So later we will see that this actually
corresponds to a place where transition
a is putting a token into, and
transition b is taking a token from.
We can look at another region.
Here, again, we see four states, and
if you look at these four states,
they form a region where
a is not crossing,
b is entering, e is exiting,
c and d do not cross.
Later we will see that this
corresponds to the place connecting b
to the final transition.
This is another region.
Now it consists of just a single state.
A is exiting the rest does not cross.
What we see if we look at this
particular region is that it
contains the initial state.
If that is the case we will mark
the corresponding place with a token.
So all regions that correspond,
that contain the initial state,
they correspond to a marked place,
that initially has one token.
This is another region, now d is exiting,
a is entering, the rest does not cross.
Let us now take a look at
something that is not a region so
that we have a good
understanding of the notion.
If we look at this example with
the three states colored red,
together they do not form
a region because we see b
arcs that are exiting,
every cb arcs that are not crossing.
So there is no consensus with
respect to the b transitions.
There's also no consensus
with respect to c and d.
Some arcs are exiting,
some of them are not crossing.
So this is not a region.
Also this is not a region,
for very similar reasons.
If we just take a look at these
two states, then we see a b
that is exiting, but
we also see b's that are not crossing.
The same holds for c and d.
So this is not a region.
So there may be multiple regions
on this small transition system.
You can see here in the different
colors the different regions.
But any combination of two
regions is again a region.
And so
the number of regions seems to explode.
So, if we selectively
choose the right regions we
get a corresponding nice process
model as you can see here.
But the question is,
how to select the right regions?
To really understand the fact that
we need to select the right regions,
it is good to look at some examples and
count the number of regions.
So take a look at this Petri net, where we
have a number of concurrent activities.
We can construct the reachability graph.
We can all imagine what
the reachability graph looks like.
How many regions does
this reachability graph,
which is a transition system,
actually have?
Take a moment to think about it.
Now let's take a look at the answer.
So there are two to the power n states
if there are n concurrent activities.
Then, if we look at the regions,
we cannot have the situation,
which is illustrated here.
Where for example two activities
are both exiting, a and b.
Because if we are in this situation,
then we also know that there will be
a's and b's that are not crossing.
So at most, one transition label can be
crossing the boundary of the region.
So if we use this reasoning, then we
can see that there are n ways to split
the states into two groups and each of
these two groups correspond to a region.
Also the empty set,
the set consisting of no states, and
the set consisting of all states,
they are regions.
So we get 2 times n plus 1, regions
that are possible in this situation.
So this is quite okay.
However let us now look
at the next question.
Now we have a sequence of n activities,
to there are n plus 1 states before,
after, and in between.
So how many regions does
the reachability graph,
which is a transition system of
this particular Petri net, have?
Again, take a moment to think about this.
The answer is that every subset of
states corresponds to a region.
So you have 2 to the power
n plus 1 possible regions.
Many of these regions look
redundant if we convert them
back to places in the Petri net.
Any combination of states,
corresponds to a region.
So, in this particular example if you
would take a look at ten activities,
executed in sequence,
we have more than 2,000 possible regions.
So imagine a Petri net with
more than 2,000 places just to
describe a sequence of ten activities.
It shows that we need to reduce the number
of regions that we are looking at and
therefore, we only consider minimal,
non-trivial regions.
So let us define these notions.
We only include non-trivial,
minimal regions.
First of all, we discard the so called
trivial regions, the empty set of states,
and the set of all states,
they are regions by definition, but
they carry no information whatsoever,
so we will not consider these.
Moreover, if a region
can be decomposed into
smaller non-trivial regions, then we
will not consider the higher region.
Okay.
because otherwise we get
an explosion of combinations.
Let's take a look what
this actually means.
So if we for
example first look at our example and
we look at trivial regions, then the set
of all states and the empty set of states,
they are both regions but they are
trivial, so we will never consider them.
To understand the notion
of minimal regions we
first need to understand
the notion of a compliment.
In this case we have the region
consisting of one blue state.
If we take all states minus this blue
state, this is the so-called complement,
indicated here by the red states, then
by definition that is also the region.
So if we have a region then all the states
minus this region is again a region.
So if we understand
the notion of a complement,
we can now try to understand why
we only consider minimal regions.
If we have a larger region, and
we have a smaller region contained
in it, and we take the difference
between the larger region and
the smaller region, then the result,
by definition, is again a region.
If we again take a look at this
region indicated here in yellow,
then the question,
is this a minimal region?
Does it contain other regions?
And if we look closely, we can see that
the last state, is again a region.
So, we have the, the yellow region,
we have the green region, and again, if we
take the difference between the larger and
the smaller one, we again get a region.
So this means that we can break down
larger regions into smaller regions and
if we can no longer identify nontrivial
regions in them, they are minimal.
And the idea is that in all of our
reasoning we will only consider minimal
regions, in order to reduce
an explosion of the number of
places in the Petri net.
So in our running example, if we look at
all the minimal regions they are indicated
here, and if you convert them into places
we get the corresponding Petri net.
So, how does it work exactly?
For each transition label
in the transition system,
we add a transition to
the corresponding Petri net.
There may be many transitions in
the transition system that have
the same label but they're all
mapped onto the same transition.
Then we compute the minimal
non trivial regions.
We're just breaking down regions into
smaller parts until they can no longer be
further decomposed.
Then each of these minimal non-trivial
regions is converted into a place in
the Petri net, and the inputs and
outputs are clear by looking at what
is entering and exiting the region.
And we add a token to each place
that corresponds to a region,
that contains the initial state.
So if we do that the result
is a minimal saturated net.
And in our example it looks like this.
So this is exactly the Petri net
that you would like to have.
So ProM supports
the construction of regions.
And a simple test to see whether it
works well is that we take a Petri net.
We construct the corresponding
reachability graph,
using the techniques that we
saw in the previous lecture.
And we get a reachability graph,
which in this case is very large.
And so here we see the top part,
we can zoom out a bit.
And we can see that there are many states.
There are more than 1000 states, and
it's impossible to visualize
this in a proper way.
So this is a transition system that
is very large and very complicated.
But if we now apply state based
regions to this transition system and
apply the algorithm just described, then
this is the Petri net that we rediscover.
So, from this mess of all these states and
all these transitions we are able to
rediscovered the concurrency that
was there in the first place.
So let us take a look at another example.
So here we see a log,
with the traces indicated.
We have seen this in the context
of the Alpha algorithm.
If we use the approach just described, so
we first construct a transition system.
Then we take this transition system and
apply state-based regions to it,
then this is the Petri net that we get.
And this is the Petri net which is
exactly the same as we would find if we
would apply the Alpha algorithm.
Note that again we have these two
redundant places towards the end of
the process model.
There are, however, also situations
where state based regions really
produce a better result than
the Alpha algorithm would do.
So for example if we take a look at
this log, we see the sequences a,
c, and d, b, c, and e.
If we create the transition
system it looks like this.
We are using the past with
a multiset abstraction.
And now if we compute the regions for
this example and convert this
into places of the corresponding
Petri net, then we discover this.
And please note the two highlighted
places, these are places
that capture the causality between a and
d, and the causality between b and
e, even though a and b and b and
e never follow one another.
So the Alpha algorithm would produce
a model that is too general in
this situation, but using regions,
we can find the right model.
In the next lecture, we will focus on
the limitations of this two-step approach.
So we will look at under which
circumstances will it not work, and
what are possible extensions
that can be used.
We are still in Chapter 6,
where we consider all these more
advanced process discovery techniques.
Thank you for watching,
and hope to see you soon.
[MUSIC]