[MUSIC]
Welcome to this lecture of the course on
process mining, data science in action.
Today we will show that there are many
ways to construct a transition system,
based on an event log.
This will be used for process discovery,
based on state-based regions.
In earlier lectures, we have seen many
different process discovery algorithms.
We started by looking at
the Alpha algorithm, and
we showed that it is
possible to discover places,
that capture concurrency, sequences,
loops, and all of these types of things.
After that we looked at heuristic mining,
consisting of two steps building a
dependency graph and, then building
a C-net capturing the nature of splits and
joins also,
being able to handle infrequent behavior.
We also looked at various tools, like for
example the fuzzy miner in ProM.
And a disco tool,
which also provides different ways
of discovering process models.
Today we will look at
another two-phase approach.
This approach is based on state-based
regions, and in the first step we create
a transition system from an event log, and
that will be the focus of this lecture.
After building the transition system,
we convert it to a Petri net
by detecting concurrency.
The result is a Petri net, and if we want
we can translate it to another language
like, for example, BPMN, so
this is the approach that we will look at.
In the next lecture we will
zoom in a lot of detail,
into the discovery of places using the
notion of so called state-based regions.
Here you see an illustration of that,
the basic idea is that a set of states in
the transition system,
corresponds to a place in the Petri net.
But today, we will focus on first
creating the transition system.
So from an event log, we want to
automatically create a transition system,
which can be compared to
the reachability graph of a Petri net.
So how does it work?
An event log consists of traces and
in every trace,
we can look at any of the positions.
So for example, here in this trace,
we look at the position between e and f.
In the longer trace,
it starts with a and ends with i.
So what is the state that this case
is in if it's in between e and f?
Well there are many ways of
defining such a state notion.
We can for example look at the past, and
consider all the activities that have
happened before, and also their order.
And now in the state you see annotated
what the description of that state is.
We can also look at the future,
and it may sound very odd, but
if we have complete traces and
we look at the position in such a trace,
we know what the future of
the case is going to be.
In this situation the next
step will be an f.
The step after that will be an a, etc.
So we can also characterize
the state where we are in,
by what is going to happen in the future,
and we can combine both.
So a state may be described by
what happened in the past, and
what will happen in the future.
So there are various ways of building
states of a transition system.
Once we have captured the states, it is
very easy to add the missing transitions.
If we do this it may be that we
have too many different states, and
that all states are more or
less unique or very infrequently visited,
so often we need to use abstractions.
If we use no abstraction, we look at
the full sequence, as you can see here.
So now if we look at the past,
both the order and
frequency of all activities matter.
But we can use an abstraction,
like for example the set abstraction
that captures the activities
that have happened in the past.
While we can ignore the order in which
these activities have been executed now so
for how many times.
So for example, now in the state
description we can not see that c and
d have been executed twice, and
we can tell nothing about the order.
We can also use the so-called multi-set
abstraction, if you now look at the state,
you can see that we capture how
many times every activity has been
executed in the past, but not their
order so, only the frequencies matter.
We can also use a time window,
an horizon of four events,
in this case we look at the four
events in the past, and
we can see that the state when
we are in between e and f for
this particular trace,
is determined by d c d e.
This is also called the k-tail, in this
case k is four of that particular state.
We can also a set abstraction, now we can
no longer so that d has happened twice and
we can no longer see the order,
in which things have happened.
We can also use the multiset abstraction,
combined with an horizon of four events.
And now we can see that
d has happened twice.
C has happened once.
E happened also once.
In the past four events, but
we cannot see the order.
So, different orderings of
the same multiset of activities,
will be mapped onto the same state.
We can also look into the future,
and look at the next two events.
In this case, we ignore the order,
so we can just see that,
in the next two steps, a and
f will happen, not knowing their order.
So there are different ways of capturing
the state, can be based on the past,
on the future or
a combination of these things.
We can use a set or
a multiset abstraction, and
we can look at just the last two,
three or four events.
Let's take a look at an example, and
that will also illustrate how we
capture the transitions and
the labels of the transitions.
So here we see an event log, that we have
seen several times before consisting of
the sequence a, b, c, d,
a, c, b, d and a, e, d.
And let's build a transition system,
using different types of abstractions.
So here we look at the complete prefixes,
so
for example it starts with the empty
prefix, then we do an a, and then we
end up in the state, which is described
by the sequence consisting of just a.
If we then take a b,
we end up in the state, described by
the sequence a comma b, et cetera.
So this is based on the past, and
we care about the ordering
of the different activities.
This is known as the so called prefix
automaton and it's an abstraction
that we will frequently use
to build transition systems.
We can also look at the future,
it may be very counterintuitive,
as I mentioned before, but if we are at
a particular position in the log,
we know what is going to
happen to that trace.
So we can describe
the corresponding state,
by the events that will happen in
the future that is what you see here.
We can also look again at the past, and
then take a so-called multi set
abstraction, so now we no longer know
the order, but we know which activities
have happened and how many times.
What is interesting here is to look at the
state, labelled with a multi set a, b, c.
In this state, we do not know
whether first b has happened and
then c or the other way around,
they are both mapped onto the same state.
And again, we get a transition system
capturing the behavior that we
have seen in the log.
We can use a more rigorous extraction,
and just look at the last event.
So here, every state is described,
by the last event that was being executed.
We can also look at the next event,
this is, again, a transition
system which is able to replay the log,
it's also generalizing a bit.
And now every state is described,
by what the next step will be.
So in the initial state of
this transition system,
we see that we will always do an a.
So let's see whether you understand
the abstractions that have been discussed.
So here you see a more
complicated event log.
I also show a transition system.
So, what kind of
abstraction was being used?
Was it the set?
The multi-set, or
the sequence abstraction?
Did we look at the past,
or the future, or both?
So, take a moment to think about this.
The answer is that when building
this transition system,
the states are determined by the last
event that was being executed, and
then the corresponding activity net.
Let's take a look at another event log and
corresponding transition system.
Again there is the question what
kind of abstraction was used?
The answer is that we use an abstraction,
that only considered the last two events,
ignoring the ordering of
these two activities.
I've shown you several transition systems,
also when we were talking about
a reachability graph of a Petri net,
we were already talking
about transition systems.
You can see that the notation
varies slightly, and
it has to do whether we want to
put inscriptions in the states.
So, if you want to label or color the
states, we don't use these black dots, but
then we don't care about their labeling,
or we don't care about
coloring them in a particular way,
we will just show them as black dots and
we also have these two notations to show
final stage, but this is not relevant.
So I've shown you the basic mechanism
to build a transition system, but if we
look at an event log, events may have
many other attributes that can be used.
So for example,
an event may have a description of
the resource executing
the corresponding activity.
We may know the location of the event,
we may know the associated cost.
There can be all kind of attributes
associated to events, and
we can use them while building
the transition system.
So, for example, states may correspond
to resources rather than activities.
Also the transitions from
one state to another state,
may have a label that is not
a corresponding activity, but
is the corresponding resource or
the corresponding customer type.
We can also filter infrequent paths,
it's very easy to do that.
We just replay the log on
the transition system, and
leave out the paths that are not often
taken the same holds for activities.
So we can prune the transition system,
to remove infrequent or noisy behavior.
Once we have the transition system,
we may also want to postprocess it,
so in some cases for
readability we may want to remove
self loops in this case transition x.
Note that this will jeopardize fitness,
if the log was
perfectly fitting the transition system
before, it may no longer be the case.
We can also improve the diamond structure,
in this situation we have,
for example, activities a and b.
If we know,
that there is a choice between a and b and
after taking a we can still do b.
Then it is reasonable to assume that a and
b are concurrent, but that we
did not happen to see
the interleaving b followed by a.
So we can improve the diamond structure,
to later be able to discover concurrency.
We also may want to merge states
having similar inputs, or
merge states having similar
outputs as is shown here.
These are all ways of
generalizing the behavior,
to avoid that we have a transition
system that is over fitting.
So if we us ProM, we can take a log,
we can build a transition system by it.
And if we actually do this,
we can see that all the different
configuration choices that I've
mentioned before, you can actually take.
And the result is always a transition
system, and under most parameters,
it is guaranteed that transition system is
able to replay the log from beginning to
end, as you can see here.
Once you have a transition system,
we can apply so-called state-based regions
to create a corresponding process model.
And, this will be the topic
of the next lecture,
how to convert transition systems into
process models, for example, a Petri net.
If you would like to read more
about this particular approach,
it is described in chapter six.
Thank you for watching this lecture,
see you next time.
[MUSIC]