[MUSIC]
Glad to see you again.
After learning how to
build a dependency graph,
we now focus on learning the more
precise split join behavior.
In other words, we will learn how
we can discover a C-net based
on the dependency graph and the event log.
This is the picture that we
have been looking at before.
We now focus on the second phase.
So we first learned how to
learn the dependency graph.
Now we are going to learn a C-net.
And once we have a C-net annotated
with the split join semantics and
also with frequencies.
We can later visualize this easily
in terms of a BPMN diagram,
UML activity diagram, or whatever
notation people would like to see.
So the focus is now on learning C-nets.
So let's see what we have
done before.
We started from a log.
From a log we count how many times an
activity is followed by another activity.
Then we compute the dependency measure
using the formulas discussed in
the previous lecture.
Then we set thresholds.
And, based on the thresholds,
we get a graph.
And the higher we set the threshold,
the fewer connections we will get.
But at some point in time we are happy
with the dependency graph that we have.
And we use it as input for
learning C-nets.
So this is the output that we are after.
From the event log and
the dependency graph learning
a C-net annotated with input and
output bindings and frequencies of
activities of connections and of bindings.
So, the question is how to do this.
So we want to learn splits and
joins, how to find these.
We want to learn about frequencies,
how to count these frequencies and
that is what we will try to uncover.
So let's take a look at activity A.
Activity A has three output bindings.
Just e, which is not visible on
this slide, or b and c together, or
just d, these are the possible
binding that we, that we have.
If we look at d, what we would like
to discover based on this event log.
We would like to discover that
there are two input bindings.
Ones of one is just a.
The other is d.
That d triggers itself because there
can be a loop involving multiple d's.
On the output side of d,
we find two output bindings.
One involving just d,
to trigger the next iteration of d.
Or we go to the end.
We have an output binding involving e.
If we look at the last activity
in this graph then, again,
we see that there
are three input bindings.
Very symmetric to the,
to the start activity.
We see just a, b, and c or just d.
These are the three combinations
that we would like to discover.
So, if we take a look
at a particular path,
then we see it indicated in red here,
a binding sequence.
The valid binding sequence
that involves a, d, d, e.
And the frequencies of the activities,
of the bindings, and
of the connections are indicated here.
So how to discover these splits and
joints?
Well, there are two main types of
approaches that one can consider.
The first one is more heuristic based,
where you take a time window.
So for example, you take a time window
before the activity and you count how many
times certain activities that
are causally related to the activity.
How many times they appear.
We do the same for
a window of activities after
the activity we are interested in.
We again count what combinations
appear in this time window, just
considering the ones that are causally
related based on the dependency graph.
Based on counting these sets of input and
output activities,
we can determine the bindings.
Another approach,
which is more expensive and
less based on heuristics is that
you choose a particular variant
of this A activity that has a finite
number of things that one can consider.
And then we see whether the traces
can be replayed properly,
assuming particular input and
output bindings.
And then using certain goal function,
we take the best bindings.
It's a more expensive approach, but
it provides certain guarantees.
It's important to realize that these are
just two main approaches, and that many
variants are possible, and are being used
in both academic and commercial tools.
So let's take a look at the first
approach, which is based on heuristics.
Here we see an activity, a,
happening somewhere in a trace.
Then we can take a window before a.
We look at what are possible input
activities of this activity a,
and we look at what kind of combinations
appear in the various traces.
We do the same on the output side.
On the output side we count how many
of the output activities appear,
and in which type of combinations.
Based on this, we determine the input and
the output bindings.
So, it is best to explain
this using a small example.
So, assume that we take
a window of size four.
Before an activity and after an activity.
And in this diagram we
just focus on activity a.
And activity a if we look at
the dependency graph there
are two input activities b and c.
There are two output activities d and e.
The dependency graph doesn't
talk about bindings and
and's and or's and things like that.
That is what we would need to derive,
but now we scan a window of size four.
Before a and
we scan a window of size four after a.
And we count which combinations appear.
And if you take a look at this very
simple log that contains the fragment of
five different traces, then what you will
see is that there were three traces,
three situations where just B appeared
before a in this time window of four.
There were two traces
where just c appeared.
Before a in this time window of four.
We can also look on the output side and
here in every window of
four following a, both d and e happen.
So in total it happens five times.
So we have these two input bindings
happening three and two times and
we have this five times that
there is a single output binding.
So we can use this to annotate the graph.
Exploiting this information.
So now you should focus on
the arcs surrounding a.
And what you see is that now
it is indicated that there
are three times where a is
being triggered by b.
Just b.
There are two times where
c is triggering a.
Together they account for
the five times that a was executed.
So we can see that there is
an XOR-join in front of a.
Now we can look at the output side of a.
We have learned, using the time windows,
that a is always followed by d and e.
In different order.
So we have output binding and it was
activated five times, and so this is
the way that we can discover frequencies
and the split and join behavior.
Let's take a look at another example,
again we focus on activity a, so
we should do this separately for
every activity, but we focus on activity a.
And if we look at activity a.
We again look at the time windows
before a and the windows
after a and we count how many
times certain combinations appear.
In this particular log
consisting of five traces and
we can only see a fragment of them.
We see that there was one trace
where just b appeared before a.
There were two traces where
just c appeared before a and
there were two traces where both b and
c appeared.
So, what we see here is that is a kind
of OR-join on the input side of a.
We can also look at the output side and
there we see that there were two
traces with just d was following, and
there were three traces where both d and
e were following.
So we can again use this information to
create bindings, and this is the result.
So, again, in the middle, we see a.
It occurred five times,
as is indicated, but now, if
we look on the input side of a, we can see
that there are three possible bindings.
Just b, just c, or b and c.
And the frequencies of these
bindings are indicated.
On the output side,
there are two possible output bindings.
One is just d, and the other is d and
e together in some order.
And all the frequencies
are indicated here.
So now here is a question for you.
Again we look at the same situation.
We have a.
A has two input activities and
two output activities.
We see a fragment of a log and
the question to you is please determine
the input and output bindings
assuming again a window size of four.
So the answer to the question is
that if we look on the input side,
we see that it is always the same.
B and c always happen in this
time window of four before a.
So there is just one input binding
that it has a frequency of five.
If we look on the output side,
we will see that there are two situations,
two cases where just e is happening, and
three situations, three cases
where both d and e are happening.
So.
There are two output bindings, and
the frequencies are indicated here.
So if you put this in a diagram,
this is the result that we have.
So the diagram clearly
shows that a is an AND-join,
so b and
c need to happen before a can happen.
And if we look on the output side of a.
We can see that there are two
possible output bindings.
One is that just both d and
e will happen.
The other one is that just e happens, and
again the frequency are indicated.
They give an idea of what
are the main flows of the process.
So the algorithm that I just
described is very simplistic.
And several refinements are needed.
So first of all, what should one
do if there are no activities in
the window size that has been indicated?
You need to resolve this in some way.
Also, often in the dependency graph there
is the requirement that there is at
least one input and one output.
That's where you should relax
things to make sure that you get
at least one input and
at least one output.
One needs to filter for noise.
And so
if certain bindings are very frequent and
other bindings are very infrequent,
perhaps you want to
cut away the bindings that are very
infrequent to just show the main behavior.
I didn't talk about the fact
that there can be multiple a's.
So, a can follow itself.
It could also be that the activities
before and after happen multiple times.
So, we need to think about extensions
that deal with this problem of
repeating activities and
there are many ways to resolve this.
But all of these details are out
of the scope of this lecture, but
when you are interpreting the results,
it's important that you understand,
let's say how this works and
that there these kind of
subtle things that need to be considered.
The other approach,
uses a more rigorous, type of analysis.
So, there are only finitely many possible,
input and
output bindings for
a particular activity.
There is only a finite number
of activities, so there is only
a finite number of possible configurations
of input and output bindings.
So what you can do is you cam simply
explore all of these possibilities,
replay traces from beginning to end,
and check whether things fit.
And then,
then you can evaluate the quality
of a particular collection of input and
output bindings.
Later we will talk about
conformance checking.
And we will provide metrics for
all of these things.
It's important to realize that
it is not just about fitness.
It is also about other things like
precision, generalization and simplicity.
But the bottom line is that you can
simply try lots of possibilities,
evaluate them, and then pick the best one.
So to illustrate this a bit,
take a look at this fragment of a model,
where we have a with two inputs,
b and c, and two outputs, d and e.
What is the total number of possible a's.
If we look at the input bindings there
a three possible input bindings,
just b, just c, or
the combination of both.
So in principle, a can have multiple
bindings, but it should be in such a way
that at least one of these bindings is
covering each of the input connections.
So for every input connection,
there should at least be one
binding that includes it.
The same holds for the output side.
So for this very simple fragment of an a
with two input and two output bindings,
there are four times
four is 16 possible a's.
Possible activities a's based on
subsets of the total number
of possible bindings.
So this is a finite number.
We can do this for a.
We can do this for all the activities.
And then we get lots of possibilities.
And we can explore them and
check which is the best one.
So we can exhaustively
try all the combinations,
use replay as we have seen before
to see whether things actually fit.
Do the traces in the log correspond
to valid binding sequences?
And in the end, we take the best one.
And as I mentioned before it's not
just about fitness also precision,
generalization, and simplicity.
The concepts that have been discussed
before need to be taken into account.
This may be very time consuming but
there are all kinds of ways of doing
it smarter and more efficient.
You can take a random selection of
bindings and pick the best one.
You can also use more
sophisticated algorithms.
Using the genetic approach where you
take good collections of bindings,
evaluate them and
if they don't fit you just change a bit to
gradually improve a generation of models
until you have the desired results.
But these concepts will be
discussed in later lectures.
So now we have a complete approach.
First we learned the dependency graph.
Then we learned the split and
join behavior.
And we can annotate
models with frequencies.
So if you look at the heuristic minor
you see many different settings that you
can set.
And they are related to the thresholds and
to the choices that we
have discussed before.
Once you run the heuristic miner
you see a model like this.
And in this visualization you cannot
see the split/join behavior, but
there are also visualizations that
show show the split/join behavior.
You can even show the frequencies,
as you can see here.
And so
everything that we have been talking about
is implemented in many
of the process mining algorithms that
you can use in a practical setting.
If you would like to learn
more about these advanced
process discovery techniques that go
far beyond the basic Alpha algorithm.
You can read more about
this in chapter six.
Thank you for watching this lecture.
See you next time.
[MUSIC]