[MUSIC]
Welcome to this lecture of the course on
Process Mining: Data Science in Action.
Today we focus on the representation
used during discovery.
We can use different modeling notations to
present discovered processes to end users.
However, this is independent of
the representation used when searching for
a process that best explains
the observed event data.
Earlier, we have been taking about
desire lines as a metaphor for
process mining and process discovery.
Here you see a picture with my daughter
cycling over such a desire line.
They indicate what people really do.
Here you see another desire line.
It's taken at the campus of
Tsinghua University in Beijing.
And we see a desire line here
that has been building over time.
Because people were leaving traces
of the things that they did.
As you can clearly see from the sign,
they are violating a rule, but there is
evidence to show what has really happened.
This metaphor of desire
lines allows us to
talk about representational
bias of process mining.
Let's take a look.
The lines here indicate
the behavior that we have observed.
Now given this observed behavior, we would
like to create a model of the behaviors
that we have seen that is also
predictive for things into the future.
And so it's a description of what
we have seen in the past, and
says something about what we
can expect in the future.
Well, so we tried to convert
what we have seen into a model.
And what is indicated here.
For example, the circular building blocks,
is that we tried to capture the behavior
that we have seen in terms of a model.
So this model seems to be a good
description of what we have seen.
However, we can take
a look at this situation.
Where the yellow line indicates
a behavior that is violating the model.
In other words,
the model doesn't allow for this behavior.
But it happened anyway.
So, is this an outlier?
Or, should we modify
our model to allow for
this particular behavior that
does not fit into the model?
So, what you see here is that we
can build an alternative model
that now has much more detail
that allows for the yellow line.
But is this model overfitting?
Before we had the outlier, which was
not possible according to the model.
Now we have adapted this
model to the outlier.
So, this is related to the four forces
that we have been talking about before.
We can also have a model that is
completely underfitting, that allows for
any behavior that is somewhere
there in the middle.
So this is an underfitting model.
So if we look at these two models, we can
see an over and an underfitting model.
But that's not the thing that
we are going to talk about.
Today, we are going to talk
about representations that we
use to capture these models.
So, before we were using circles and
these other objects.
But what would happen if our basic
building blocks our modeling language.
Does not allow for these circles,
and these bars, and
these triangles, but also it only
allows for this particular shape.
We then have a different modeling language
and we cannot capture exactly the same
things, and we are tempted to capture
the behavior in a particular way.
So this is what
representational bias is about.
It impacts the search space of
process discovery techniques.
Let's take a look at an example
to make this more clear.
So this is a Petri net and
a Petri net has no problems
whatsoever to capture concurrency.
So if you have a process discovery
technique using Petri nets natively,
the discovery technique will be
tempted to discover concurrency.
However, if we would use as
a representation a transition system.
This is the transition system
corresponding to the same process.
And we are only seeing
a tiny fraction of it.
It has many different states and
many different transitions because it is
not able to capture concurrency natively.
So when we use this representation,
discovering concurrency will be
much more difficult.
So the representation is influencing
how we can discover processes and
there are many possible languages that
we internally use for process discovery.
We've seen Petri nets,
we can look at workflow nets,
we can look at transition systems.
Later we will look at BPMN diagrams.
And there are many other
notations that you can see.
The notations that you see
here are just a few of
the process modelling
languages that are out there.
So the choice of language will
influence how our discovery
process will actually be conducted and
it will influence the outcome.
So before, with the transition system,
I already indicated that
to discover concurrency, you need to have
a notation that allows for concurrency.
So let us elaborate a bit about this.
Many things in real life are concurrent.
If we look at an office.
If we look at a factory, many things
are happening at the same time.
If we want to mine things on the internet
like social media, we will see that
many actors, many people are acting
concurrently at the same thing.
And you don't want to build one big
transition system to capture this.
Also if we look at complex machines,
like X-ray machines, they
are composed of many components that are
interacting and are working concurrently.
So concurrency is very important.
So should the process discovery
notation that we are using,
should it be able to capture
concurrency compactly?
Probably yes.
If we look at processes that
have these types of behavior.
But if we want to capture
concurrency are there
also higher level constructs
that we should also capture?
Like for example OR-joins and
cancellations.
And these are the things that we
will elaborate on in later lectures.
So let's go back to the case of
concurrency and the OR-joins.
First we look at concurrency, and I ask
you a question which is very much related
to things that we have seen before when
we were talking about workflow nets and
Petri nets and reachability graphs.
So, suppose that we have a process that
has a start activity an end activity, and
k activities that are concurrently in
between the start and end activity.
So, my question to you is,
how many traces are possible.
And if we feed the Alpha algorithm
with all of these traces,
will it be able to discover such a model?
And what is the minimum number
of observations needed?
Please think about this.
The answer to the question is as follows.
So if we model these k parallel activities,
nobody will be surprised that
the process model looks like this, and the
Alpha algorithm is able to discover it.
If we look at the number of different,
sequences allowed by this model,
it's easy to compute and here you can see
the numbers for different values of k.
So the moment that k becomes bigger,
many different traces are possible.
The Alpha algorithm does not need
to observe all of these traces.
In principal, k times k minus 1
observations are sufficient.
What do I mean by that?
If an activity b1 can be followed by b3,
we should observe that at least once.
And so in this model k times k minus 1
is the number of observations that we
need to see.
And in a single trace they can be
already multiple observations.
Let's take a look at another
question involving an OR-join.
Suppose that we have again k parallel
activities but these are all optional.
So they can be skipped.
The questions are: is the Alpha algorithm
able to discover this process and
how many traces are possible
let's say again for k is ten.
To answer this question,
let us first take a look at a model
that captures this type of behavior.
We see k concurrent
activities in the middle, and
they all have a so-called tau
transition associated to it.
That allows us to bypass that activity.
So this models the behavior
that was described.
The alpha algorithm is
unable to discover this
model because the Alpha algorithm is
unable to detect silent transitions.
It will create a model.
For this event log, that is incorrect.
How many traces are there?
That number is incredible.
And here you can see for
different values of k,
what the corresponding number
of possible traces is.
So these numbers are incredible.
And you can imagine that, if you would
like to represent this behavior as
a transition system,
it would look like a big bag of spaghetti.
Incredibly complicated, but
as the Petri net model looks very simple.
So, if we would like to
discover concurrency or
OR-joins we should have a representation
that can represent these behaviors easily.
Otherwise your discovery
technique will be,
not able to capture that
behavior that you're looking for.
The discovery process
is guided by the bias.
That is the important
message of this lecture.
So let us take a look at some examples
that we have seen in the past, and
that we now can relate to,
to this problem.
So we assume that our representational
bias is workflow-nets with unique labels.
So they cannot be two
transitions with the same label.
And we are given this event log.
Now think of a perfect discovery
algorithm as long as it is using
a representational bias that only allows
for work flow nets with unique labels.
Then, there is no technique that
actually can discover this model for
this event log.
The Petri net that is able to
reflect behavior well is shown here.
But you can see that the e
activity is duplicated.
There are two e's, and only by duplicating
e, we get a process model that fits well
in all the four quality dimensions with
respect to the log that we used as input.
So if we require that we need to
have a work flow net with unique labels we
are unable to find this desirable model.
Let's take a look at another example.
Here we have a log.
Acd and bce are frequent traces.
Suppose now that we have a representation
that does not allow for indirect or
long term dependencies.
So, we can only connect two activities if
one is directly influencing the other.
And in this model this is not the case,
because the choice between a and
b is influencing the choice between d and
e.
If a happens then d will happen later and
not e.
But a and
e are never following one another.
The model that describes this
behavior well is shown here.
And you can see that there is a dependency
between a and d, and b and e.
Although these two pairs of activities
never followed one another.
So, a representation
that does not allow for
indirect dependencies will be unable
to discover this particular model.
So, the representational bias matters a
lot if we are discovering process models.
It is impact to search space
of the discovery process.
One point that I would
like to make very clear
is that the visualization of
the discovered model to the end user
is something completely different than
the internal representational bias.
Using while searching for
a suitable process model.
You can always use one
technique during discovery, and
then visualize it in the notation
that people would like to use.
That is why later we will talk about
the BPMN notation as a notation that
people would often like to see.
But it's a notation that is rarely used
in the discovery algorithm itself.
So these conversions are easy.
So here you see, for
example, the model discovered
using using the alpha algorithm.
You have seen that before.
And we can take such Petri nets and
automatically convert it to a BPMN
diagram as you can here in ProM.
So the visualization of what we show
to the end user does not need to the be
same as the representation
that was used internally.
Much more important than what kind of
flavor of visualization you are using.
Is to realize that process
discovery is a difficult problem.
And that the choice of
representational bias is important.
For finding the right model,
not the right visualization.
A problem that we have mentioned before is
that we do not have any negative examples,
which is making discovery challenging.
Also the search space has a very
complicated structure there are constructs
like concurrency, loops, OR-splits,
OR-joins, cancellations.
This makes things very difficult and
we only see a fraction of the behavior
that is actually possible.
There is also a very unclear relationship
between the size of the model and
the behavior.
A smaller model may actually allow for
much more traces than a larger model.
But also the relationship
can hold in the other way.
That the larger model has much more
behavior than the smaller model.
This is making discovery difficult.
So a careful consideration of
the representational bias is key
to discovering the right process model.
If you are interested in
reading more about this,
please take a look at these two chapters.
That will provide you with more examples.
Thank you for watching this lecture.
See you next time.
[MUSIC]