[MUSIC]
Today we focus on BPMN, a notation
used to model business processes.
The BPMN notation is widely
used to document processes and
is similar to UML activity diagrams,
event-driven process chains,
YAWL models, and many other notations.
These all have in common
that there can be AND-,
XOR-,
and OR-splits and joins.
Given their widespread use,
we often need map discovered process
models to notations similar to BPMN.
This explains the focus of this lecture.
In the last lecture, we looked at
different process modeling notations and
the impact that they have
on the discovery process.
So for an example, we discussed
a notion of representational bias as
something being very important
of process discovery.
There are many different
notations that one can use.
So Petri nets,
transition systems, etcetera.
Today we will focus on BPMN, not so
much as a representational bias, but
more as a notation that people in practice
often use to visualize process models.
So Business Process Model and
Notation, as is the official term,
is also known as
the Business Process Modelling Notation.
In this lecture, we will simply
refer to it as the BPMN notation.
BPMN emerged in 2004.
And it is at this point and
time an OMG standard.
And here you can see some
references if you would like to
see some more information.
It is highly relevant, because it
is supported by many vendors and
used by many people in industry.
That's why we often want to convert
our results to this notation.
On the other hand, there is nothing new.
It is very similar to UML
activity diagrams and
event-driven process chains as we
will see later in this lecture.
Typically, only a small subset is being
considered, and we will do the same here.
So what are the notational
elements of a BPMN diagram?
We have tasks or activities,
we have splits and
joints, we have AND-splits,
XOR-splits, AND-joins, and XOR-joins.
Just like we have seen before.
There are also other constructs such
as the OR-split and the OR-join.
And we will look at these
constructs in more detail.
A BPMN diagram starts with the start
event, it ends with an end event,
and there can be other types of events.
For example, events triggered by a clock
or events triggered by a message.
There also more advanced
constructs like the deferred choice.
So, here you see a pattern where after
x there is a choice between y and z.
And, there is a race between a clock and
a message.
If the message is received before
a particular point in time we do z,
otherwise we will do y.
So, let us take a look at an example.
So here you see a BPMN model with
a corresponding notational element.
So, first of all we have the start and
the end event.
Very clear in this diagram.
Then we have the XOR-splits.
We also have XOR-joins,
this case three of them.
We have an AND-split and
an AND-join as are indicated here.
And this is how we can model
this particular process.
We have seen this example model before,
but it's important to realize that
just like Petri nets, BPMN models
have also a token-based semantics.
So, we can replay this process model for
a particular scenario.
So, we first execute activity a,
then we do the AND-splits.
We go to the XOR-split.
And after that we do d, then we do c.
We first have an OR-join.
Then we have an AND-join,
we synchronize the two signals.
And we can do e.
After doing e, we decide that we
have to go through another loop.
So we execute activity f.
Bring the model back to state
before activities in the middle.
We do a b, we do a d,
we do an e again, and
now we choose the path h
leading to the final state.
So this is one run of the model, and
of course this model allows for
infinitely many behaviors.
Now we take this model and
we have changed the AND-split,
XOR-split, XOR-join, AND-join groups of
gateways by so-called OR-splits and
OR-join gateway.
Indicated with the yellow here.
So, still the original
behavior is possible, but
we can, of the three activities in the
middle, we can take any subset of them.
And so we can execute all three of them.
We can execute two of these three
activities or just one of them.
So most difficult is
the notion of an OR-join.
When can we move on from an OR-join?
The informal semantics is that you
wait until all the work has been done.
In other words there is no need for
any further synchronizations.
So to make this more clear it helps
to look at concrete examples.
Even though they are a bit abstract.
So here we have a
process model where we first do an a,
then we start three parallel paths
one involving b, one involving c,
the other one involving
a choice between d and e.
Then we do an OR-join and
finally we do an f.
So you should now be
able to understand what
the traces are that
are allowed by this model.
So please think about how many traces
are possible in this BPMN diagram.
The answer is 12.
There are 12 possible traces.
First of all,
we have to take a choice between d or e,
and then we execute the three activities.
That can be done in any or other, so
we have 3 times 2 times 1 multiplied by 2,
the choice between d and e.
So, in total
there are twelve possible traces,
and here you can see them.
So the OR-join has a semantics where
we wait until everything has finished.
What should happen before.
But it is unknown what the exact
number of synchronizations is.
Here the synchronization is
always three out of four.
But that does not need to be the case.
Let's take a look at another model, and
now I ask you the question of soundness.
We have defined soundness
very precisely for
workflow nets, but
of course you can also define them for
other notations like the BPMN notation
that have a well defined start and end.
Is this model sound?
The answer is no.
There are many potential deadlocks.
Here you see the deadlock where,
after doing a, there is an OR-split.
So we can do b, and c, and d.
But we can also just do b, or
just do b and d as is indicated here.
So if we choose to do b and d but
not c, in that case we cannot
synchronize three flows.
Where as the gateway
before f requires that on
all four of the incoming signals,
there will be a token.
So this is yeah, this construct
does not make a lot of sense here
because typically you would like to
combine an END-split with an END-join or
an OR-split with an OR-join.
And here that is not the case.
So there are many deadlocks here.
We can take a look at this BPMN
model which has a more complicated
combination of of gateways,
is this model sound or not?
The answer is, no.
If you look at all
the behavior of this model,
there are several potential deadlocks.
If you look carefully at the diagram,
you will see that c and
e should happen together or
d and f should happen together.
If that is not the case, then you
will run into a deadlock trying to
synchronize flows which
cannot be synchronized.
So this is one possible deadlock
where you do the c and f and
then you cannot synchronize,
or you do d and e.
And then you also run into a deadlock.
There are also behaviors
that are possible.
So here you can see some traces that
indeed lead from beginning to end.
For example,
we can do first a followed by c.
And then at the bottom,
we need to do b followed by e.
Then we can synchronize both flows and
do g at the end.
And so there are also several good traces,
but this model also has deadlocks.
As I said at the beginning,
the BPMN notation is very comparable to
UML activity diagrams, or
to more classical notations like the so
called event-driven process chains,
simply referred to as EPCs.
What you see here in this
diagram is an EPC which has
exactly the same behaviour as the BPMN
model that we showed at the beginning.
So what are the notational
elements of an EPC diagram?
We have functions that corresponds
to activities in a BPMN diagram or
activities in the way that
we have spoken about before.
You have connectors, they correspond
to gateways in the BPMN notation.
And again we have XOR, AND, and
OR, also the inclusive of OR
to model the same types of behavior as
what we have seen in the BPMN notation.
The OR-join deserves
some special attention.
And to illustrate this a bit that
this is a difficult concept and
that you should be very careful about it,
I'm going to show you a paradox.
What you see here is that there
is one EPC diagram having two OR-joins.
And remember that an understanding of an
OR-join is that everything that has been
done before, has been done.
In other words, no tokens may arrive.
So if you look at this initial situation,
where there are two tokens in front of
these two OR-joins, the question
is can additional tokens arrive
through these two other inputs
that these two OR-joins have?
Well, suppose that you say that
is not the case, then one
OR-join should block and because of
symmetry the other should also block.
So both should block, but
if they both block that means that
you will never receive the second signal,
so the OR-join should not have waited.
So you create a contradiction.
If you block,
you should not have blocked.
So okay, so blocking is not an option.
So now we can say, okay.
If one is not blocked, then by symmetry
the other one should also not be blocked.
So they both can go.
But if they both go, then there will be
signals on the OR-joins
of the other input.
So this is again a wrong
choice because we
should have waited because there
was still a token arriving.
So due to symmetry, you can see,
clearly see that there is a paradox
in which all the choices are wrong.
So this is illustrated that you
should be very careful when
interpreting these OR-joins.
And it also shows
the complexity of some of
these process modeling notations
like the BPMN notation.
What I stressed already
before is visualization of
the discovered models is different
from the representational bias.
So often, we convert to a BPMN
model to make a model that
people would like to see and it is
unrelated to the representations that I
used internally by the process
discovering techniques.
There are a few miners that
work directly on BPMN models.
Most of the miners will discover Petri
nets, causal nets, process trees,
heuristic nets, and all kinds of
other notations that are suitable for
process discovery and only towards
the end they are converted to BPMN.
Sometimes the conversion is a bit lossy,
that you generalize the model a bit, or
make a bit more specific.
Here you see a screenshot
of the inductive miner,
that provides a visualizer that shows
the process tree as a BPMN model,
so that people can more easily
understand what it represents.
This concludes this lecture.
I hope that you now understand
more of the BPMN notation that was
already introduced in
chapter two of the book.
Thank you for watching,
and hope to see you soon.
[MUSIC]