[MUSIC]
Welcome to this lecture of the course on
Process Mining: Data Science in Action.
Today we will learn about
dependency graphs and causal nets.
These are important because mining
algorithms like the Heuristic Miner
are based on them.
In earlier lectures, we have seen many
different types of process models.
Sometimes we talk about a Tower
of Babel because there are so
many process models to choose from.
But the choice of process models
is very important during mining.
This, we discussed elaborately when
we talked about representational bias
of process mining.
Today we will focus on two representations
which are used internally during mining.
By algorithms like
the heuristic mining algorithm.
So the first representation that we
will talk about are dependency graphs.
So, dependency graphs
are very important to
get the causal structure
of a process model.
And, this is often used as input for
all kind of algorithms that look for
more refined representations.
Here you see an example
of a dependency graph.
It is just a graph with arcs and nodes.
All the nodes correspond to activities.
All the arcs correspond
to causal dependencies.
And you can think of a causal dependency
as a relationship between two activities
that is directed, where one is
triggering or enabling the other one.
Arcs will be annotated with numbers,
these can represent frequencies,
these can represent confidence,
how certain we
are that there is a particular
causality between these two activities.
So the challenge of building
such a dependency graph is that
we need to deal with concurrency.
So activities can be
interleafed in many ways, but
that doesn't mean that they
causally depend on each other.
So this is the challenge
that is very important.
The graphs that we are looking at
now have no executable semantics.
It's not like a petri net that,
based on such a model,
there is a clear set of traces that is
possible according to a certain semantics.
In other words,
if there are multiple ingoing and
outgoing arcs, there is no clear AND
or XOR semantics.
One can think of this as the input and
output behavior as a fuzzy fight
version of the OR-join and OR-split
without having a very clear semantics.
Sometimes you need one input.
Sometimes you need two inputs.
So we interpret them in a very loose way.
Without associating any
executable semantics to it.
So, let's relate this to some of the
representations that we have seen before.
We all have seen diagrams like this.
The causal footprint.
The arrows in such a matrix correspond
to the arcs in the dependency graphs.
So here you see the mapping.
From such a footprint
to a dependency graph.
We can also look at the Petri net,
so here you see a Petri net.
And in essence,
if I would remove all the places, and
just connect the activities directly as
they were connected through the places.
But now after removing the places, then
we also get a kind of dependency graph.
So a Petri net can be translated
into a dependency graph, but
we lose lots of the semantics.
Here's another example.
Again, we take a look at the footprint.
We look at the arrows that
are in the footprint matrix, and
they correspond to the arrows
in the dependency graph.
If we look at the corresponding Petri
net, again we can remove the places, and
we get the corresponding dependency graph.
So this gives an intuitive idea
of what the dependency graph is.
It is something that has no semantics,
but that tries to capture causalities.
Why are these important?
These are important because all
kinds of mining algorithms,
start from such a representation.
They are using it in a first phase or
it is the final product that they show.
So one can think of fuzzy models and
the models in disco as dependency graphs.
So there's no precise semantics.
There are many ways to create them.
There are many algorithms to
create such dependency graphs.
And they are often based on heuristics.
So we will talk about later, we will talk
about the specific way of learning them,
but there are many ways to do it actually.
Dependency graphs have a fuzzy semantics.
C-nets take these dependency graphs and
add a bit more semantics,
but not by making them executable,
but more sketching the possibilities.
So what you see here is an example
of a causal net.
It's a dependency graph annotated
with so-called input and
output bindings that are showing
what the possible behaviors are,
without associating
an executable semantics to it.
So why do we talk about C-nets?
Well, many of the process mining
algorithms that can deal with noise and
other advanced concepts, they use
a representation very similar to C-nets.
And the primary example that we will
use here is the heuristics miner.
It fits very well with
mainstream languages.
They often talk about ors and ands in
a more elaborate way than what is possible
in Petri net model or a transition
system, so there is a nice fit.
Using C-nets we are able to mobile XOR's,
AND's, and
very important OR's but
we do so without adding any other
modeling elements like silent or
duplicate transitions in a Petri net.
Last but not least,
we use C-net's to avoid non-signed models.
So the semantics are in such a way that
we avoid having deadlocks in them.
So the semantics are very loose,
as I explained before.
The moment of choice is not fixed.
We just look in hindsight.
Does a trace fit into this model?
Is there a possible explanation
according to this model?
That whether trace behavior
fits with the model behavior.
So if you look in the process mining book,
you can see a formal description
of this type of notation.
It's not important that you
are able to understand it now, but
if you would like to read the details,
you can do so in chapter two.
What is important is that there is one
initial activity that is a final activity,
that there are these dependencies,
these connections between
the different elements and
there are inputs and output bindings.
So the definition of a binding can
be formalized, the definition of
a state can be formalized and
based on these notions we can talk
about sequences that are possible
according to such a C-net.
But, as I said, I will try to
explain it in a more intuitive way.
So there is one start activity,
in this case the start activity is a, and
this will be the one that happened first.
And a can only happen in
the first position of a trace.
Not in any later positions.
This a is a start activity and
there are two output bindings so
after a there are two possibilities.
We can either do b and
d or we can do c and d.
Yeah?
That's the idea.
So after executing a, we need to
choose one of these output bindings,
and here you can see that
the choice was made to do b and d.
And if we take this binding it means that
we are creating the obligation that in
the future b will need to happen and
d will need to happen.
So, you're creating obligations and
the input bindings are able to
remove these obligations, whereas
the output bindings are creating them.
So, after b occurs we have removed
the obligation between a and b.
And we have created
an obligation between b and e.
So now, in the future,
we know that we will have to do e.
And we will need to match it to
one of the input bindings of e.
But e is not yet enabled.
The next thing that will
happen is that d occurs.
We remove an obligation
on the incoming side and
we create an obligation
on the outgoing side.
In the next step, we execute e and
we remove two obligations.
So this is like an AND-join, but
not off all three incoming arcs,
just from two of them.
So you can think of this as an OR.
We removed two obligations,
and we created a new one, and
the new obligation says that g
will need to happen in the future.
Then we execute g, we remove
an obligation, we create an obligation
until we can do the final step.
Where we execute the end activity,
which may only happen at the very end,
where we again, remove an obligation.
So this was one run of the model.
So what are the rules of the game?
We start always with the start activity,
and that can happen only once.
At the end there is always
a designated end activity and
the activities in between cannot
be the start and end activities.
Obligations are like tokens and
they need to be there in order to
be consumed by input bindings.
And at the end there should
be no remaining obligations.
At the moment of choice is not fixed.
Only in hindsight we need to find
an explanation that has these
properties that are listed here.
So let's talk more about binding.
So activity x in this diagram.
Has two input bindings and
three output bindings and
one possible execution of this
activity x is highlighted here in red.
That we have an input
binding involving two,
earlier activities and, so, there need
to be two, obligations from before.
Before we can do x.
And x is creating two
obligations into the future.
And so
now you should look at this diagram.
You should think of how
many bindings are there.
How many bindings are possible
in this activity.
That has two input bindings and
three output bindings.
Well the answer is very simple.
There are of course six possible bindings
because you can take any combination of
an input binding with
any of the output bindings.
So you get 2 times 3 and
here in red all the six possible
combinations are highlighted.
So, it is very important to see that we
only consider valid binding sequences.
So we only look at executions
that go from beginning to end.
Where each time you take an input binding
all the obligations are present and
at the end all the obligations
have been consumed and
there are no remaining obligations.
Then we have a valid binding sequence,
and we only consider those.
So, this way we avoid talking
about deadlocks and other things.
We just talk about the behavior
of such a model in
terms of it's valid binding sequences.
So the moment of choice is not relevant.
There is no executable semantics.
It is just an explanation
of possible traces.
So we talk about the fact that the
semantics are declarative in a way that
they only describe possible
paths without telling when which
decision was being made.
Let's try to relate this to workflow
nets or Petri nets in general.
If we take a C-net.
A causal net.
We can easily translate it into
a Petri net that allows for
the behavior that we see in the C-net.
And the translation
is straightforward.
We just take all the output bindings.
And convert them into silent transitions.
We take all the input bindings,
and create them.
We create also silent transitions for
them.
And then we connect where the arcs are,
we add places connecting
the output bindings of one transition to
the input binding of another transition.
That's the way that it works
and I think when you look at this picture.
It is fairly straightforward.
If you look at this workflow net, you will
see that there may be many bad behaviors,
like deadlocks and
all kinds of other anomalies.
But in terms of a C-net,
we do not talk about it.
Because we only consider the valid
binding sequences to avoid.
That our discovery techniques will
continuously generate models that we
consider to be bad because
they have deadlocks.
We have a more loose semantics
exploiting this behavior.
So how do work flow nets and
C-nets relate to each other?
Every valid binding sequence of the C-net
corresponds to a firing sequence
of the workflow net that goes from
the initial marking to the final marking.
We can call this a valid firing sequence.
Every execution of the workflow net,
starting in the initial marking and
ending in the final marking corresponds
to a valid binding sequence.
But in the petri net,
in the workflow net there may
be many executions that do not
correspond to a valid binding sequence,
because they end up in a deadlock or
unable to reach the final state.
So, when we talk about C-nets,
we only consider valid binding sequences.
When we talk about workflow nets.
We also are confronted with deadlocks and
livelocks that need to be considered.
A workflow net does not need to be sound,
but this type of soundness is
not required for C-nets because we
only use their declarative semantics.
So, let's see whether you now understand
the declarative semantics of C-net.
So here you see a C-net.
So how many valid binding
sequences are there in this C-net?
So take a minute to think about this.
The answer is that there are 12
valid binding sequences.
For example, we can decide to do just b.
We can decide to do just c.
We can decide to do b and d, but
then there are two possible combinations,
because we can do first b and
then d, or in the other order.
The same holds for c and d.
We can also do these two but they can
do be done in two different orders and
we have the possibility to do b, c, and
d like all three of them they
can be done in any order so
that again yields an extra six
possible binding sequences.
So, that brings the total to 12.
Here you see one of these
binding sequences highlighted.
And so there is one binding sequence that,
creates the trace ADCE, and
here you can see the bindings that
are involved highlighted in red.
So the work flow interpretation
of a C-net, can be given
by converting bindings into silent
transitions, indicated in black.
That do not leave a trail
in the event logs,
that have a behavior that is invisible but
that provide a very easy translation.
But as said before the
corresponding workflow net
does not need to be sound.
So we only consider valid sequences.
Here you see the relationship
between the output bindings and
the silent transitions modeling.
All these possible combinations.
Here if you look at the input
bindings of the end activity again we
see that there are five silent transitions
corresponding to these bindings.
The workflow-net may have deadlocks, but
we don't consider them if we talked about
the semantics of the corresponding C-nets.
C-nets are remarkably expressive just by
the different interpretation
of their semantics.
So here you see an example of
a C-net that has a behavior that
cannot be expressed in
an ordinary petri net.
Why is this the case?
If you look carefully,
you will see that b, c,
and d can happen an unbounded
number of times.
So it can happen one million times.
But it is ensured by the model
that they all will happen
exactly the same number of times and
still the order is preserved.
So you can not do first five
c's when you only did four b's.
That's why these
causalities are preserved.
And one can not express this in a
in a classical Petri net.
So let's look at the question.
If we look at this more complicated C-net,
you see here four binding sequences.
Which of these four binding
sequences is not a valid one?
The answer is that trace b does not
correspond to a valid binding sequence.
And how can one see that?
Well there are two reasons why
one can see that this
doesn't correspond
to a valid binding sequence.
The second c is executed
before the second b,
which is not possible
according to the C-net.
Also, if we see the first d,
then it cannot be
that after the first d there are still
b's, by the nature of the net.
And these two properties are violated, so
this is not a, valid binding sequence.
Many plug-ins in ProM use C-nets,
or some notation that is very similar
to C-nets like heuristic nets and all
kinds of other terms that are being used.
So here you see a C-net and
there are different visualizations here,
we do not see the AND's and
the XOR's etcetera.
One can make them graphical and so
here you see a BPMN like
notation showing a C-net.
But we can also take these nets and
convert them to Petri nets and
now you can see the bindings all
represented in terms of silent
transitions as I've shown before.
So in the next two lectures we
will talk about heuristic mining,
where we use C-nets and dependency graphs.
So there will be one lecture devoted
to learning dependency graphs, and
there will be one lecture
devoted to causal nets.
If you would like to learn more,
in chapter two,
we spoke about many different
types of process models.
Now in chapter six, we are focusing
on more advanced mining techniques.
And heuristic mining is one of these
more advanced techniques that we
are discussing in the next two lectures.
Thank you for watching this lecture.
See you next time.
[MUSIC]