[MUSIC]
Welcome to this lecture.
In week two,
we focused on process models and
one concrete process discovery algorithm.
In week three, we will discuss more
advanced process discovery techniques.
However before doing so,
we first discuss the four key quality
dimensions for process mining.
We will see that there are trade-offs
between fitness, simplicity, precision and
generalization, thus making process
discovery a very challenging task.
Measuring the quality of discovered
process models is very important.
What we will see in this lecture is
that there are different forces, so
we can view model quality
from different angles.
But let us start by looking
at what is the problem?
So we have a process that
leaves trails in event logs.
Using these event logs,
we can discover process models or
we can do conformance checking.
However, what this picture shows is that
we would like to say something about
the relationship between the process
model and the real process.
But we cannot do because
the real process is unknown.
You can only say something
with respect to event data.
So, the foundational question
that we would like to answer,
is the process model a correct
reflection of the real process and
we can only do so by looking at
the event data that we happen to see.
So for people that have a background in
data mining, you can think of this as
a classification problem, but we will
see that it is not as easy as this.
If you think about classification, you
try to construct a confusion matrix and
in a confusion matrix, you indicate first,
what the true positives are.
So in the context of process discovery,
these are the traces that are possible in
the model, and
also possible in the real process.
We also can define the true negatives.
These are the traces that are not
possible in the model and
also not possible in the real process
that we are trying to analyze.
These are good things.
Bad things are false positives.
Traces possible in the model but
not possible in the real process, and
the reverse, false negatives, traces
that are not possible in the model but
that are possible in the real process.
So we would like to see lots of TPs and
TNs, and just a few FPs and FNs.
And in the confusion matrix,
we can kind of analyze the distribution
over these four categories.
So we can also view the confusion
matrix in a different way, as a so
called Venn diagram.
What you see here, this square represents
all possible behavior in any process.
In the space of all possible behaviors
we can highlight, here in red,
the real behavior of the process.
So the behaviors that are possible
according to the real process,
that we do not know.
The green part indicates
the model behavior.
So what is possible according to the model
that we have made by hand, or that we
have discovered, the bigger the overlap
between these ovals, the better it is.
So true positives are in the overlap
between real behavior and
modeled behavior.
False negatives, we would like
to avoid that, because this is
behavior that can happen in reality, but
is not possible according to the model.
We also would like to avoid
having many false positives,
things possible according to the model,
but not possible in reality.
So if you think about this in the context
of data mining or information retrieval,
once you have these notions,
you can talk about things like recall.
So recall is TP divided by TP plus FN.
In other words, if there are no
false negatives, recall will be one.
It will be perfect.
We can also look at precision.
TP divided by TP plus FP, so
if there are no false positives, the
precision is one, and that is excellent.
So if these two numbers are high, it means
that the model has a very good quality,
and that is why people often
use recall and precision and
you can also look at the F1 score,
which is based on these two numbers.
So let's try to apply that in
the context of process mining and
if you try to do that, then you very
quickly see that this is not possible.
Why is it not possible?
You know what the behaviors are that
are allowed by the model that you
have discovered, but
you do not know what the real behavior
is that the real process allows for.
You only see a small set of examples and
based on that,
you would like to make conclusions.
So if you look at the formulas,
you can simply not apply them.
If you look at the event log which
is also indicated in this diagram,
you can define a kind of metric and
that's what we call here replay fitness.
Later on,
we talk about conformance checking.
We will discuss this topic
in much more detail, but
the basic idea is that you look at
TP prime divided by TP prime plus
FN prime where these things are based on
the behavior that we saw in the event log.
What you can see is if all the behavior
in the event log is possible according to
the model,
then you have a replay fitness of one.
If nothing is possible,
then you can see that this metric will
indeed indicate that there is a problem.
So it is difficult to apply classical
techniques like as precision or
recall into this setting, but
there are many more challenges.
Related to the problem that
I discused before is that we
have no negative examples.
The event log will never
tell what was not possible.
We can only see the things
that have happened.
The log contains typically, a very
tiny fraction of the possible traces.
So we should avoid to overfit the data
set that we are analyzing.
We would like to distinguish
not between cases that fit and
cases that do not fit,
instead, we would also like to
reason about the fact that one case
is fitting better than another case.
And so, we should distinguish
between these different situations.
If a model has a loop,
like a Petri net with the self loop,
then it will have infinitely
many possible traces.
So you cannot simply count traces because
all the formulas that I showed before,
do not make any sense.
Related to this topic is what
I call Murphy's laws for
process mining, that says that anything
is possible if you wait long enough.
So it is not an interesting question
whether something is possible.
If you wait long enough, it will happen.
What is much more important is to
think about the likelihood and
the model should only indicate things
that have a certain level of likelihood.
So this leads to the situation that
we have to deal with four forces.
If you look at a plane,
there are these four forces that you
see here that keep a plane in the air.
If we look at process mining,
there are similarly four types of forces.
Fitness, we've already
discussed that a bit before.
But, it's not only fitness.
It's not only important whether the
observed behavior is possible according to
the model.
The model should also be as simple
as possible, Occam's razor.
The model should be precise.
It should not allow for
all kinds of behavior unrelated to
the event data that we have seen.
And at the same time,
it should not be overfitting.
So it should be general enough.
So, process mining needs to
find a balance between these
four forces that you see here.
Well it's best to explain
this using a small log.
What you see here are traces and
the corresponding frequency.
So the first trace acdeh
happened 455 times.
The second one, 191, etcetera.
So we can see that in total,
we have observed 21 different traces.
And together if we
count also the fact that a certain
trace can happen multiple times,
there were almost 1400 traces, but
there were only 21 different ones.
So, what is now a good model for
such a log?
Here I show you a model that looks okay.
Given this data set it seems to be
very related to the process model.
We can now look again at the dimensions
that I mentioned before.
So every trace in the log
fits into this model.
I can replay it from beginning
to end without any problems.
The model is also simple.
There are not too many nodes and,
and connections.
We can also look at
the notion of precision.
And if we look at precision, we will
see that this model seems to be okay.
Last but not least,
we can look at generalization.
Is it general enough?
And it is not overfitting
on the 21 cases.
Well, it is a bit difficult to argue that
this model is good by not having
defined any metrics, but we can look at
some extreme cases of models that have
a problem in one of these four areas.
For example, this event log and
this model if we compare it,
we will see that the model is non-fitting,
only the most frequent trace fits.
All the other traces do
not fit into this model.
So it doesn't fit very well.
And so fitness is bad,
simplicity is good, precision is good.
It does not allow for
all kinds of behavior that we did not see.
Generalization is poor.
It is very likely that the next
observation will not fit into this model.
Let's take a look at
another extreme example.
This is what we call a flower model.
Apart from the initial activity and
the final two activities, anything can
happen in between any number of times.
So, this allows for many behaviors.
Also many behaviors that are completely
unrelated to what we have seen in the log.
And so for example,
we can have to trace a, b, b, b, g.
And if you look at the log, you will
agree with me that that is very unlikely.
So despite this problem,
the model has perfect fitness.
All of the traces can be
replayed from beginning to end.
It is also very simple,
but it lacks precision.
It is under-fitting the data set.
it allows for much more behavior
unrelated to what we have see before.
On the other hand, generalization is good.
So under-fitting models have a problem
with respect to precision in
a way the model allows for too much,
much more behavior than what we have seen.
This is an example of
an over-fitting model.
It has the the opposite problem.
What I did here is I just listed the 21
different traces that we have seen, and
we have to choose one of these 21 paths.
So if we take a look at this model,
we will see that the fitness is good.
All the observed behavior
fits into this model,
but it is far from simple,
it is very complicated.
It has a good precision.
It's not allowing for behavior completely
different from what we have seen, but
the key point here is that
generalization is poor.
The model just allows for
the example behavior that we have seen and
nothing more.
So we call this an over-fitting model and
a the definition of an over-fitting model
is that there is a high likelihood that
the next trace that we will observe
will actually not fit into the model.
So the model has a poor predictive power.
So let's see what this means
using some small examples and
I would like to ask you some
questions about these examples.
Consider this event log, where a,
c, e happen 77 times, b, c,
d 92 times and we have this model and
now, we compare these two.
Is the fitness of this model good or
bad with respect to this log?
The answer is that the fitness is bad.
Why is it bad?
None of the traces that we have seen in
the log is actually possible
according to this model.
So it's the model allows for
a, c, d, but not a, c, e.
The model allows for b, c,
e, but not for b, c, d.
So it's clear that the fitness
is bad in this example.
Let's take a look at another example.
Again, you can see an event log,
you can see a process model.
Is the precision good or bad?
The answer is, the precision is good.
Why is it good?
It is good because the model
does not allow for
free behavior very different from
what we have seen in the log.
So it's not underfitting.
Let's take a look at another model.
Look at the model now.
Is the precision good or bad?
The answer is that the precision is bad.
Why is it bad?
It allows for
all kinds of traces, very different
from the behavior that we have seen.
If you take a look at the event log,
it is very unlikely that we could do
ten c's in a row, whereas if we look at
this model, that is perfectly possible.
Another example.
Note that the traces now
are very infrequent.
So the question is, is this model general
enough, if we compare it to the event log?
The answer is no.
Generalization is bad.
We have seen only five example traces.
So it is very likely that if we would
take a look at the sixth trace that
it would have a behavior different
from what we have seen before.
Generalization is a very difficult notion
because it reasons about behavior.
That we did not see yet.
Think about the discussion that we
had at the beginning of this lecture.
Another example, we see these traces.
Is generalization good or bad?
The answer is generalization is good.
The model is not overfitting and we see
all of these things happened frequently.
So there's no reason to believe
that the next observation will be
very different from what is
currently allowed by the model.
Let's take a look at
the notion of simplicity.
We have again an event log and a model.
Is the model simple enough?
The answer is no.
Simplicity is bad because the model
is overly complicated and
specific for this particular log.
So we have seen that b can be repeated
up to four times in our example log,
but it could easily happen that
it is repeated five or six times.
Simplicity, is it good or bad if you
look at this model and this event log?
In this case, simplicity is good.
The model is very simple and
is not overfitting or
overly complicated compared
to what we have seen before.
So this is using the principle
of Occam's razor.
If there is a simple explanation, then we
choose the simple explanation rather
than a complicated large involved model.
So in this lecture, I've shown you
that there are these four forces, and
I hope that you can see that it is
not easy to define them precisely.
In later courses, we will provide metrics
to quantify these different dimensions and
we will mostly focus on fitness, but
all four of them are very important.
The modeling language that we are using
is an element which is very important and
in later lectures,
we will start looking at the so
called representational
bias of process mining.
So, whether the model allows for
concurrency, OR-joins,
cancellation, priorities,
duplicate activities is very important and
it is related to the four forces
that we have seen in this lecture.
If you would like to read more
about these four forces and
see more examples,
please take a look at these two chapters.
Thank you for watching this lecture,
see you next time.
[MUSIC]